<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="forest.xsl"?>
<tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5033</anchor>  <addr>sga1</addr><route>sga1.xml</route>    <title>SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group</title>   </frontmatter> <mainmatter><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5034</anchor>  <addr>sga1-introduction</addr><route>sga1-introduction.xml</route>    <title>Introduction</title>   </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
  In the first section of this introduction, we give some details about the contents of the present volume; in the second, about the entirety of the <em>Séminaire de Géométrie Algébrique du Bois-Marie</em>, of which the present volume constitutes the first tome.
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5035</anchor>  <addr>sga1-introduction-1</addr><route>sga1-introduction-1.xml</route>     <number>1</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    The present volume details the fundamentals of a theory of the fundamental group in algebraic geometry, from the &quot;Kroneckerian&quot; point of view, which allows us to treat the case of an algebraic variety, in the usual sense, and that of a ring of integers of a number field, for example, on an equal footing.
    This point of view can only be expressed in a satisfactory manner in the language of schemes, and we will freely use this language, as well as the main results stated in the first three chapters of the <em>Éléments de Géométrie Algébrique</em> by J. Dieudonné and A. Grothendieck (cited as &quot;EGA&quot;).
    The study of this present volume of the <em>Séminaire de Géométrie Algébrique du Bois-Marie</em> does not require any other knowledge of algebraic geometry, and can thus serve as an introduction to the current techniques of algebraic geometry to a reader who wishes to familiarise themselves with them.
  </p><p>
    Exposés I to XI of this book are a textual reproduction, practically unchanged, of the mimeographed notes from the oral seminar, which were distributed by the <em>Institut des Hautes Études Scientifiques</em>.
    (As well as the notes of the following seminars. Since this method of distribution turned out to be impractical and inadequate in the long term, all the <em>Séminaire de Géométrie Algébrique du Bois-Marie</em> from now on will appear in book form, like the present volume.)
    We have restricted ourselves to adding some footnotes to the original text, correcting typos, and making an adjustment to terminology (notably, &quot;simple morphism&quot; being replaced with &quot;smooth morphism&quot;, which does not lead to the same confusion).
  </p><p>
    Exposés I to IV present the local notions of <em>étale</em> and <em>smooth</em> morphisms;
    they hardly ever use the language of schemes, as detailed in Chapter I of the <em>Éléments</em>.
    (A more complete study is now available in EGA IV, 17 and 18.)
    Exposé V presents the axiomatic description of the fundamental group of a scheme, which is useful even in the classical case where the scheme is simply the spectrum of a field, since we then find a strong and convenient reformulation of usual Galois theory.
    Exposés VI and VIII present the <em>theory of descent</em>, which has become more and more important in algebraic geometry over the past few years, and which could do the same in analytic geometry and in topology.
    We note that Exposé VII was not transcribed, but its contents can be found incorporated into an article by J. Giraud (&quot;Méthode de la Descente&quot;. <em>Bull. Soc. Math. France</em> <strong>2</strong> (1964), viii+150 p.).
    In Exposé IX, we study more specifically the theory of descent by étale morphisms, obtaining a systematic approach for Van Kampen type theorems for the fundamental group, which appear here as simple translations of theorems of descent.
    This essentially involves a calculation of the fundamental group of a connected scheme <tex>X</tex> endowed with a surjective and proper morphism (say, <tex>X' \to  X</tex>) in terms of the fundamental groups of the connected components of <tex>X'</tex> and of the fibre products <tex>X' \times _X X'</tex>, <tex>X' \times _X X' \times _X X'</tex>, and the homomorphisms between these groups induced by the canonical simplicial morphisms between the above schemes.
    Exposé X gives the theory of <em>specialisation of the fundamental group</em> for a proper and smooth morphism, with the most striking result being the determination (more or less) of the fundamental group of a smooth algebraic curve in characteristic <tex>p&gt;0</tex>, thanks to the known result obtained by transcendental methods in characteristic zero.
    <tex>Exposé XI</tex> gives some examples and addenda, including a cohomological version of Kummer's theory of coverings, as well as Artin--Schreier's.
    For other commentaries on the text, see the Foreword <ref addr="sga1-foreword" href="sga1-foreword.xml"/>, found after this Introduction.
  </p><p>
    Since the writing of the seminar in 1961, the language of <em>étale topology</em>, along with a corresponding cohomology theory, has been developed by M. Artin in collaboration with myself;
    it is detailed in tome 4 (&quot;Cohomologie étale des schémas&quot;) of the <em>Séminaire de Géométrie Algébrique</em>, which will appear in the same series as the present volume.
    This language, as well as the results that it has given up until now, give us a particularly supple tool for the study of the fundamental group, allowing us to better understand (and even improve upon) certain results given here.
    There will thus be a need to entirely rewrite the theory of the fundamental group from this point of view (in fact, all the key results so far appear in <em>loc. cit.</em>).
    This was what was planed for the chapter of <em>Éléments</em> dedicated to the fundamental group, which also had to cover many other ideas which could not find their place here (relying on the technique of resolution of singularities):
    calculation of the &quot;local fundamental group&quot; of a complete local ring in terms of a suitable resolution of singularities of the ring, local and global Künneth formulas for the fundamental group without any hypotheses of properness (cf. Exposé XIII), the results of M. Artin on the comparison of the local fundamental groups of an excellent Henselian local ring and of its completion (SGA 4 XIX).
    We also note the necessity of developing a theory of the fundamental group of a topos, which would simultaneously cover the ordinary topological theory, the semi-simplicial version, the &quot;profinite&quot; version developed in Exposé V, and the slightly more general pro-discrete version found in [SGA 3 X 7] (adapted to the case of non-normal and non-unibranch schemes).
    While we wait for such a rewriting of the whole theory, Exposé XIII, by Mme Raynaud, using the language and results of SGA 4, aims to show the part that we can extract in some typical questions, most notably generalising certain results of Exposé X to non-proper relative schemes.
    There we give, in particular, the structure of the &quot;prime at <tex>p</tex>&quot; fundamental group of a non-complete algebraic curve in arbitrary characteristic (which I announced in 1959, but for which a proof had not been published up until now).
  </p><p>
    Despite these numerous gaps and imperfections (as others would say: because of these gaps and imperfections), I think that the present volume could be useful for the reader who wishes to familiarise themselves with the theory of the fundamental group, as well as a work of reference, while we await the writing and appearance of a text that avoids the criticisms that I have just listed.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5036</anchor>  <addr>sga1-introduction-2</addr><route>sga1-introduction-2.xml</route>     <number>2</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    The present volume constitutes tome 1 of the <em>Séminaire de Géométrie Algébrique du Bois-Marie</em>, whose following volumes are intended to appear in the same series as this one.
    The aim of the <em>Séminaire</em>, parallel to the <em>Éléments de Géométrie Algébrique</em> by J. Dieudonné and A. Grothendieck, is to establish the fundamentals of algebraic geometry, following the points of view of the latter.
    The standard reference for all the volumes of the <em>Séminaire</em> consists of Chapters I, II, and III of <em>Éléments de Géométrie Algébrique</em> (cited as EGA I, II, and III), and we assume the reader to be have the education in commutative algebra and homological algebra that these chapters imply.
    (See the Introduction of EGA I for more precise details.)
    Furthermore, in each volume of the <em>Séminaire</em>, we will freely refer as needed to previous volumes of the same <em>Séminaire</em>, or to other chapters of <em>Éléments</em>, either already published or on the brink of being published.
  </p><p>
    Each <em>volume</em> of the <em>Séminaire</em> is based on a main subject, indicated in the title of the corresponding volume(s);
    the oral seminar generally lasts one academic year, sometimes more.
    The exposés within each volume of the <em>Séminaire</em> are generally in a logical order of dependence on one another;
    however, the different volumes of the <em>Séminaire</em> are largely logically independent of one another.
    So the volume &quot;Group schemes&quot; is largely logically independent of the two volumes of the <em>Séminaire</em> that come before it chronologically;
    however, it makes frequent reference to results of EGA IV.
    Here is the list of the volumes of the <em>Séminaire</em> that should appear (cited as SGA I to SGA 7 in what follows):
  </p><ul><li><strong>SGA 1.</strong>
      Étale covers and the fundamental group, 1960/61.
    </li>
    <li><strong>SGA 2.</strong>
      Local cohomology of coherent sheaves and local and global Lefschetz theorems, 1961/62.
    </li>
    <li><strong>SGA 3.</strong>
      Group schemes, 1963/64 (3 volumes, in collaboration with M. Demazure).
    </li>
    <li><strong>SGA 4.</strong>
      Topos theory and étale cohomology of schemes, 1963/64 (3 volumes, in collaboration with M. Artin and J.L. Verdier).
    </li>
    <li><strong>SGA 5.</strong>
      <tex>\ell</tex>-adic cohomology and <tex>L</tex>-functions, 1964/65 (2 volumes).
    </li>
    <li><strong>SGA 6.</strong>
      Intersection theory and the Riemann--Roch theorem, 1966/67 (2 volumes, in collaboration with P. Berthelot and L. Illusie).
    </li>
    <li><strong>SGA 7.</strong>
      Local monodromy groups in algebraic geometry.
    </li></ul><p>
    Three of these partial <em>Séminaires</em> have been written in <em>collaboration</em> with other mathematicians, who appear as coauthors on the covers of the corresponding volumes.
    As for the other active participants of the <em>Séminaire</em>, whose roles (from as much of an editorial point of view as a mathematical one) have grown over the years, the name of each participant appears at the top of the exposés for which they are responsible, either as speaker or as writer, and the list of those who appear in a given volume can be found on the flyleaf of the volume in question.
  </p><p>
    It is useful to give some precise remarks concerning the relation between the <em>Séminaire</em> and the <em>Éléments</em>.
    The latter was intended, in principle, to give an exposé of a set of ideas and techniques that were judged to be the most fundamental in Algebraic Geometry, as these ideas and techniques emerge all by themselves from the natural requirements of logical and aesthetic coherence.
    From this point of view, it was natural to consider the <em>Séminaire</em> as a preliminary version of the <em>Éléments</em>, destined to be included almost entirely, sooner or later, in the latter.
    This process had already somewhat started a few years ago, since Exposés I to IV of the current volume (SGA 1) are entirely covered by EGA IV, and Exposés VI to VIII should be, in some years, in EGA VI.
    However, given how the work in constructing the <em>Éléments</em> and the <em>Séminaire</em> is developing, and as the proportions of the two become more precise, the initial principle (that the <em>Séminaire</em> should be only a preliminary and provisional version) seems less and less realistic, for the reason (amongst others) of the limits imposed by the long-sighted nature of the length of the human life.
    Taking into account the care that is generally given to the writing of the various parts of the <em>Séminaire</em>, there will doubtless be no need to go back over them in the <em>Éléments</em> (or other treaties that would take over from it) until further progress in the writing process would allow us to make very substantial improvements, at the cost of rather big changes.
    This is the case as of now for the current seminar SGA 1, as we said above, and also for SGA 2 (thanks to recent results by Mme. Raynaud).
    However, nothing currently indicates that this will also be the case in the near future for any of the other parts mentioned above (SGA 3 to SGA 7).
  </p><p><em>[Trans.] We omit one paragraph from this translation since it simply describes the citation and cross-reference formatting of the book, which we do not precisely follow here.</em></p><p>
    Finally, for the ease of the reader, every time that it seems necessary, at the end of the volumes of the SGA we attach an index of notation and an index of terminology containing, if necessary, an English translation of the French terms used.
  </p><p>
    I want to add an extra-mathematical comment to this introduction.
    In the month of November, 1969, I discovered that the Institut des Hautes Études Scientifiques, where I have been a professor essentially since its founding, had been receiving subventions from the Ministère des Armées for three years.
    Already as a young researcher, I found it extremely regrettable how few qualms the majority of scientists had in agreeing to collaborate in one form or another with military institutions.
    My motivations back then were essentially of a moral nature, and thus not very likely to be taken seriously.
    Today they acquire a new force and dimension, given the danger of destruction of the human species threatened by the proliferation of military institutions and of the means of mass destruction that they posses.
    I have explained my thoughts on these problems, which are much more important than the advancement of any of the sciences (mathematics included), in more detail in other places;
    the reader can, for example, consult the article by G. Edwards in the Volume 1 of the journal <em>Survivre</em> (August, 1970), which gives a more detailed summary of these problems than I have done elsewhere.
    So I found myself working for three years at an institution even though it was, unbeknownst to me, participating in a financing model that I consider immoral and dangerous.
    (It goes without saying that the opinion that I express here is entirely my own, and not that of the publishing house Springer, which is editing this volume.)
    Being currently the only person to have this opinion amongst my colleagues at the IHES, which has condemned to fail my efforts to suppress military subventions from the IHES budget, I have taken the necessary decision to leave the IHES on the 30th of September, 1970, and to equally suspend all scientific collaboration with this institute for as long as it continues to accept such subventions.
    I have asked M. Motchane, the director of the IHES, for the IHES to abstain, starting from the 1st of October, 1970, from sharing mathematical texts of which I am an author, or which form part of the <em>Séminaire de Géométrie Algébrique du Bois-Marie</em>.
    As was mentioned above, the diffusion of this seminar will be undertaken by the publishing house Julius Springer, in the <em>Lecture Notes</em> series.
    I am happy to thank here Springer and Mr. K. Peters for the efficient and polite help that they have given me in making this publication possible, in particular for dealing with the typing of the photo-offset of new exposés added to old seminars, and of missing exposés in incomplete seminars.
  </p><p>
    I equally thank Mr. J.P. Delale, who had the thankless job of compiling the index of notation and the index of terminology.
  </p><p><em>Massy, August 1970.</em></p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5037</anchor>  <addr>sga1-foreword</addr><route>sga1-foreword.xml</route>    <title>Foreword</title>   </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
  Each of these written exposés covers the material of multiple consecutive oral exposés.
  It did not seem useful to make a note of the dates.
</p><p>
  Exposé VII, which is referenced at various points throughout Exposé VIII, has not been written by the speaker, who, in the oral conferences, was limited to outlining the language of descent in general categories, by working from a strictly utilitarian point of view and not entering into the logical difficulties that often arise due to this language.
  It seemed that a proper exposé of this language would go beyond the limits of these current notes, even if only due to length.
  For a proper exposé of the theory of descent, I refer the reader to an article in preparation by Jean Giraud.
  Whilst waiting for its appearance (it is now published: J. Giraud, “Méthode de la Descente”. <em>Bull. Soc. Math. France</em> <strong>2</strong> (1964), viii+150 p.), I think that an attentive reader will have no problems in supplementing, by their own means, the phantom references in Exposé VIII.
</p><p>
  Other oral exposés, found after Exposé XI, and to which there are references in certain places of the text, have also not been written down, and were meant to form the substance of an Exposé XII and an Exposé XIII.
  The first of these oral exposés covered, in the framework of schemes and analytic spaces with nilpotent elements (as introduced in the <em>Séminaire Cartan 1960/61</em>), the construction of the analytic space associated to a prescheme of locally finite type over a complete valuation field <tex>k</tex>, GAGA-type theorems in the case where <tex>k</tex> is the field of complex numbers, and the application to the comparison of the fundamental group defined by transcendental methods and the fundamental group studied in these notes (cf. A. Grothendieck, “Fondements de la Géométrie Algébrique”. <em>Séminaire Bourbaki</em> <strong>190</strong> (December 1959), page 10).
  The latter oral exposés outlined the generalisation of methods developed in the text for the study of coverings that admit moderate ramification, and of the structure of the fundamental group of a complete curve minus a finite number of points (cf. <em>loc. cit.</em> <strong>182</strong>, page 27, théorème 14).
  These exposés do not introduce any essentially new ideas, which is why it did not seem necessary to write them up properly before the appearance of the corresponding chapters of <em>Éléments de Géométrie Algébrique</em>.
  (They are included in the present volume in Exposé XII by Mme Raynaud with a different proof from the original given in the oral seminar (cf. <ref addr="sga1-introduction" href="sga1-introduction.xml"/>).)</p><p>
  However, the Lefschetz type theorems for the fundamental group and the Picard group, from both a local and a global point of view, were the subject of a separate seminar in 1962, which was completely written down and is available to read.
  (<em>Cohomologie étale des faisceaux cohérents et théorèmes de Lefschetz locaux et globaux</em> (SGA 2), appeared in North Holland Pub. Cie.)
  We point out that the results developed, both in the present <em>Séminaire</em> and the seminar from 1962, will be used in an essential manner in the appearance of many key results about the étale cohomology of preschemes, which will be the subject of a <em>Séminaire</em> (led by M. Artin and myself) in 1963/64, currently in preparation.
  (<em>Cohomologie étale des schémas</em> (SGA 4), to appear in the same series.)
  Exposés I to IV, which are of an essentially local nature, and very elementary, will be absorbed entirely by Chapter IV of <em>Éléments de Géométrie Algébrique</em>, of which the first part is being printed and will probably be published towards the end of 1964.
  They can, nevertheless, be useful for a reader who wants to catch up to speed with the essential properties of smooth, étale, or flat morphisms, before diving into the arcana of a systematic treatment.
  As for the other exposés, they will be absorbed into Chapter VIII of the <em>Éléments</em>, whose publication can barely even be contemplated for many years.
  (In fact, following a change to the initial plan for the <em>Éléments</em>, the study of the fundamental group has been postponed to a later chapter of the <em>Éléments</em>, cf. the Introduction <ref addr="sga1-introduction" href="sga1-introduction.xml"/> that precedes this Foreword.)</p><p><em>Bures, June 1963.</em></p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5038</anchor> <taxon>Exposé</taxon> <addr>sga1-i</addr><route>sga1-i.xml</route>    <title>ÉTale morphisms</title> <number>I</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
  To simplify the exposition, we assume that all preschemes in the following are locally Noetherian (at least, starting from <ref addr="sga1-i.2" href="sga1-i.2.xml" taxon="Section" number="I.2"/>).
</p><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="true" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5039</anchor> <taxon>Section</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.1</addr><route>sga1-i.1.xml</route>    <title>Basics of differential calculus</title> <number>I.1</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
  Let <tex>X</tex> be a prescheme over <tex>Y</tex>, and <tex>\Delta _{X/Y}</tex> the diagonal morphism <tex>X \to  X \times _Y X</tex>.
  This is an immersion, and thus a closed immersion of <tex>X</tex> into an open subset <tex>V</tex> of <tex>X \times _Y X</tex>.
  Let <tex>\mathcal { I } _X</tex> be the ideal of the closed sub-prescheme corresponding to the diagonal in <tex>V</tex> (N.B. if one really wishes to do things intrinsically, without assuming that <tex>X</tex> is separated over <tex>Y</tex> — a misleading hypothesis — then one should consider the set-theoretic inverse image of <tex>\mathcal { O } _{X \times  X}</tex> in <tex>X</tex> and denote by <tex>\mathcal { I } _X</tex> the augmentation ideal in the above ...).
  The sheaf <tex>\mathcal { I } _X/ \mathcal { I } _X^2</tex> can be thought of as a quasi-coherent sheaf on <tex>X</tex>, which we denote by <tex>\Omega _{X/Y}^1</tex>.
  This sheaf is of finite type if <tex>X \to  Y</tex> is of finite type, and it behaves well with respect to a base change <tex>Y' \to  Y</tex>.
  We also introduce the sheaves <tex>\mathcal { O } _{X \times _Y X}/ \mathcal { I } _X^{n+1}= \mathcal { P } ^n_{X/Y}</tex>, which are sheaves of <em>rings</em> on <tex>X</tex>, giving us preschemes denoted by <tex>\Delta _{X/Y}^n</tex> and called the <em><tex>n</tex>-th infinitesimal neighbourhood of <tex>X/Y</tex></em>.
  The polysyllogism is entirely trivial, even if rather long (cf. EGA IV 16.3);
  it seems wise to not discuss it until we use it for something helpful, with smooth morphisms.
</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="true" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5040</anchor> <taxon>Section</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.2</addr><route>sga1-i.2.xml</route>    <title>Quasi-finite morphisms</title> <number>I.2</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5041</anchor> <taxon>Proposition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.2.1</addr><route>sga1-i.2.1.xml</route>     <number>I.2.1</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>A \to  B</tex> be a local homomorphism (N.B. all rings are now Noetherian), and let <tex>\mathfrak {m}</tex> be the maximal ideal of <tex>A</tex>.
    Then the following conditions are equivalent:
  </p><p><strong><em>TO-DO: the following list should be i, ii, etc</em></strong></p><ol><li><tex>B/ \mathfrak {m}B</tex> is of finite dimension over <tex>k=A/ \mathfrak {m}</tex>.
    </li>
    <li><tex>\mathfrak {m}B</tex> is an ideal of definition, and <tex>B/ \mathfrak {r}(B)=k(B)</tex> is an extension of <tex>k=k(A)</tex>.
    </li>
    <li>
      The completion <tex>\widehat {B}</tex> of <tex>B</tex> is finite over the completion <tex>\widehat {A}</tex> of <tex>A</tex>.
    </li></ol></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  If the conditions of <ref addr="sga1-i.2.1" href="sga1-i.2.1.xml" taxon="Proposition" number="I.2.1"/> are satisfied, then we say that <tex>B</tex> is <em>quasi-finite</em> over <tex>A</tex>.
  A morphism <tex>f \colon  X \to  Y</tex> is said to be quasi-finite at <tex>x</tex> (or the <tex>Y</tex>-prescheme <tex>f</tex> is said to be quasi-finite at <tex>x</tex>) if <tex>\mathcal { O } _x</tex> is quasi-finite over <tex>\mathcal { O } _{f(x)}</tex>.
  This is equivalent to saying that <tex>x</tex> is <em>isolated in its fibre <tex>f^{-1}(x)</tex></em>.
  A morphism is said to be quasi-finite if it is quasi-finite at each point.
  (In [EGA II 6.2.3] we further suppose that <tex>f</tex> is of finite type.)
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5042</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.2.2</addr><route>sga1-i.2.2.xml</route>     <number>I.2.2</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    If <tex>A</tex> is complete, then quasi-finiteness is equivalent to finiteness.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  We could also give the usual polysyllogism (i), (ii), (iii), (iv), (v) for quasi-finite morphisms, but that doesn't seem necessary here.
</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="true" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5043</anchor> <taxon>Section</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.3</addr><route>sga1-i.3.xml</route>    <title>Unramified morphisms</title> <number>I.3</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5044</anchor> <taxon>Proposition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.3.1</addr><route>sga1-i.3.1.xml</route>     <number>I.3.1</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>f \colon  X \to  Y</tex> be a morphism of finite type, <tex>x \in  X</tex>, and <tex>y=f(x)</tex>.
    Then the following conditions are equivalent:
  </p><p><strong><em>TO-DO: the following list should be i, ii, etc</em></strong></p><ol><li><tex>\mathcal { O } _x/ \mathfrak {m}_y \mathcal { O } _x</tex> is a finite separable extension of <tex>k(y)</tex>.
    </li>
    <li><tex>\Omega _{X/Y}^1</tex> is zero at <tex>x</tex>.
    </li>
    <li>
      The diagonal morphism <tex>\Delta _{X/Y}</tex> is an open immersion on a neighbourhood of <tex>x</tex>.
    </li></ol>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5045</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      For the implication (i) <tex>\implies</tex> (ii), we can use Nakayama to reduce to the case where <tex>Y= \operatorname {Spec} (k)</tex> and <tex>X= \operatorname {Spec} (k')</tex>, where it is well known, and also trivial by the definition of separable;
      (ii) <tex>\implies</tex> (iii) comes from a nice and easy characterisation of open immersions, using Krull;
      (iii) <tex>\implies</tex> (i) follows as well from reducing to the case where <tex>Y= \operatorname {Spec} (k)</tex> and the diagonal morphism is everywhere an open immersion.
      We must then prove that <tex>X</tex> is finite with separable ring over <tex>k</tex>, and this leads us to consider the case where <tex>k</tex> is algebraically closed.
      But then every closed point of <tex>X</tex> is isolated (since it is identical to the inverse image of the diagonal by the morphism <tex>X \to  X \times _k X</tex> defined by <tex>x</tex>), whence <tex>X</tex> is finite.
      We can thus suppose that <tex>X</tex> consists of a single point, with ring <tex>A</tex>, and so <tex>A \otimes _k A \to  A</tex> is an isomorphism, hence <tex>A=k</tex>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5046</anchor> <taxon>Definition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.3.2</addr><route>sga1-i.3.2.xml</route>     <number>I.3.2</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p><strong><em>TO-DO: the following list should be a, b</em></strong></p><ol><li>
      Let <tex>f</tex> satisfy one of the equivalent conditions of <ref addr="sga1-i.3.1" href="sga1-i.3.1.xml" taxon="Proposition" number="I.3.1"/>.
      Then we say that <tex>f</tex> is <em>unramified</em> at <tex>x</tex>, or that <tex>X</tex> is unramified at <tex>x</tex> on <tex>Y</tex>.
    </li>
    <li>
      Let <tex>A \to  B</tex> be a local homomorphism.
      We say that it is <em>unramified</em>, or that <tex>B</tex> is a local <em>unramified</em> algebra on <tex>A</tex>, if <tex>B/ \mathfrak {r}(A)B</tex> is a finite separable extension of <tex>A/ \mathfrak {r}(A)</tex>, i.e. if <tex>\mathfrak {r}(A)B= \mathfrak {r}(B)</tex> and <tex>k(B)</tex> is a separable extension of <tex>k(A)</tex>.
      (cf. regrets in [III 1.2])
    </li></ol></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5047</anchor> <taxon>Remarks</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    The fact that <tex>B</tex> is unramified over <tex>A</tex> can be seen at the level of the completions of <tex>A</tex> and <tex>B</tex>.
    Unramified implies quasi-finite.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5048</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.3.3</addr><route>sga1-i.3.3.xml</route>     <number>I.3.3</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    The set of points where <tex>f</tex> is unramified is open.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5049</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.3.4</addr><route>sga1-i.3.4.xml</route>     <number>I.3.4</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>X'</tex> and <tex>X</tex> be preschemes of finite type over <tex>Y</tex>, and <tex>g \colon  X' \to  X</tex> a <tex>Y</tex>-morphism.
    If <tex>X</tex> is unramified over <tex>Y</tex>, then the graph morphism <tex>\Gamma _g \colon  X' \to  X \times _Y X</tex> is an open immersion.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  Indeed, this is the inverse image of the diagonal morphism <tex>X \to  X \times _Y X</tex> by
  <tex display="block">g \times _Y  \mathrm {id} _{X'} \colon  X' \times _Y X \to  X \times _Y X.</tex>
  One can also introduce the annihilator ideal <tex>\mathfrak {d}_{X/Y}</tex> of <tex>\Omega _{X/Y}^1</tex>, called the <em>different ideal</em> of <tex>X/Y</tex>;
  it defines a closed sub-prescheme of <tex>X</tex> which, set-theoretically, is the set of point where <tex>X/Y</tex> is ramified, i.e. not unramified.
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5050</anchor> <taxon>Proposition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.3.5</addr><route>sga1-i.3.5.xml</route>     <number>I.3.5</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p><strong><em>TO-DO: the following list should be i, ii, etc</em></strong></p><ol><li>
      An immersion is ramified.
    </li>
    <li>
      The composition of two ramified morphisms is also ramified.
    </li>
    <li>
      Base extension of a ramified morphisms is also ramified.
    </li></ol></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  We are rather indifferent about (ii) and (iii) (the second seems more interesting to me).
  We can, of course, also be more precise, by giving some one-off statements;
  this is more general only in appearance (except for in the case of definition (b)), and is boring.
  We obtain, as per usual, the corollaries:
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5051</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.3.6</addr><route>sga1-i.3.6.xml</route>     <number>I.3.6</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p><strong><em>TO-DO: the following list should be iv, v, etc</em></strong></p><ol><li>
      The cartesian product of two unramified morphisms is unramified.
    </li>
    <li>
      If <tex>gf</tex> is unramified then so too is <tex>f</tex>.
    </li>
    <li>
      If <tex>f</tex> is unramified then so too is <tex>f_ \mathrm {red}</tex>.
    </li></ol></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5052</anchor> <taxon>Proposition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.3.7</addr><route>sga1-i.3.7.xml</route>     <number>I.3.7</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>A \to  B</tex> be a local homomorphism, and suppose that the residue extension <tex>k(B)/k(A)</tex> is trivial, with <tex>k(A)</tex> algebraically closed.
    In order for <tex>B/A</tex> to be unramified, it is necessary and sufficient that <tex>\widehat {B}</tex> be (as an <tex>\widehat {A}</tex>-algebra) a quotient of <tex>\widehat {A}</tex>.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5053</anchor> <taxon>Remarks</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter><ul><li>
      In the case where we don't suppose that the residue extension is trivial, we can reduce to the case where it is by taking a suitable finite flat extension of <tex>A</tex> which destroys the aforementioned extension.
    </li>
    <li>
      Consider the example where <tex>A</tex> is the local ring of an ordinary double point of a curve, and <tex>B</tex> a point of its normalisation:
      then <tex>A \subset  B</tex>, <tex>B</tex> is unramified over <tex>A</tex> with trivial residue extension, and <tex>\widehat {A} \to \widehat {B}</tex> is surjective but <em>not injective</em>.
      We are thus going to strengthen the notion of unramified-ness.
    </li></ul></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="true" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5054</anchor> <taxon>Section</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.4</addr><route>sga1-i.4.xml</route>    <title>ÉTale morphisms. Étale covers</title> <number>I.4</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><strong><em>TO-DO: fix the auto-capitalisation of the title not recognising É</em></strong><p>
  We are going to suppose that everything concerning flat morphisms that we need to be true is indeed true;
  these facts will be proved later, if there is time.
  (cf. [sga1-iv <strong>(?)</strong>].)</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5055</anchor> <taxon>Definition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.4.1</addr><route>sga1-i.4.1.xml</route>     <number>I.4.1</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><strong><em>TO-DO: this list should be a, b</em></strong><ol><li>
      Let <tex>f \colon  X \to  Y</tex> be a morphism of finite type.
      We say that <tex>f</tex> is <em>étale</em> at <tex>x</tex> if <tex>f</tex> is both flat and unramified at <tex>x</tex>.
      We say that <tex>f</tex> is étale if it is étale at all points.
      We say that <tex>X</tex> is étale at <tex>x</tex> over <tex>Y</tex>, or that it is a <tex>Y</tex>-prescheme which is étale at <tex>x</tex> etc.
    </li>
    <li>
      Let <tex>f \colon  A \to  B</tex> be a local homomorphism.
      We say that <tex>f</tex> is étale, or that <tex>B</tex> is étale over <tex>A</tex>, if <tex>B</tex> is flat and unramified over <tex>A</tex>
      (cf. regrets in [sga1-iii.1.2 <strong>(?)</strong>].)</li></ol></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5056</anchor> <taxon>Proposition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.4.2</addr><route>sga1-i.4.2.xml</route>     <number>I.4.2</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    For <tex>B/A</tex> to be étale, it is necessary and sufficient that <tex>\widehat {B}/ \widehat {A}</tex> be étale.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5057</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      This is true individually for both &quot;unramified&quot; and &quot;flat&quot;.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5058</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.4.3</addr><route>sga1-i.4.3.xml</route>     <number>I.4.3</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>f \colon  X \to  Y</tex> be of finite type, and <tex>x \in  X</tex>.
    The property of <tex>f</tex> being étale at <tex>x</tex> depends only on the local homomorphism <tex>\mathcal { O } _{f(x)} \to \mathcal { O } _x</tex>, and in fact only on the corresponding homomorphism for the completions.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5059</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.4.4</addr><route>sga1-i.4.4.xml</route>     <number>I.4.4</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Suppose that the residue extension <tex>k(A) \to  k(B)</tex> is trivial, or that <tex>k(A)</tex> is algebraically closed.
    Then <tex>B/A</tex> is étale if and only if <tex>\widehat {A} \to \widehat {B}</tex> is an isomorphism.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  We can combine flatness with <ref addr="sga1-i.3.7" href="sga1-i.3.7.xml" taxon="Proposition" number="I.3.7"/>.
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5060</anchor> <taxon>Proposition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.4.5</addr><route>sga1-i.4.5.xml</route>     <number>I.4.5</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>f \colon  X \to  Y</tex> be a morphism of finite type.
    Then the set of points where <tex>f</tex> is étale is open.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5061</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      Again, this is true individually for both &quot;unramified&quot; and &quot;flat&quot;.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><p>
  This proposition shows that we can forget about the &quot;one-off&quot; comments in the study of morphisms of finite type that are somewhere étale.
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5062</anchor> <taxon>Proposition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.4.6</addr><route>sga1-i.4.6.xml</route>     <number>I.4.6</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><strong><em>TO-DO: this list should be i, ii etc</em></strong><ol><li>
      An open immersion is étale.
    </li>
    <li>
      The composition of two étale morphisms is étale.
    </li>
    <li>
      The base extension of an étale morphism is étale.
    </li></ol>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5063</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      Indeed, (i) is trivial, and for (ii) and (iii) it suffices to note that it is true for &quot;unramified&quot; and &quot;flat&quot;.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><p>
  As a matter of fact, there are also corresponding comments to make about local homomorphisms (without the finiteness condition), which in any case should appear in the multiplodoque (starting with the case of unramified).
  (<em>[Trans.] Grothendieck's &quot;multiplodoque d'algèbre homologique&quot; was the final version of his Tohoku paper — see (2.1) in &quot;Life and work of Alexander Grothendieck&quot; by Ching-Li Chan and Frans Oort for more information.</em>)</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5064</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.4.7</addr><route>sga1-i.4.7.xml</route>     <number>I.4.7</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    The cartesian product of two étale morphisms is étale.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5065</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.4.8</addr><route>sga1-i.4.8.xml</route>     <number>I.4.8</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>X</tex> and <tex>X'</tex> be of finite type over <tex>Y</tex>, and <tex>g \colon  X \to  X'</tex> a <tex>Y</tex>-morphism.
    If <tex>X'</tex> is unramified over <tex>Y</tex> and <tex>X</tex> is étale over <tex>Y</tex>, then <tex>g</tex> is étale.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5066</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      Indeed, <tex>g</tex> is the composition of the graph morphism <tex>\Gamma _g \colon  X \to  X \times _Y X'</tex> (which is an open immersion by <ref addr="sga1-i.3.4" href="sga1-i.3.4.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.3.4"/>) and the projection morphism, which is étale since it is just a &quot;change of base&quot; by <tex>X' \to  Y</tex> of the étale morphism <tex>X \to  Y</tex>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5067</anchor> <taxon>Definition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.4.9</addr><route>sga1-i.4.9.xml</route>     <number>I.4.9</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    We say that a cover of <tex>Y</tex> is étale (resp. unramified) if it is a <tex>Y</tex>-scheme <tex>X</tex> that is finite over <tex>Y</tex> and étale (resp. unramified) over <tex>Y</tex>.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  The first condition means that <tex>X</tex> is defined by a coherent sheaf of algebras <tex>\mathcal { B }</tex> over <tex>Y</tex>.
  The second means that <tex>\mathcal { B }</tex> is locally free over <tex>Y</tex> (resp. means absolutely nothing) <em>and</em>, further, that, for all <tex>y \in  Y</tex>, the fibre <tex>\mathcal { B } (y)= \mathcal { B } _y \otimes _{ \mathcal { O } _y}k(y)</tex> is a separable algebra (i.e. a finite composition of finite separable extensions) over <tex>k(y)</tex>.
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5068</anchor> <taxon>Proposition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.4.10</addr><route>sga1-i.4.10.xml</route>     <number>I.4.10</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>X</tex> be a flat cover of <tex>Y</tex> of degree <tex>n</tex> (the definition of this term deserved to figure in <ref addr="sga1-i.4.9" href="sga1-i.4.9.xml" taxon="Definition" number="I.4.9"/>) defined by a locally free coherent sheaf <tex>\mathcal { B }</tex> of algebras.
    We define, as usual, the trace homomorphism <tex>\mathcal { B } \to \mathcal { A }</tex> (that is, a homomorphism of <tex>\mathcal { A }</tex>-modules, where <tex>\mathcal { A } = \mathcal { O } _Y</tex>).
    For <tex>X</tex> to be étale it is necessary and sufficient that the corresponding bilinear form <tex>\operatorname {tr} _{ \mathcal { B } / \mathcal { A } }xy</tex> define an isomorphism of <tex>\mathcal { B }</tex> over <tex>\mathcal { B }</tex>, or, equivalently, that the <em>discriminant section</em>
    <tex display="block">       d_{X/Y}       = d_{ \mathcal { B } / \mathcal { A } }        \in   \Gamma \big (Y, \wedge ^n \check { \mathcal { B } } \otimes _ \mathcal { A } \wedge ^n \check { \mathcal { B } } \big )     </tex>
    is invertible, or that the discriminant ideal defined by this section is the unit ring.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5069</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      We can reduce to the case where <tex>Y= \operatorname {Spec} (k)</tex>, and then it is a well-known criterion of separability, and thus trivial by passing to the algebraic closure of <tex>k</tex>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5070</anchor> <taxon>Remark</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    We will have a less trivial statement to make later on, when we do not suppose a priori that <tex>X</tex> is flat over <tex>Y</tex>, but instead require some normality hypothesis.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="true" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5071</anchor> <taxon>Section</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.5</addr><route>sga1-i.5.xml</route>    <title>Fundamental property of étale morphisms</title> <number>I.5</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5072</anchor> <taxon>Theorem</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.5.1</addr><route>sga1-i.5.1.xml</route>     <number>I.5.1</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>f \colon  X \to  Y</tex> be a morphism of finite type.
    For <tex>f</tex> to be an open immersion, it is necessary and sufficient that it be <em>étale</em> and <em>radicial</em>.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5073</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      Recall what &quot;radicial&quot; means: injective, with radicial residual extensions (recall also that it means that the morphism remains injective under any base extension).
      The necessity is trivial, and the sufficiency remains to be shown.
      We are going to give two different proofs: the first is shorter, the second is more elementary.
    </p>

    <ol><li>
        A flat morphism is open, and so we can suppose (by replacing <tex>Y</tex> with <tex>f(X)</tex>) that <tex>f</tex> is an onto <em>homeomorphism</em>.
        For any base extension, it remains true that <tex>f</tex> is flat, radicial, and surjective, thus a homeomorphism, and a fortiori closed.
        Thus <tex>f</tex> is <em>proper</em>.
        Thus <tex>f</tex> is <em>finite</em> (reference: Chevalley's theorem), defined by a coherent sheaf <tex>\mathcal { B }</tex> of algebras.
        Now <tex>\mathcal { B }</tex> is locally free, and further, by hypothesis, of rank 1 everywhere, and so <tex>X=Y</tex>.
      </li>

      <li>
        We can suppose that <tex>Y</tex> and <tex>X</tex> are <em>affine</em>.
        We can further easily reduce to proving the following:
        if <tex>Y= \operatorname {Spec} (A)</tex>, with <tex>A</tex> local, and if <tex>f^{-1}(y)</tex> is non-empty (where <tex>y</tex> is the closed point of <tex>Y</tex>), then <tex>X=Y</tex> (indeed, this would imply that every <tex>y \in  f(X)</tex> has an open neighbourhood <tex>U</tex> such that <tex>X|U=U</tex>).
        We will then have that <tex>X= \operatorname {Spec} (B)</tex>, and wish to prove that <tex>A=B</tex>.
        But for this we can reduce to proving the analogous claim where we replace <tex>A</tex> by <tex>\widehat {A}</tex>, and <tex>B</tex> by <tex>B \otimes _A \widehat {A}</tex>
        (taking into account the fact that <tex>\widehat {A}</tex> is faithfully flat over <tex>A</tex>).
        We can thus suppose that <tex>A</tex> is <em>complete</em>.
        Let <tex>x</tex> be the point over <tex>y</tex>.
        By <ref addr="sga1-i.2.2" href="sga1-i.2.2.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.2.2"/>, <tex>\mathcal { O } _x</tex> is finite over <tex>A</tex>, and is thus (being flat and radicial over <tex>A</tex>) identical to <tex>A</tex>.
        So <tex>X=Y \coprod  X'</tex> (disjoint sum).
        But since <tex>X</tex> is radicial over <tex>Y</tex>, <tex>X'</tex> is empty.
      </li></ol>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5074</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.5.2</addr><route>sga1-i.5.2.xml</route>     <number>I.5.2</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>f \colon  X \to  Y</tex> be a morphism that is both a <em>closed immersion</em> and <em>étale</em>.
    If <tex>X</tex> is connected, then <tex>f</tex> is an isomorphism from <tex>X</tex> to a connected component of <tex>Y</tex>.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5075</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      Indeed, <tex>f</tex> is also an open immersion.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><p>
  We thus deduce:
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5076</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.5.3</addr><route>sga1-i.5.3.xml</route>     <number>I.5.3</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>X</tex> be an unramified <tex>Y</tex>-scheme, with <tex>Y</tex> connected.
    Then every section of <tex>X</tex> over <tex>Y</tex> is an isomorphism from <tex>Y</tex> to a connected component of <tex>X</tex>.
    There is thus a bijective correspondence between the set of such sections and the set of connected components <tex>X_i</tex> of <tex>X</tex> such that the projection <tex>X_i \to  Y</tex> is an isomorphism (or, equivalently, by <ref addr="sga1-i.5.1" href="sga1-i.5.1.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.5.1"/>, surjective and radicial).
    In particular, a section is determined by its value at a point.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5077</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      Only the first claim demands a proof;
      by <ref addr="sga1-i.5.2" href="sga1-i.5.2.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.5.2"/>, it suffices to note that a section is a closed immersion (since <tex>X</tex> is separated over <tex>Y</tex>) and also étale, by <ref addr="sga1-i.4.8" href="sga1-i.4.8.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.4.8"/>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5078</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.5.4</addr><route>sga1-i.5.4.xml</route>     <number>I.5.4</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>X</tex> and <tex>Y</tex> be preschemes over <tex>S</tex>, with <tex>X</tex> unramified and separated over <tex>S</tex>, and <tex>Y</tex> connected.
    Let <tex>f</tex> and <tex>g</tex> be <tex>S</tex>-morphisms from <tex>Y</tex> to <tex>X</tex>, and suppose that <tex>y</tex> is a point of <tex>Y</tex> such that <tex>f(y)=g(y)=x</tex>, and such that the residue homomorphisms <tex>k(x) \to  k(y)</tex> defined by <tex>f</tex> and <tex>g</tex> are identical (&quot;<tex>f</tex> and <tex>g</tex> agree geometrically at <tex>y</tex>&quot;).
    Then <tex>f</tex> and <tex>g</tex> are identical.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5079</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      This follows from <ref addr="sga1-i.5.3" href="sga1-i.5.3.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.5.3"/> by reducing to the case where <tex>Y=S</tex>, and by replacing <tex>X</tex> with <tex>X \times _S Y</tex>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><p>
  Here is a particularly important variant of <ref addr="sga1-i.5.3" href="sga1-i.5.3.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.5.3"/>:
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5080</anchor> <taxon>Theorem</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.5.5</addr><route>sga1-i.5.5.xml</route>     <number>I.5.5</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>S</tex> be a prescheme, and let <tex>X</tex> and <tex>Y</tex> be <tex>S</tex>-preschemes.
    Let <tex>S_0</tex> be a closed sub-prescheme of <tex>S</tex> that has the same underlying space as <tex>S</tex>, and let <tex>X_0=X \times _S S_0</tex> and <tex>Y_0=Y \times _S S_0</tex> be the &quot;restrictions&quot; of <tex>X</tex> and <tex>Y</tex> to <tex>S_0</tex>.
    Suppose that <tex>X</tex> is étale over <tex>S</tex>.
    Then the natural map
    <tex display="block">\operatorname {Hom} _S(Y,X)  \to   \operatorname {Hom} _{S_0}(X_0,Y_0)</tex>
    is <em>bijective</em>.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5081</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      We can again reduce to the case where <tex>Y=S</tex>, and then this follows from the &quot;topological&quot; description of sections of <tex>X/Y</tex> given in <ref addr="sga1-i.5.3" href="sga1-i.5.3.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.5.3"/>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5082</anchor> <taxon>Scholium</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>S</tex> be a prescheme, and let <tex>X</tex> and <tex>Y</tex> be <tex>S</tex>-preschemes.
    Let <tex>S_0</tex> be a closed sub-prescheme of <tex>S</tex> that has the same underlying space as <tex>S</tex>, and let <tex>X_0=X \times _S S_0</tex> and <tex>Y_0=Y \times _S S_0</tex> be the &quot;restrictions&quot; of <tex>X</tex> and <tex>Y</tex> to <tex>S_0</tex>.
    Suppose that <tex>X</tex> is étale over <tex>S</tex>.
    Then the natural map
    <tex display="block">\operatorname {Hom} _S(Y,X)  \to   \operatorname {Hom} _{S_0}(X_0,Y_0)</tex>
    is <em>bijective</em>.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  The following form of <ref addr="sga1-i.5.5" href="sga1-i.5.5.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.5.5"/> (which looks more general) is often useful:
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5083</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.5.6</addr><route>sga1-i.5.6.xml</route>    <title>Extension of liftings</title> <number>I.5.6</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Consider a commutative diagram of morphisms
    <tex display="block">        \begin {CD}         X @&lt;&lt;&lt; Y_0        \\ @VVV @VVV        \\ S @&lt;&lt;&lt; Y        \end {CD}     </tex>
    where <tex>X \to  S</tex> is étale, and <tex>Y_0 \to  Y</tex> is a bijective closed immersion.
    Then we can find a unique morphism <tex>Y \to  X</tex> such that the two corresponding triangles commute.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5084</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      By replacing <tex>S</tex> with <tex>Y</tex>, and <tex>X</tex> with <tex>X \times _S Y</tex>, we can reduce to the case where <tex>Y=S</tex>, and this is then a particular case of <ref addr="sga1-i.5.5" href="sga1-i.5.5.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.5.5"/> for <tex>Y=S</tex>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><p>
  We also note the following immediate consequence of <ref addr="sga1-i.5.1" href="sga1-i.5.1.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.5.1"/> (which we did not give as a corollary, in order to not interrupt the line of ideas developed following <ref addr="sga1-i.5.1" href="sga1-i.5.1.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.5.1"/>):
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5085</anchor> <taxon>Proposition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.5.7</addr><route>sga1-i.5.7.xml</route>     <number>I.5.7</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>X</tex> and <tex>X'</tex> be preschemes that are of finite type and flat over <tex>Y</tex>, and let <tex>g \colon  X \to  X'</tex> be a <tex>Y</tex>-morphism.
    For <tex>g</tex> to be an open immersion (resp. an isomorphism), it is necessary and sufficient that the induced morphism on the fibres
    <tex display="block">       g \otimes _Y k(y) \colon        X \otimes _Y k(y)  \to  X' \otimes _Y k(y)     </tex>
    be an open immersion (resp. an isomorphism) for all <tex>y \in  Y</tex>.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5086</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      It suffices to prove sufficiency;
      since it is true for the property of being a surjection, we can reduce to the case of an open immersion.
      By <ref addr="sga1-i.5.1" href="sga1-i.5.1.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.5.1"/>, we have to show that <tex>g</tex> is <em>radicial</em> (which is trivial) and <em>étale</em> (which follows from <ref addr="sga1-i.5.9" href="sga1-i.5.9.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.5.9"/> below).
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5087</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.5.8</addr><route>sga1-i.5.8.xml</route>     <number>I.5.8</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>X</tex> and <tex>X'</tex> be <tex>Y</tex>-preschemes, <tex>g \colon  X \to  X'</tex> a <tex>Y</tex>-morphism, <tex>x</tex> a point of <tex>X</tex>, and <tex>y</tex> the projection of <tex>x</tex> in <tex>Y</tex>.
    For <tex>g</tex> to be quasi-finite (resp. unramified) at <tex>x</tex>, it is necessary and sufficient that <tex>g \otimes _Y k(y)</tex> be so.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5088</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      The two algebras over <tex>k(g(x))</tex> that we have to study in order to see whether or not we do indeed have a morphism which is quasi-finite (resp. unramified) at <tex>x</tex> are the same for <tex>g</tex> and <tex>g \otimes _Y k(y)</tex>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5089</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.5.9</addr><route>sga1-i.5.9.xml</route>     <number>I.5.9</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    With the notation of <ref addr="sga1-i.5.8" href="sga1-i.5.8.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.5.8"/>, suppose that <tex>X</tex> and <tex>X'</tex> are flat and of finite type over <tex>Y</tex>.
    For <tex>g</tex> to be flat (resp. étale) at <tex>x</tex>, it is necessary and sufficient that <tex>g \otimes _Y k(y)</tex> be so.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5090</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      For &quot;flat&quot;, the statement only serves as a reminder, since this is one of the fundamental criteria of flatness.
      (cf. [sga1-iv.5.9 <strong>(?)</strong>].)
      For &quot;étale&quot;, this follows by taking <ref addr="sga1-i.5.8" href="sga1-i.5.8.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.5.8"/> into account.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="true" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5091</anchor> <taxon>Section</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.6</addr><route>sga1-i.6.xml</route>    <title>Application to étale extensions of complete local rings</title> <number>I.6</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
  This section is a particular case of the results on formal preschemes, which should appear in the multiplodoque.
  Nevertheless, here we get away without much difficulty, i.e. without the explicit local determination of the étale morphisms in [sga1-i.7 <strong>(?)</strong>] (using the Main Theorem).
  This is perhaps sufficient reason to keep this current section (even in the multiplodoque) where it is.
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5092</anchor> <taxon>Theorem</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.6.1</addr><route>sga1-i.6.1.xml</route>     <number>I.6.1</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>A</tex> be a complete local ring (Noetherian, of course), with residue field <tex>k</tex>.
    For any <tex>A</tex>-algebra <tex>B</tex>, let <tex>R(B)=B \otimes _Ak</tex> be thought of as a <tex>k</tex>-algebra;
    this depends functorially on <tex>B</tex>.
    Then <tex>R</tex> defines an <em>equivalence</em> between the category of <tex>A</tex>-algebras that are <em>finite and étale over <tex>A</tex></em> and the category of algebras that are <em>finite rank and separable over <tex>k</tex></em>.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  Firstly, the functor in question is fully faithful, as follows from the more general fact:
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5093</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.6.2</addr><route>sga1-i.6.2.xml</route>     <number>I.6.2</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>B</tex> and <tex>B'</tex> be <tex>A</tex>-algebras that are finite over <tex>A</tex>.
    If <tex>B</tex> is étale over <tex>A</tex>, then the canonical map
    <tex display="block">        \operatorname {Hom} _{ A \mathsf {-alg} }(B,B')        \to   \operatorname {Hom} _{ k \mathsf {-alg} }(R(B),R(B'))     </tex>
    is bijective.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5094</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      We can reduce to the case where <tex>A</tex> is Artinian (by replacing <tex>A</tex> by <tex>A/ \frak {m}^n</tex>), and then this is a particular case of <ref addr="sga1-i.5.5" href="sga1-i.5.5.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.5.5"/>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><p>
  It remains to prove that, for every finite and separable <tex>k</tex> algebra (or we can simply say &quot;étale&quot;, for brevity) <tex>L</tex>, there exists some <tex>B</tex> étale over <tex>A</tex> such that <tex>R(B)</tex> is isomorphic to <tex>L</tex>.
  We can suppose that <tex>L</tex> is a separable extension of <tex>k</tex>, and, as such, it admits a generator <tex>x</tex>, i.e. it is isomorphic to an algebra <tex>k[t]/Fk[t]</tex>, where <tex>F \in  k[t]</tex> is a monic polynomial.
  We can lift <tex>F</tex> to a monic polynomial <tex>F_1</tex> in <tex>A[t]</tex>, and we take <tex>B=A[t]/F_1A[t]</tex>.
</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="true" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5095</anchor> <taxon>Section</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.7</addr><route>sga1-i.7.xml</route>    <title>Local construction of unramified and étale morphisms</title> <number>I.7</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5096</anchor> <taxon>Proposition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.7.1</addr><route>sga1-i.7.1.xml</route>     <number>I.7.1</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>A</tex> be a Noetherian ring, <tex>B</tex> an algebra which is finite over <tex>A</tex>, and <tex>u</tex> a generator of <tex>B</tex> over <tex>A</tex>.
    Let <tex>F \in  A[t]</tex> be such that <tex>F(u)=0</tex> (we do not assume <tex>F</tex> to be monic), and <tex>u'=F'(u)</tex> (where <tex>F'</tex> is the differentiated polynomial).
    Let <tex>\mathfrak {q}</tex> be a prime ideal of <tex>B</tex> not containing <tex>u'</tex>, and <tex>\mathfrak {p}</tex> its intersection with <tex>A</tex>.
    Then <tex>B_ \mathfrak {q}</tex> is unramified over <tex>A_ \mathfrak {p}</tex>.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  In other words, taking <tex>Y= \operatorname {Spec} (A)</tex>, <tex>X= \operatorname {Spec} (B)</tex>, and <tex>X_{u'}= \operatorname {Spec} (B_{u'})</tex>, we claim that <tex>X_{u'}</tex> is unramified over <tex>Y</tex>.
  This statement follows from the following, more precise:
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5097</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.7.2</addr><route>sga1-i.7.2.xml</route>     <number>I.7.2</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    The different ideal of <tex>B/A</tex> contains <tex>u'B</tex>, and is equal to <tex>u'B</tex> if the natural homomorphism <tex>A[t]/FA[t] \to  B</tex> (sending <tex>t</tex> to <tex>u</tex>) is an isomorphism.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5098</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      Let <tex>J</tex> be the kernel of the homomorphism <tex>C=A[t] \to  B</tex>, so that <tex>J</tex> contains <tex>FA[t]</tex>, and is equal to it in the second case described in <ref addr="sga1-i.7.2" href="sga1-i.7.2.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.7.2"/>.
      Since the homomorphism <tex>C \to  B</tex> is surjective, <tex>\Omega _{B/A}^1</tex> can be identified with the quotient of <tex>\Omega _{C/A}^1</tex> by the sub-module generated by <tex>J \Omega _{C/A}^1</tex> and <tex>\mathrm {d} (J)</tex> (we should have explicitly described the definition of the homomorphism <tex>d</tex> and the calculation of <tex>\Omega ^1</tex> for an algebra of polynomials in <ref addr="sga1-i" href="sga1-i.xml" taxon="Exposé" number="I"/>).
      Identifying <tex>\Omega _{C/A}^1</tex> with <tex>C</tex>, via the basis <tex>\mathrm {d}  t</tex>, we obtain <tex>B/B \cdot  J'</tex>, and so the different ideal is generated by the set <tex>J'</tex> of images in <tex>B</tex> of derivatives of <tex>G \in  J</tex> (and it suffices to take <tex>G</tex> that generate <tex>J</tex>).
      Since <tex>F \in  J</tex> (resp. <tex>F</tex> is a generator of <tex>J</tex>), we are done.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5099</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.7.3</addr><route>sga1-i.7.3.xml</route>     <number>I.7.3</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Under the conditions of <ref addr="sga1-i.7.1" href="sga1-i.7.1.xml" taxon="Proposition" number="I.7.1"/>, and supposing that <tex>F</tex> is monic and that <tex>A[t]/FA[t] \to  B</tex> is an isomorphism, in order for <tex>B_ \mathfrak {q}</tex> to be étale over <tex>A_ \mathfrak {p}</tex> it is necessary and sufficient that <tex>\mathfrak {q}</tex> not contain <tex>u'</tex>.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5100</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      Since <tex>B</tex> is flat over <tex>A</tex>, being étale is equivalent to being unramified, and we can apply <ref addr="sga1-i.7.2" href="sga1-i.7.2.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.7.2"/>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5101</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.7.4</addr><route>sga1-i.7.4.xml</route>     <number>I.7.4</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Under the conditions of <ref addr="sga1-i.7.3" href="sga1-i.7.3.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.7.3"/>, in order for <tex>B</tex> to be étale over <tex>A</tex>, it is necessary and sufficient that <tex>u'</tex> be invertible, or for the ideal <tex>F'</tex> generated by <tex>F</tex> in <tex>A[t]</tex> to be the unit ideal.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5102</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      The second claim follows from the first along with Nakayama (in <tex>B</tex>).
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><p>
  A monic polynomial <tex>F \in  A[t]</tex> that has the property stated in <ref addr="sga1-i.7.4" href="sga1-i.7.4.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.7.4"/> is said to be a <em>separable polynomial</em> (if <tex>F</tex> is not monic, we must at least require that the coefficient of its leading term be invertible; in the case where <tex>A</tex> is a field, we recover the usual definition).
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5103</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.7.5</addr><route>sga1-i.7.5.xml</route>     <number>I.7.5</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>B</tex> be an algebra which is <em>finite</em> over the <em>local</em> ring <tex>A</tex>.
    Suppose that <tex>K(A)</tex> is infinite, or that <tex>B</tex> is local.
    Let <tex>n</tex> be the rank of <tex>L=B \otimes _A K(A)</tex> over <tex>K(A)=k</tex>.
    For <tex>B</tex> to be unramified (resp. étale) over <tex>A</tex>, it is necessary and sufficient that <tex>B</tex> be isomorphic to a quotient of (resp. isomorphic to) <tex>A[t]/FA[t]</tex>, where <tex>F</tex> is a separable monic polynomial, which we can assume to be (resp. which is necessarily of) degree <tex>n</tex>.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5104</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      We only have to prove necessity.
      Suppose that <tex>B</tex> is unramified over <tex>A</tex>, and thus that <tex>L</tex> is separable over <tex>k</tex>.
      It then follows from the hypotheses that <tex>L/k</tex> admits a generator <tex>\xi</tex>, and so the <tex>\xi ^i</tex> (for <tex>0 \leq  i&lt;n</tex>) form a basis for <tex>L</tex> over <tex>k</tex>.
      Let <tex>u \in  B</tex> be a lift of <tex>\xi</tex>;
      by Nakayama, the <tex>u^i</tex> (for <tex>0 \leq  i&lt;n</tex>) generate (resp. form a basis of) the <tex>A</tex>-module <tex>B</tex>, and, in particular, we obtain a monic polynomial <tex>F \in  A[t]</tex> such that <tex>F(u)=0</tex>;
      then <tex>B</tex> is isomorphic to a quotient of (resp. isomorphic to) <tex>A[t]/FA[t]</tex>.
      Finally, by applying <ref addr="sga1-i.7.4" href="sga1-i.7.4.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.7.4"/> to <tex>L/k</tex>, we see that <tex>F</tex> and <tex>F'</tex> generate <tex>A[t]</tex> modulo <tex>\mathfrak {m}A[t]</tex>, and so (by Nakayama in <tex>A[t]/FA[t]</tex>) <tex>F</tex> and <tex>F'</tex> generate <tex>A[t]</tex>, and we are done.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5105</anchor> <taxon>Theorem</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.7.6</addr><route>sga1-i.7.6.xml</route>     <number>I.7.6</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>A</tex> be a local ring, and <tex>A \to \mathcal { O }</tex> a local homomorphism such that <tex>\mathcal { O }</tex> is isomorphic to the localisation of an algebra of finite type over <tex>A</tex>.
    Suppose that <tex>\mathcal { O }</tex> is <em>unramified</em> over <tex>A</tex>.
    Then we can find an <tex>A</tex>-algebra <tex>B</tex> that is integral over <tex>A</tex>, a maximal ideal <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex> of <tex>B</tex>, a generator <tex>u</tex> of <tex>B</tex> over <tex>A</tex>, and a monic polynomial <tex>F \in  A[t]</tex> such that <tex>\mathfrak {n} \not \ni  F'(u)</tex> and such that <tex>\mathcal { O }</tex> is isomorphic (as an <tex>A</tex>-algebra) to <tex>B_ \mathfrak {n}</tex>.
    If <tex>\mathcal { O }</tex> is étale over <tex>A</tex>, then we can take <tex>B=A[t]/FA[t]</tex>.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  (Of course, these conditions are more than sufficient ...)
</p><p>
  Before proving <ref addr="sga1-i.7.6" href="sga1-i.7.6.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.7.6"/>, we first state some nice corollaries:
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5106</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.7.7</addr><route>sga1-i.7.7.xml</route>     <number>I.7.7</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    For <tex>\mathcal { O }</tex> to be unramified over <tex>A</tex>, it is necessary and sufficient that <tex>\mathcal { O }</tex> be isomorphic to the quotient of an algebra which is unramified and <em>étale</em> over <tex>A</tex>.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5107</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      We can take <tex>\mathcal { O } '=B'_{ \mathfrak {n}'}</tex>, where <tex>B'=A[t]/FA[t]</tex> and where <tex>\mathfrak {n}'</tex> is the inverse image of <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex> in <tex>B'</tex>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5108</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.7.8</addr><route>sga1-i.7.8.xml</route>     <number>I.7.8</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>f \colon  X \to  Y</tex> be a morphism of finite type, and <tex>x \in  X</tex>.
    For <tex>f</tex> to be unramified at <tex>x</tex>, it is necessary and sufficient that there exist an open neighbourhood <tex>U</tex> of <tex>x</tex> such that <tex>f|U</tex> factors as <tex>U \to  X' \to  Y</tex>, where the first arrow is a closed immersion, and the second is an étale morphism.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5109</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      This is a simple translation of <ref addr="sga1-i.7.7" href="sga1-i.7.7.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.7.7"/>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><p>
  We will now show how the jargon of <ref addr="sga1-i.7.6" href="sga1-i.7.6.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.7.6"/> follows from the main theorem:
  there exists, by <ref addr="sga1-i.7.7" href="sga1-i.7.7.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.7.7"/>, an epimorphism <tex>\mathcal { O } ' \to \mathcal { O }</tex>, where <tex>\mathcal { O }</tex> has all the desired properties;
  but since <tex>\mathcal { O } '</tex> and <tex>\mathcal { O }</tex> are étale over <tex>A</tex>, the morphism <tex>\mathcal { O } ' \to \mathcal { O }</tex> is étale by <ref addr="sga1-i.4.8" href="sga1-i.4.8.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.4.8"/>, and thus an isomorphism.
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5110</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.7.6-proof</addr><route>sga1-i.7.6-proof.xml</route>     <number>I.7.6</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    This mimics a proof from the <em>Séminaire Chevalley</em>.
    By the &quot;Main Theorem&quot;, we have that <tex>\mathcal { O } =B_ \mathfrak {n}</tex>, where <tex>B</tex> is an algebra that is finite over <tex>A</tex>, and <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex> is a maximal ideal.
    Then <tex>B/ \mathfrak {n}=B( \mathcal { O } )</tex> is a separable, and thus monogenous, extension of <tex>k</tex>;
    if <tex>\mathfrak {n}_i</tex> (for <tex>1 \leq  i \leq  r</tex>) are maximal ideas of <tex>B</tex> that are distinct from <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex>, then there thus exists an element <tex>u</tex> of <tex>B</tex> that belongs to all the <tex>\mathfrak {n}_i</tex>, and thus whose image in <tex>B/ \mathfrak {n}</tex> is a generator.
    But <tex>B/ \mathfrak {n}=B_ \mathfrak {n}/ \mathfrak {n}B_ \mathfrak {n}=B_ \mathfrak {n}/ \mathfrak {m}B_ \mathfrak {n}</tex> (where <tex>\mathfrak {m}</tex> is the maximal ideal of <tex>A</tex>).

    Suppose, for the moment, that we have both <ref addr="sga1-i.7.9" href="sga1-i.7.9.xml" taxon="Lemma" number="I.7.9"/> and <ref addr="sga1-i.7.10" href="sga1-i.7.10.xml" taxon="Lemma" number="I.7.10"/>.
    Let <tex>n</tex> be the rank of the <tex>k</tex>-algebra <tex>L=B \otimes _A k</tex>.
    By Nakayama, there exists a monic polynomial of degree <tex>n</tex> in <tex>A[t]</tex> such that <tex>F(u)=0</tex>.
    Let <tex>f</tex> be the polynomial induced from <tex>F</tex> by reduction <tex>\mod \mathfrak {m}</tex>.
    Then <tex>L</tex> is <tex>k</tex>-isomorphic to <tex>k[t]/fk[t]</tex>, and so, by <ref addr="sga1-i.7.3" href="sga1-i.7.3.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.7.3"/>, <tex>f'( \xi )</tex> is not contained in the maximal ideal of <tex>L</tex> that corresponds to <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex> (where <tex>\xi</tex> denotes the image of <tex>t</tex> in <tex>L</tex>, i.e. the image of <tex>u</tex> in <tex>L</tex>).
    Since <tex>f'( \xi )</tex> is the image of <tex>F'(u)</tex>, we are done.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5111</anchor> <taxon>Lemma</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.7.9</addr><route>sga1-i.7.9.xml</route>     <number>I.7.9</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>A</tex> be a local ring, <tex>B</tex> an algebra that is finite over <tex>A</tex>, <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex> a maximal ideal of <tex>B</tex>, and <tex>u</tex> an element of <tex>B</tex> whose image in <tex>B_ \mathfrak {n}/ \mathfrak {m}B_ \mathfrak {n}</tex> is a generator as an algebra over <tex>k=A/ \mathfrak {m}</tex>, and such that <tex>u</tex> is contained in every maximal ideal of <tex>B</tex> that is distinct from <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex>.
    Let <tex>B'=B[u]</tex> and <tex>\mathfrak {n}'= \mathfrak {n}B'</tex>.
    Then the canonical homomorphism <tex>B'_{ \mathfrak {n}'} \to  B_ \mathfrak {n}</tex> is an isomorphism.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5112</anchor> <taxon>Lemma</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.7.10</addr><route>sga1-i.7.10.xml</route>     <number>I.7.10</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>B</tex> be a algebra that is finite over <tex>A</tex> and generated by a single element <tex>u</tex>, and let <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex> be a maximal ideal of <tex>B</tex> such that <tex>B_ \mathfrak {n}</tex> is unramified over <tex>A</tex>.
    Then there exists a monic polynomial <tex>F \in  A[t]</tex> such that <tex>F(u)=0</tex> and <tex>F'(u) \not \in \mathfrak {n}</tex>.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  N.B. <ref addr="sga1-i.7.10" href="sga1-i.7.10.xml" taxon="Lemma" number="I.7.10"/> should have appeared as a corollary to <ref addr="sga1-i.7.1" href="sga1-i.7.1.xml" taxon="Proposition" number="I.7.1"/>, and before <ref addr="sga1-i.7.5" href="sga1-i.7.5.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.7.5"/> (which it implies).
</p><p>
  So <ref addr="sga1-i.7.6" href="sga1-i.7.6.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.7.6"/> now follows from the combination of <ref addr="sga1-i.7.9" href="sga1-i.7.9.xml" taxon="Lemma" number="I.7.9"/> and <ref addr="sga1-i.7.10" href="sga1-i.7.10.xml" taxon="Lemma" number="I.7.10"/>;
  it remains only to prove <ref addr="sga1-i.7.9" href="sga1-i.7.9.xml" taxon="Lemma" number="I.7.9"/>.
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5113</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.7.9-proof</addr><route>sga1-i.7.9-proof.xml</route>     <number>I.7.9</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>S'=B' \setminus \mathfrak {n}'</tex>, so that <tex>B'S'^{-1}=B'_ \mathfrak {n'}</tex>.
    Similarly, let <tex>S=B \setminus \mathfrak {n}</tex>, so that <tex>BS^{-1}=B_ \mathfrak {n}</tex>.
    We then have a natural homomorphism <tex>BS'^{-1} \to  BS^{-1}=B_ \mathfrak {n}</tex>;
    we will show that this is an isomorphism, i.e. that the elements of <tex>S</tex> are invertible in <tex>BS'^{-1}</tex>, i.e. that every maximal ideal <tex>\mathfrak {p}</tex> of <tex>BS'^{-1}</tex> does not meet <tex>S</tex>, i.e. that every maximal ideal of <tex>BS'^{-1}</tex> induces <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex> on <tex>B</tex>.
    <tex display="block">        \begin {CD}         B @&gt;&gt;&gt; BS'^{-1} @&gt;&gt;&gt; BS^{-1} = B_ \mathfrak {n}        \\ @AAA @AAA        \\ B' @&gt;&gt;&gt; B'S'^{-1} = B'_{ \mathfrak {n}'}        \end {CD}     </tex>
    Since <tex>BS'^{-1}</tex> is finite over <tex>B'S'^{-1}=B'_{ \mathfrak {n}'}</tex>, <tex>\mathfrak {p}</tex> induces the unique maximal ideal <tex>\mathfrak {n}'B_{ \mathfrak {n}'}</tex> of <tex>B'_{ \mathfrak {n}'}</tex>, and thus induces the maximal ideal <tex>\mathfrak {n}'</tex> of <tex>B'</tex>;
    since <tex>B</tex> is finite over <tex>B'</tex>, the ideal <tex>\mathfrak {q}</tex> of <tex>B</tex> induced by <tex>\mathfrak {p}</tex>, which lives over <tex>\mathfrak {n}'</tex>, is necessarily maximal, and does not contain <tex>u</tex>, and is thus identical to <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex>.
    (We have just used the fact that <tex>u</tex> belongs to every maximal ideal of <tex>B</tex> that is distinct from <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex>).
    We now prove that <tex>BS'^{-1}</tex> is equal to <tex>B'S'^{-1}</tex>:
    since the former is finite over the latter, we can reduce, by Nakayama, to proving equality modulo <tex>\mathfrak {n}'BS'^{-1}</tex>, and, a fortiori, it suffices to prove equality modulo <tex>\mathfrak {m}BS'^{-1}</tex>;
    but <tex>BS'^{-1}/ \mathfrak {m}BS'^{-1}=B_ \mathfrak {n}/ \mathfrak {m}B_ \mathfrak {n}</tex> is generated, over <tex>k</tex>, by <tex>u</tex> (here we use the other property of <tex>u</tex>), and so the image of <tex>B'</tex> (and, a fortiori, of <tex>B'S'^{-1}</tex>) inside is everything (as a sub-ring that contains <tex>k</tex> and the image of <tex>u</tex>.)
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5114</anchor> <taxon>Remark</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    We must be able to state <ref addr="sga1-i.7.6" href="sga1-i.7.6.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.7.6"/> for a ring <tex>\mathcal { O }</tex> that is only semi-local, so that we also cover <ref addr="sga1-i.7.5" href="sga1-i.7.5.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.7.5"/>:
    we make the hypothesis that <tex>\mathcal { O } / \mathfrak {m} \mathcal { O }</tex> is a <em>monogenous</em> <tex>k</tex>-algebra;
    we can thus find some <tex>u \in  B</tex> whose image in <tex>B/ \mathfrak {m}B</tex> is a generator, and belongs to every maximal ideal of <tex>B</tex> that doesn't come from <tex>\mathcal { O }</tex>.
    Both <ref addr="sga1-i.7.9" href="sga1-i.7.9.xml" taxon="Lemma" number="I.7.9"/> and <ref addr="sga1-i.7.10" href="sga1-i.7.10.xml" taxon="Lemma" number="I.7.10"/> should be able to be adapted without difficulty.
    More generally, ...
  </p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="true" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5115</anchor> <taxon>Section</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.8</addr><route>sga1-i.8.xml</route>    <title>Infinitesimal lifting of étale schemes. Applications to formal schemes</title> <number>I.8</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5116</anchor> <taxon>Proposition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.8.1</addr><route>sga1-i.8.1.xml</route>     <number>I.8.1</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>Y</tex> be a prescheme, <tex>Y_0</tex> a sub-prescheme, <tex>X_0</tex> an étale <tex>Y_0</tex>-scheme, and <tex>x</tex> a point of <tex>X_0</tex>.
    Then there exists an étale <tex>Y</tex>-scheme <tex>X</tex>, a neighbourhood <tex>U_0</tex> of <tex>x</tex> in <tex>X_0</tex>, and a <tex>Y_0</tex>-isomorphism <tex>U_0 \xrightarrow { \sim }X \times _Y Y_0</tex>.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5117</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      Let <tex>y</tex> be the projection of <tex>x</tex> in <tex>Y_0</tex>;
      applying <ref addr="sga1-i.7.6" href="sga1-i.7.6.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.7.6"/> to the étale local homomorphism <tex>A_0 \to  B_0</tex> of local rings of <tex>y</tex> and <tex>x</tex> in <tex>Y_0</tex> and <tex>X_0</tex>, we obtain an isomorphism
      <tex display="block">          \begin {aligned}           B_0 &amp;= (C_0)_{ \mathfrak {n}_0}          \\ C_0 &amp;= A_0[t]/F_0A_0[t]          \end {aligned}       </tex>
      where <tex>F_0</tex> is a monic polynomial, and <tex>\mathfrak {n}_0</tex> is a maximal ideal of <tex>C_0</tex> not containing the class of <tex>F'_0(t)</tex> in <tex>C_0</tex>.
      Let <tex>A</tex> be the local ring of <tex>y</tex> in <tex>Y</tex>, let <tex>F</tex> be a monic polynomial in <tex>A[t]</tex> that gives <tex>F_0</tex> under the surjective homomorphism <tex>A \to  A_0</tex> (we lift the coefficients of <tex>F_0</tex>), and let <tex>C=A[t]/FA[t]</tex>, with <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex> the maximal ideal of <tex>C</tex> given by the inverse image of <tex>\mathfrak {n}_0</tex> under the natural epimorphism <tex>C \to  C \otimes _A A_0=C_0</tex>.
      Let
      <tex display="block">         B = C_ \mathfrak {n}.       </tex>
      It is immediate, by construction and by <ref addr="sga1-i.7.1" href="sga1-i.7.1.xml" taxon="Proposition" number="I.7.1"/>, that <tex>B</tex> is étale over <tex>A</tex>, and that we have an isomorphism <tex>B \otimes _A A_0=A_0</tex>.
    </p>

    <p>
      We know that there exists a <tex>Y</tex>-scheme <tex>X</tex> of finite type, along with a point <tex>z</tex> of <tex>X</tex> over <tex>y</tex> such that <tex>\mathcal { O } _z</tex> is <tex>A</tex>-isomorphic to <tex>C</tex>;
      since the latter is étale over <tex>A= \mathcal { O } _y</tex>, we can (by taking <tex>X</tex> to be small enough) assume that <tex>X</tex> is étale over <tex>Y</tex>.
      Let <tex>X'_0=X \times _Y Y_0</tex>.
      Then the local ring of <tex>z</tex> in <tex>X'_0</tex> can be identified with <tex>\mathcal { O } _z \otimes _A A_0=B \otimes _A A_0</tex>, and is thus isomorphic to <tex>B_0</tex>.
      This isomorphism is defined by an isomorphism from a neighbourhood <tex>U_0</tex> of <tex>x</tex> in <tex>X</tex> to a neighbourhood of <tex>z</tex> in <tex>X'_0</tex>, and we can assume this to be identical to <tex>X'_0</tex> by taking <tex>X</tex> to be small enough.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5118</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.8.2</addr><route>sga1-i.8.2.xml</route>     <number>I.8.2</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    The analogous claim holds for étale <em>covers</em>, if we suppose the residue field <tex>k(y)</tex> to be infinite.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5119</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      The proof is the same, just replacing <ref addr="sga1-i.7.5" href="sga1-i.7.5.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.7.5"/> by <ref addr="sga1-i.7.6" href="sga1-i.7.6.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.7.6"/>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5120</anchor> <taxon>Theorem</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.8.3</addr><route>sga1-i.8.3.xml</route>     <number>I.8.3</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    The functor described in <ref addr="sga1-i.5.5" href="sga1-i.5.5.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.5.5"/> is an <em>equivalence</em> of <em>categories</em>.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5121</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    By <ref addr="sga1-i.5.5" href="sga1-i.5.5.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.5.5"/>, it remains only to show that every étale <tex>S_0</tex>-scheme <tex>X_0</tex> is isomorphic to an <tex>S_0</tex>-scheme <tex>X \times _S S_0</tex>, where <tex>X</tex> is an étale <tex>S</tex>-scheme.
    The underlying topological space of <tex>X</tex> must necessarily be identical to the one of <tex>X_0</tex>, and with <tex>X_0</tex> being identified with a closed sub-prescheme of <tex>X</tex>.
    The problem is thus equivalent to the following:
    find, on the underlying topological space <tex>|X_0|</tex> of <tex>X_0</tex>, a sheaf of algebras <tex>\mathcal { O } _X</tex> over <tex>f_0^*( \mathcal { O } _S)</tex> (where <tex>f_0</tex> is the projection <tex>X_0 \to  S_0</tex>, thought of here as a continuous map of the underlying spaces) that makes <tex>|X_0|</tex> an étale <tex>S</tex>-prescheme <tex>X</tex>, as well as an algebra homomorphism <tex>\mathcal { O } _X \to \mathcal { O } _{X_0}</tex> that is compatible with the homomorphism <tex>f_0^*( \mathcal { O } _S) \to  f_0^*( \mathcal { O } _{S_0})</tex> on the sheaves of scalars, and that induces an isomorphism <tex>\mathcal { O } _X \otimes _{f_0^*( \mathcal { O } _S)*}f_0^*( \mathcal { O } _{S_0}) \xrightarrow { \sim } \mathcal { O } _{X_0}</tex>.
    (Then <tex>X</tex> will be an étale <tex>S</tex>-prescheme that is reduced along <tex>X_0</tex>, and thus separated over <tex>S</tex>, since <tex>X_0</tex> is separated over <tex>S_0</tex>, and <tex>X</tex> satisfies all the desired properties).

    If <tex>(U_i)</tex> is an open cover of <tex>X_0</tex>, and if we find a solution to the problem on each of the <tex>U_i</tex>, then it follows from the uniqueness theorem <ref addr="sga1-i.5.5" href="sga1-i.5.5.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.5.5"/> that these solutions glue (i.e. the sheaves of algebras that they define, endowed with their augmentation homomorphisms, glue), and we claim that the ringed space thus constructed over <tex>S</tex> is an étale <tex>S</tex>-prescheme <tex>X</tex> endowed with an isomorphism <tex>X \times _S S_0 \xleftarrow { \sim }X_0</tex>.
    It thus suffices to find a solution locally, which we know is possible by <ref addr="sga1-i.8.1" href="sga1-i.8.1.xml" taxon="Proposition" number="I.8.1"/>.
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5122</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.8.4</addr><route>sga1-i.8.4.xml</route>     <number>I.8.4</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>S</tex> be a locally Noetherian formal prescheme, endowed with an ideal of definition <tex>\mathcal { J }</tex>, and let <tex>S_0=(|S|, \mathcal { O } _S/ \mathcal { J } )</tex> be the corresponding ordinary prescheme.
    Then the functor <tex>\mathfrak {X} \mapsto \mathfrak {X} \times _S S_0</tex> from the category of étale covers of <tex>S</tex> to the category of étale covers of <tex>S_0</tex> is an equivalence of categories.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5123</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      Of course, we define an étale cover of a <em>formal</em> prescheme <tex>S</tex> to be a cover of <tex>S</tex> (i.e a formal prescheme over <tex>S</tex> defined by a coherent sheaf of algebras <tex>\mathcal { B }</tex>) such that <tex>\mathcal { B }</tex> is <em>locally free</em>, and such that the residue fibres <tex>\mathcal { B } _s \otimes _{ \mathcal { O } _s}k(s)</tex> of <tex>\mathcal { B }</tex> are <em>separable</em> algebras over <tex>k(s)</tex>.
      If we denote by <tex>S_n</tex> the ordinary prescheme <tex>(|S|, \mathcal { O } _S/ \mathcal { J } ^{n+1})</tex>, then the data of a coherent sheaf of algebras <tex>\mathcal { B }</tex> on <tex>S</tex> is equivalent to the data of a sequence of coherent sheaves of algebras <tex>\mathcal { B } _n</tex> on the <tex>S_n</tex>, endowed with a transitive system of homomorphisms <tex>\mathcal { B } _m \to \mathcal { B } _n</tex> (for <tex>m \geq  n</tex>) defining the isomorphisms <tex>\mathcal { B } _m \otimes _{ \mathcal { O } _{S_m}} \mathcal { O } _{S_n} \xrightarrow { \sim } \mathcal { B } _n</tex>.
      It is immediate that <tex>\mathcal { B }</tex> is locally free if and only if the <tex>\mathcal { B } _n</tex> are locally free over the <tex>S_n</tex>, and that the separability condition is satisfied if and only if it is satisfied for <tex>\mathcal { B } _0</tex>, or for all the <tex>\mathcal { B } _n</tex>.
      Thus <tex>\mathcal { B }</tex> is étale over <tex>S</tex> if and only if the <tex>\mathcal { B } _n</tex> are étale over the <tex>S_n</tex>.
      Taking this into account, <ref addr="sga1-i.8.4" href="sga1-i.8.4.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.8.4"/> follows immediately from <ref addr="sga1-i.8.3" href="sga1-i.8.3.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.8.3"/>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5124</anchor> <taxon>Remark</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    It was not necessary to restrict ourselves to the case of <em>covers</em> in <ref addr="sga1-i.8.4" href="sga1-i.8.4.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.8.4"/>, but this is the only case that we will use for the moment.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="true" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5125</anchor> <taxon>Section</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.9</addr><route>sga1-i.9.xml</route>    <title>Invariance properties</title> <number>I.9</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
  Let <tex>A \to  B</tex> be a morphism that is local and étale;
  we study here some cases where a certain property of <tex>A</tex> implies the same property for <tex>B</tex>, or vice versa.
  A certain number of such propositions are already consequences of the simple fact that <tex>B</tex> is <em>quasi-finite</em> and <em>flat</em> over <tex>A</tex>, and we content ourselves with &quot;recalling&quot; some of them.
  <em><tex>A</tex> and <tex>B</tex> have the same Krull dimension, and the same depth</em> (Serre's &quot;cohomological codimension&quot;, in the more modern language).
  It also follows, for example, that <em><tex>A</tex> is Cohen–Macaulay if and only if <tex>B</tex> is</em>.
  Also, for any prime ideal <tex>\mathfrak {q}</tex> of <tex>B</tex> (inducing some <tex>\mathfrak {p}</tex> of <tex>A</tex>), <tex>B_ \mathfrak {q}</tex> is again quasi-finite and flat over <tex>A_ \mathfrak {p}</tex>, as long as we suppose that <tex>B</tex> is the localisation of an algebra of finite type over <tex>A</tex> (this follows from the fact that the set of points where a morphism of finite type is quasi-finite (resp. flat) is open);
  furthermore, <em>every</em> prime ideal <tex>\mathfrak {p}</tex> of <tex>A</tex> is induced by a prime ideal <tex>\mathfrak {q}</tex> of <tex>B</tex> (since <tex>B</tex> is <em>faithfully</em> flat over <tex>A</tex>).
  It thus follows, for example, that <em><tex>\mathfrak {q}</tex> and <tex>\mathfrak {p}</tex> have the same rank</em>;
  also, <em><tex>A</tex> has no embedded prime ideals if and only if <tex>B</tex> has none</em>.
</p><p>
  We will thus content ourselves with more specific propositions concerning the case of étale morphisms.
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5126</anchor> <taxon>Proposition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.9.1</addr><route>sga1-i.9.1.xml</route>     <number>I.9.1</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>A \to  B</tex> be an étale local homomorphism.
    For <tex>A</tex> to be regular, it is necessary and sufficient that <tex>B</tex> be regular.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5127</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      Let <tex>k</tex> be the residue field of <tex>A</tex>, and <tex>L</tex> the residue field of <tex>B</tex>.
      Since <tex>B</tex> is flat over <tex>A</tex>, and since <tex>L=B \otimes _A k</tex> (i.e. <tex>\mathfrak {n}= \mathfrak {m}B</tex>, where <tex>\mathfrak {m}</tex> and <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex> are the maximal ideals of <tex>A</tex> and <tex>B</tex> respectively), the <tex>\mathfrak {m}</tex>-adic filtration on <tex>B</tex> is identical to the <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex>-adic filtration, and
      <tex display="block">          \operatorname {gr} ^ \bullet (B) =  \operatorname {gr} ^ \bullet (A) \otimes _k L.       </tex>
      It follows that <tex>\operatorname {gr} ^ \bullet (B)</tex> is a polynomial algebra over <tex>L</tex> if and only if <tex>\operatorname {gr} ^ \bullet (A)</tex> is a polynomial algebra over <tex>K</tex>.
      (N.B. we have not used the fact that <tex>L/k</tex> is separable.)
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5128</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.9.2</addr><route>sga1-i.9.2.xml</route>     <number>I.9.2</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>f \colon  X \to  Y</tex> be an étale morphism.
    If <tex>Y</tex> is regular, then <tex>X</tex> is regular;
    the converse is true if <tex>f</tex> is surjective.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5129</anchor> <taxon>Proposition</taxon>      <number>I.9.2</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>f \colon  X \to  Y</tex> be an étale morphism.
    If <tex>Y</tex> is reduced, then <tex>X</tex> is reduced;
    the converse is true if <tex>f</tex> is surjective.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  This is equivalent to the following:
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5130</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.9.3</addr><route>sga1-i.9.3.xml</route>     <number>I.9.3</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>f \colon  A \to  B</tex> be an étale local homomorphism, with <tex>B</tex> isomorphic to the localisation of an <tex>A</tex>-algebra of finite type over <tex>A</tex>.
    For <tex>A</tex> to be reduced, it is necessary and sufficient that <tex>B</tex> be reduced.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5131</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      The necessity is trivial, since <tex>A \to  B</tex> is injective (since <tex>B</tex> is faithfully flat over <tex>A</tex>).
      For the sufficiency, let <tex>\mathfrak {p}_i</tex> be the minimal prime ideals of <tex>A</tex>.
      By hypothesis, the natural map <tex>A \to \prod _i A/ \mathfrak {p}_i</tex> is injective, and so tensoring with the flat <tex>A</tex>-module <tex>B</tex> gives that <tex>B \to \prod _i B/ \mathfrak {p}_iB</tex> is injective, and we can thus reduce to proving that the <tex>B/ \mathfrak {p}_iB</tex> are reduced.
      Since <tex>B/ \mathfrak {p}_iB</tex> is étale over <tex>A/ \mathfrak {p}_i</tex>, we can reduce to the case where <tex>A</tex> is integral.
      Let <tex>K</tex> be the field of fractions of <tex>A</tex>, so that <tex>A \to  K</tex> is injective, and thus so too is <tex>B \to  B \otimes _A K</tex> (since <tex>B</tex> is <tex>A</tex>-flat), and we can thus reduce to proving that <tex>B \otimes _A K</tex> is reduced.
      But <tex>B</tex> is the localisation of an <tex>A</tex>-algebra of finite type over <tex>A</tex>, and thus is the local ring of a point <tex>x</tex> of a scheme of finite type <tex>X= \operatorname {Spec} (C)</tex> over <tex>Y= \operatorname {Spec} (A)</tex> that is also <em>étale</em> over <tex>Y</tex>, so <tex>B \otimes _A K</tex> is a localisation (with respect to some suitable multiplicatively stable set) of the ring <tex>C \otimes _A K</tex> of <tex>X \otimes _A K</tex>.
      Since <tex>X \otimes _A K</tex> is étale over <tex>K</tex>, its ring is a finite product of fields (that are separable extensions of <tex>K</tex>), and thus so too is <tex>B \otimes _A K</tex>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5132</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.9.4</addr><route>sga1-i.9.4.xml</route>     <number>I.9.4</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>f \colon  A \to  B</tex> be an étale local homomorphism, with <tex>A</tex> analytically reduced (i.e. such that the completion <tex>\widehat {A}</tex> of <tex>A</tex> has no nilpotent elements).
    Then <tex>B</tex> is analytically reduced, and a fortiori reduced.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5133</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    Indeed, <tex>\widehat {B}</tex> is <em>finite</em> and étale over <tex>\widehat {A}</tex>;
    we can apply <ref addr="sga1-i.9.3" href="sga1-i.9.3.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.9.3"/>.
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5134</anchor> <taxon>Theorem</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.9.5</addr><route>sga1-i.9.5.xml</route>     <number>I.9.5</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>f \colon  A \to  B</tex> be a local homomorphism, with <tex>B</tex> isomorphic to the localisation of an <tex>A</tex>-algebra of finite type over <tex>A</tex>.
  </p><p><strong><em>TO-DO: the following list should be i, ii</em></strong></p><ol><li>
      If <tex>f</tex> is étale, then <tex>A</tex> is normal if and only if <tex>B</tex> is normal.
    </li>
    <li>
      If <tex>A</tex> is normal, then <tex>f</tex> is étale if and only if <tex>f</tex> is injective and unramified (and then <tex>B</tex> is normal, by (i)).
    </li></ol></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  We will give two different proofs of (i):
  the first using certain properties of quasi-finite flat morphisms (stated at the start of this section) and without using <ref addr="sga1-i.7.6" href="sga1-i.7.6.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.7.6"/> (and thus the Main Theorem);
  the second proof does the opposite.
  For (ii), it seems like we do indeed need the Main Theorem, no matter what.
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5135</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.9.5.i-proof-1</addr><route>sga1-i.9.5.i-proof-1.xml</route>    <title>First proof</title> <number>I.9.5.i</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    We use the following necessary and sufficient condition for a local Noetherian ring <tex>A</tex> of dimension <tex>\neq0</tex> to be normal.
  </p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5136</anchor>  <addr>sga1-i.9-serres-criterion</addr><route>sga1-i.9-serres-criterion.xml</route>    <title>Serre's criterion</title>   </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p><strong><em>TO-DO: the following list should be i, ii</em></strong></p><ol><li>
        For every rank-<tex>1</tex> prime ideal <tex>\mathfrak {p}</tex> of <tex>A</tex>, <tex>A_ \mathfrak {p}</tex> is normal (or, equivalently, regular);
      </li>
      <li>
        For every rank-<tex>\geq2</tex> prime ideal <tex>\mathfrak {p}</tex> of <tex>A</tex>, the depth of <tex>A_ \mathfrak {p}</tex> is <tex>\geq2</tex>.
        (cf. EGA IV 5.8.6.)</li></ol></mainmatter> </tree><p>
    We assume this criterion here, but it should also appear in the section on flatness.
    Its main advantage is that it does not suppose a priori that <tex>A</tex> is reduced, nor a fortiori that <tex>A</tex> is integral.
    Here, we can already suppose that <tex>\dim  A= \dim  B \neq0</tex>.
  </p><p>
    By the statements at the start of this section, the rank-<tex>1</tex> (resp. rank-<tex>\geq2</tex>) prime ideals <tex>\mathfrak {p}</tex> of <tex>A</tex> are exactly the intersections of <tex>A</tex> with the rank-<tex>1</tex> (resp. rank-<tex>\geq2</tex>) prime ideals <tex>\mathfrak {q}</tex> of <tex>B</tex>.
    Finally, if <tex>\mathfrak {p}</tex> and <tex>\mathfrak {q}</tex> correspond to one another, then <tex>B_ \mathfrak {q}</tex> is étale over <tex>A_ \mathfrak {p}</tex>, and thus of the same depth as <tex>A_ \mathfrak {p}</tex>, and is regular if and only if <tex>A_ \mathfrak {p}</tex> is (by <ref addr="sga1-i.9.1" href="sga1-i.9.1.xml" taxon="Proposition" number="I.9.1"/>).
    Applying <link href="sga1-i.9-serres-criterion.xml" type="local" addr="sga1-i.9-serres-criterion" title="SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group › Étale morphisms › Invariance properties › First proof › Serre's criterion">Serre's criterion</link>, we see that <tex>A</tex> is normal if and only if <tex>B</tex> is.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5137</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.9.5.i-proof-2</addr><route>sga1-i.9.5.i-proof-2.xml</route>    <title>Second proof</title> <number>I.9.5.i</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Suppose that <tex>B</tex> is normal, with field of fractions <tex>L</tex>;
    let <tex>K</tex> be the field of fractions of <tex>A</tex> (and note that <tex>A</tex> is integral, since <tex>B</tex> is integral).
    We have already seen, in the proof of <ref addr="sga1-i.9.3" href="sga1-i.9.3.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.9.3"/>, that <tex>B \otimes _A K</tex> is a finite product of fields;
    since it is contained in <tex>L</tex>, it is a field;
    since it contains <tex>B</tex>, it is equal to <tex>L</tex> itself.
    An element of <tex>K</tex> that is integral over <tex>A</tex> is integral over <tex>B</tex>, and is thus in <tex>B</tex>, since <tex>B</tex> is normal, and thus also in <tex>A</tex>, since <tex>B \cap  K=A</tex> (as follows from the fact that <tex>B</tex> is faithfully flat over <tex>A</tex>).
  </p><p>
    Now suppose that <tex>A</tex> is normal;
    we will prove that <tex>B</tex> is also normal.
    By <ref addr="sga1-i.7.6" href="sga1-i.7.6.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.7.6"/>, we have that <tex>B=B'_ \mathfrak {n}</tex>, where <tex>B'=A[t]/FA[t]</tex> (with <tex>F</tex> and <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex> as in <ref addr="sga1-i.7.6" href="sga1-i.7.6.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.7.6"/>).
    Thus <tex>L=B \otimes _A K</tex> is a localisation of <tex>B' \otimes _A K=K[t]/FK[t]</tex>, and also a product of fields (finite separable extensions of <tex>K</tex>).
    This latter product (<tex>B' \otimes _A K</tex>) is a direct factor of <tex>B'_K</tex> (since each time we localise an Artinian ring (here <tex>B'_K</tex>) with respect to a multiplicatively stable set), and thus corresponds to a decomposition <tex>F=F_1F_2</tex> in <tex>K[t]</tex>, with the generator of <tex>L</tex> corresponding to <tex>t</tex> being annihilated by <tex>F_1</tex>.
    But, <em>since <tex>A</tex> is normal, the <tex>F_i</tex> are in <tex>A[t]</tex></em> (supposing that they are monic).
    Note that <tex>B \to  L=B \otimes _A K</tex> is injective (since <tex>A \to  K</tex> is, since <tex>B</tex> is flat over <tex>A</tex>), and so <tex>F_1(u)=0</tex>, with <tex>u</tex> being the class of <tex>t</tex> in <tex>L</tex>.
    Suppose that <tex>F</tex> were of minimal degree;
    then it would follows that <tex>F_2=1</tex>.
    (N.B. we would have <tex>F'(u)=F'_1(u)F_2(u)+F_1(u)F'_2(u)=F'_1(u)F_2(u)</tex>, since <tex>F_1(u)=0</tex>, whence <tex>F'_1(u) \neq  0</tex> since <tex>F'(u) \neq0</tex>.)
    Thus
    <tex display="block">       L = B \otimes _A K = K[t]/FK[t]     </tex>
    and so <tex>F</tex> is a separable polynomial in <tex>K[T]</tex> (but evidently not necessarily in <tex>A[t]</tex>).
    (N.B. for now, we have only shown, essentially, that we can choose <tex>F</tex> and <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex> in <ref addr="sga1-i.7.6" href="sga1-i.7.6.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.7.6"/> such that, with the above notation, <tex>B' \to  B'_ \mathfrak {n}=B</tex> is <em>injective</em>;
    for this, we have used the fact that <tex>A</tex> is normal;
    I do not know if this remains true without this normality hypothesis).
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  Now recall the well-known lemma, taken from Serre's lectures last year:
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5138</anchor> <taxon>Lemma</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.9.6</addr><route>sga1-i.9.6.xml</route>     <number>I.9.6</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>K</tex> be a ring, <tex>F \in  K[t]</tex> a separable monic polynomial, <tex>L=K[t]/FK[t]</tex>, and <tex>u</tex> the class of <tex>t</tex> in <tex>L</tex> (so that <tex>F'(u)</tex> is an invertible element of <tex>L</tex>).
    Then
    <tex display="block">        \operatorname {tr} _{L/K} u^i/F'(u) =        \begin {cases}         0 &amp; \text {if }0 \leq  i&lt;n-1 \text {;}        \\ 1 &amp; \text {if }i=n-1        \end {cases}     </tex>
    where <tex>n= \deg  F</tex>.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5139</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.9.7</addr><route>sga1-i.9.7.xml</route>     <number>I.9.7</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    The determinant of the matrix <tex>(u^j \cdot  u^i/F'(u))_{0 \leq  i,j \leq  n-1}</tex> is equal to <tex>(-1)^{n(n-1)/2}</tex>, and thus invertible in every sub-ring <tex>A</tex> of <tex>K</tex>.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5140</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.9.8</addr><route>sga1-i.9.8.xml</route>     <number>I.9.8</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>A</tex> be a sub-ring of <tex>K</tex>, <tex>V</tex> the <tex>A</tex>-module generated by the <tex>u^i</tex> (for <tex>0 \leq  i \leq  n-1</tex>), and <tex>V'</tex> the sub-<tex>A</tex>-module of <tex>L</tex> consisting of the <tex>x \in  L</tex> such that <tex>\operatorname {tr} _{L/K}(xy) \in  A</tex> for all <tex>y \in  V</tex> (i.e. for <tex>y</tex> of the form <tex>u^i</tex>, for <tex>0 \leq  i \leq  n-1</tex>).
    Then <tex>V'</tex> is the <tex>A</tex>-module given by the basis <tex>u^i/F'(u)</tex> (for <tex>0 \leq  i \leq  n-1</tex>).
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5141</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.9.9</addr><route>sga1-i.9.9.xml</route>     <number>I.9.9</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Suppose that <tex>K</tex> is the field of fractions of an integral normal ring <tex>A</tex>, with the coefficients of <tex>F</tex> lying in <tex>A</tex>.
    Then, with the notation of <ref addr="sga1-i.9.8" href="sga1-i.9.8.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.9.8"/>, <tex>V'</tex> contains the normal closure <tex>A'</tex> of <tex>A</tex> in <tex>L</tex>, which is thus contained in <tex>A[u]/F'(u)</tex>, and a fortiori in <tex>A[u][F'(u)^{-1}]</tex>.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  We can apply <link href="sga1-i.9.9.xml" type="local" addr="sga1-i.9.9">the above corollary</link> to the situation that we have obtained in the proof: since <tex>F'(u)</tex> is invertible in <tex>B</tex>, and since <tex>B</tex> contains <tex>A[u]</tex>, <tex>B</tex> contains <tex>A'</tex>.
  By the Main Theorem (or by the fact that <tex>B=A[u]_ \mathfrak {n}</tex>), <tex>B</tex> is a localisation of <tex>A'</tex>.
  Since <tex>A'</tex> is normal, so too is <tex>B</tex>.
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5142</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.9.5.ii-proof</addr><route>sga1-i.9.5.ii-proof.xml</route>     <number>I.9.5.ii</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    We proceed as in the above proof to show that we can choose <tex>F</tex> in <ref addr="sga1-i.7.6" href="sga1-i.7.6.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.7.6"/> such that we again have
    <tex display="block">       L = B \otimes _A K = K[t]/FK[t]     </tex>
    The only obstacle a priori is that we can no longer prove that <tex>B \to  L</tex> is injective, since <tex>B</tex> is no longer assumed to be flat over <tex>A</tex>, and so we can only apply the same argument a priori to the image <tex>B_1</tex> of <tex>B</tex> under the aforementioned homomorphism.
    It immediately follows that <tex>B_1</tex> is flat over <tex>A</tex> (since it is the localisation of a free <tex>A</tex>-algebra).
    By <ref addr="sga1-i.4.8" href="sga1-i.4.8.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.4.8"/>, the morphism <tex>B \to  B_1</tex> is étale, and thus an isomorphism, which finishes the proof.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  (From an editorial point of view, we should perform the two proofs above, and place the formal calculations of the lemma and of its corollaries in a separate section).
</p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> <backmatter><contributions/> <context/> <related/> <backlinks><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5143</anchor>  <addr>sga1-foreword</addr><route>sga1-foreword.xml</route>    <title><link href="sga1.xml" type="local" addr="sga1" title="SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group">SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group</link> › Foreword</title>  <parent>sga1</parent> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
  Each of these written exposés covers the material of multiple consecutive oral exposés.
  It did not seem useful to make a note of the dates.
</p><p>
  Exposé VII, which is referenced at various points throughout Exposé VIII, has not been written by the speaker, who, in the oral conferences, was limited to outlining the language of descent in general categories, by working from a strictly utilitarian point of view and not entering into the logical difficulties that often arise due to this language.
  It seemed that a proper exposé of this language would go beyond the limits of these current notes, even if only due to length.
  For a proper exposé of the theory of descent, I refer the reader to an article in preparation by Jean Giraud.
  Whilst waiting for its appearance (it is now published: J. Giraud, “Méthode de la Descente”. <em>Bull. Soc. Math. France</em> <strong>2</strong> (1964), viii+150 p.), I think that an attentive reader will have no problems in supplementing, by their own means, the phantom references in Exposé VIII.
</p><p>
  Other oral exposés, found after Exposé XI, and to which there are references in certain places of the text, have also not been written down, and were meant to form the substance of an Exposé XII and an Exposé XIII.
  The first of these oral exposés covered, in the framework of schemes and analytic spaces with nilpotent elements (as introduced in the <em>Séminaire Cartan 1960/61</em>), the construction of the analytic space associated to a prescheme of locally finite type over a complete valuation field <tex>k</tex>, GAGA-type theorems in the case where <tex>k</tex> is the field of complex numbers, and the application to the comparison of the fundamental group defined by transcendental methods and the fundamental group studied in these notes (cf. A. Grothendieck, “Fondements de la Géométrie Algébrique”. <em>Séminaire Bourbaki</em> <strong>190</strong> (December 1959), page 10).
  The latter oral exposés outlined the generalisation of methods developed in the text for the study of coverings that admit moderate ramification, and of the structure of the fundamental group of a complete curve minus a finite number of points (cf. <em>loc. cit.</em> <strong>182</strong>, page 27, théorème 14).
  These exposés do not introduce any essentially new ideas, which is why it did not seem necessary to write them up properly before the appearance of the corresponding chapters of <em>Éléments de Géométrie Algébrique</em>.
  (They are included in the present volume in Exposé XII by Mme Raynaud with a different proof from the original given in the oral seminar (cf. <ref addr="sga1-introduction" href="sga1-introduction.xml"/>).)</p><p>
  However, the Lefschetz type theorems for the fundamental group and the Picard group, from both a local and a global point of view, were the subject of a separate seminar in 1962, which was completely written down and is available to read.
  (<em>Cohomologie étale des faisceaux cohérents et théorèmes de Lefschetz locaux et globaux</em> (SGA 2), appeared in North Holland Pub. Cie.)
  We point out that the results developed, both in the present <em>Séminaire</em> and the seminar from 1962, will be used in an essential manner in the appearance of many key results about the étale cohomology of preschemes, which will be the subject of a <em>Séminaire</em> (led by M. Artin and myself) in 1963/64, currently in preparation.
  (<em>Cohomologie étale des schémas</em> (SGA 4), to appear in the same series.)
  Exposés I to IV, which are of an essentially local nature, and very elementary, will be absorbed entirely by Chapter IV of <em>Éléments de Géométrie Algébrique</em>, of which the first part is being printed and will probably be published towards the end of 1964.
  They can, nevertheless, be useful for a reader who wants to catch up to speed with the essential properties of smooth, étale, or flat morphisms, before diving into the arcana of a systematic treatment.
  As for the other exposés, they will be absorbed into Chapter VIII of the <em>Éléments</em>, whose publication can barely even be contemplated for many years.
  (In fact, following a change to the initial plan for the <em>Éléments</em>, the study of the fundamental group has been postponed to a later chapter of the <em>Éléments</em>, cf. the Introduction <ref addr="sga1-introduction" href="sga1-introduction.xml"/> that precedes this Foreword.)</p><p><em>Bures, June 1963.</em></p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5144</anchor>  <addr>sga1-introduction</addr><route>sga1-introduction.xml</route>    <title><link href="sga1.xml" type="local" addr="sga1" title="SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group">SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group</link> › Introduction</title>  <parent>sga1</parent> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
  In the first section of this introduction, we give some details about the contents of the present volume; in the second, about the entirety of the <em>Séminaire de Géométrie Algébrique du Bois-Marie</em>, of which the present volume constitutes the first tome.
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5145</anchor>  <addr>sga1-introduction-1</addr><route>sga1-introduction-1.xml</route>     <number>1</number> <parent>sga1-introduction</parent> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    The present volume details the fundamentals of a theory of the fundamental group in algebraic geometry, from the &quot;Kroneckerian&quot; point of view, which allows us to treat the case of an algebraic variety, in the usual sense, and that of a ring of integers of a number field, for example, on an equal footing.
    This point of view can only be expressed in a satisfactory manner in the language of schemes, and we will freely use this language, as well as the main results stated in the first three chapters of the <em>Éléments de Géométrie Algébrique</em> by J. Dieudonné and A. Grothendieck (cited as &quot;EGA&quot;).
    The study of this present volume of the <em>Séminaire de Géométrie Algébrique du Bois-Marie</em> does not require any other knowledge of algebraic geometry, and can thus serve as an introduction to the current techniques of algebraic geometry to a reader who wishes to familiarise themselves with them.
  </p><p>
    Exposés I to XI of this book are a textual reproduction, practically unchanged, of the mimeographed notes from the oral seminar, which were distributed by the <em>Institut des Hautes Études Scientifiques</em>.
    (As well as the notes of the following seminars. Since this method of distribution turned out to be impractical and inadequate in the long term, all the <em>Séminaire de Géométrie Algébrique du Bois-Marie</em> from now on will appear in book form, like the present volume.)
    We have restricted ourselves to adding some footnotes to the original text, correcting typos, and making an adjustment to terminology (notably, &quot;simple morphism&quot; being replaced with &quot;smooth morphism&quot;, which does not lead to the same confusion).
  </p><p>
    Exposés I to IV present the local notions of <em>étale</em> and <em>smooth</em> morphisms;
    they hardly ever use the language of schemes, as detailed in Chapter I of the <em>Éléments</em>.
    (A more complete study is now available in EGA IV, 17 and 18.)
    Exposé V presents the axiomatic description of the fundamental group of a scheme, which is useful even in the classical case where the scheme is simply the spectrum of a field, since we then find a strong and convenient reformulation of usual Galois theory.
    Exposés VI and VIII present the <em>theory of descent</em>, which has become more and more important in algebraic geometry over the past few years, and which could do the same in analytic geometry and in topology.
    We note that Exposé VII was not transcribed, but its contents can be found incorporated into an article by J. Giraud (&quot;Méthode de la Descente&quot;. <em>Bull. Soc. Math. France</em> <strong>2</strong> (1964), viii+150 p.).
    In Exposé IX, we study more specifically the theory of descent by étale morphisms, obtaining a systematic approach for Van Kampen type theorems for the fundamental group, which appear here as simple translations of theorems of descent.
    This essentially involves a calculation of the fundamental group of a connected scheme <tex>X</tex> endowed with a surjective and proper morphism (say, <tex>X' \to  X</tex>) in terms of the fundamental groups of the connected components of <tex>X'</tex> and of the fibre products <tex>X' \times _X X'</tex>, <tex>X' \times _X X' \times _X X'</tex>, and the homomorphisms between these groups induced by the canonical simplicial morphisms between the above schemes.
    Exposé X gives the theory of <em>specialisation of the fundamental group</em> for a proper and smooth morphism, with the most striking result being the determination (more or less) of the fundamental group of a smooth algebraic curve in characteristic <tex>p&gt;0</tex>, thanks to the known result obtained by transcendental methods in characteristic zero.
    <tex>Exposé XI</tex> gives some examples and addenda, including a cohomological version of Kummer's theory of coverings, as well as Artin--Schreier's.
    For other commentaries on the text, see the Foreword <ref addr="sga1-foreword" href="sga1-foreword.xml"/>, found after this Introduction.
  </p><p>
    Since the writing of the seminar in 1961, the language of <em>étale topology</em>, along with a corresponding cohomology theory, has been developed by M. Artin in collaboration with myself;
    it is detailed in tome 4 (&quot;Cohomologie étale des schémas&quot;) of the <em>Séminaire de Géométrie Algébrique</em>, which will appear in the same series as the present volume.
    This language, as well as the results that it has given up until now, give us a particularly supple tool for the study of the fundamental group, allowing us to better understand (and even improve upon) certain results given here.
    There will thus be a need to entirely rewrite the theory of the fundamental group from this point of view (in fact, all the key results so far appear in <em>loc. cit.</em>).
    This was what was planed for the chapter of <em>Éléments</em> dedicated to the fundamental group, which also had to cover many other ideas which could not find their place here (relying on the technique of resolution of singularities):
    calculation of the &quot;local fundamental group&quot; of a complete local ring in terms of a suitable resolution of singularities of the ring, local and global Künneth formulas for the fundamental group without any hypotheses of properness (cf. Exposé XIII), the results of M. Artin on the comparison of the local fundamental groups of an excellent Henselian local ring and of its completion (SGA 4 XIX).
    We also note the necessity of developing a theory of the fundamental group of a topos, which would simultaneously cover the ordinary topological theory, the semi-simplicial version, the &quot;profinite&quot; version developed in Exposé V, and the slightly more general pro-discrete version found in [SGA 3 X 7] (adapted to the case of non-normal and non-unibranch schemes).
    While we wait for such a rewriting of the whole theory, Exposé XIII, by Mme Raynaud, using the language and results of SGA 4, aims to show the part that we can extract in some typical questions, most notably generalising certain results of Exposé X to non-proper relative schemes.
    There we give, in particular, the structure of the &quot;prime at <tex>p</tex>&quot; fundamental group of a non-complete algebraic curve in arbitrary characteristic (which I announced in 1959, but for which a proof had not been published up until now).
  </p><p>
    Despite these numerous gaps and imperfections (as others would say: because of these gaps and imperfections), I think that the present volume could be useful for the reader who wishes to familiarise themselves with the theory of the fundamental group, as well as a work of reference, while we await the writing and appearance of a text that avoids the criticisms that I have just listed.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5146</anchor>  <addr>sga1-introduction-2</addr><route>sga1-introduction-2.xml</route>     <number>2</number> <parent>sga1-introduction</parent> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    The present volume constitutes tome 1 of the <em>Séminaire de Géométrie Algébrique du Bois-Marie</em>, whose following volumes are intended to appear in the same series as this one.
    The aim of the <em>Séminaire</em>, parallel to the <em>Éléments de Géométrie Algébrique</em> by J. Dieudonné and A. Grothendieck, is to establish the fundamentals of algebraic geometry, following the points of view of the latter.
    The standard reference for all the volumes of the <em>Séminaire</em> consists of Chapters I, II, and III of <em>Éléments de Géométrie Algébrique</em> (cited as EGA I, II, and III), and we assume the reader to be have the education in commutative algebra and homological algebra that these chapters imply.
    (See the Introduction of EGA I for more precise details.)
    Furthermore, in each volume of the <em>Séminaire</em>, we will freely refer as needed to previous volumes of the same <em>Séminaire</em>, or to other chapters of <em>Éléments</em>, either already published or on the brink of being published.
  </p><p>
    Each <em>volume</em> of the <em>Séminaire</em> is based on a main subject, indicated in the title of the corresponding volume(s);
    the oral seminar generally lasts one academic year, sometimes more.
    The exposés within each volume of the <em>Séminaire</em> are generally in a logical order of dependence on one another;
    however, the different volumes of the <em>Séminaire</em> are largely logically independent of one another.
    So the volume &quot;Group schemes&quot; is largely logically independent of the two volumes of the <em>Séminaire</em> that come before it chronologically;
    however, it makes frequent reference to results of EGA IV.
    Here is the list of the volumes of the <em>Séminaire</em> that should appear (cited as SGA I to SGA 7 in what follows):
  </p><ul><li><strong>SGA 1.</strong>
      Étale covers and the fundamental group, 1960/61.
    </li>
    <li><strong>SGA 2.</strong>
      Local cohomology of coherent sheaves and local and global Lefschetz theorems, 1961/62.
    </li>
    <li><strong>SGA 3.</strong>
      Group schemes, 1963/64 (3 volumes, in collaboration with M. Demazure).
    </li>
    <li><strong>SGA 4.</strong>
      Topos theory and étale cohomology of schemes, 1963/64 (3 volumes, in collaboration with M. Artin and J.L. Verdier).
    </li>
    <li><strong>SGA 5.</strong>
      <tex>\ell</tex>-adic cohomology and <tex>L</tex>-functions, 1964/65 (2 volumes).
    </li>
    <li><strong>SGA 6.</strong>
      Intersection theory and the Riemann--Roch theorem, 1966/67 (2 volumes, in collaboration with P. Berthelot and L. Illusie).
    </li>
    <li><strong>SGA 7.</strong>
      Local monodromy groups in algebraic geometry.
    </li></ul><p>
    Three of these partial <em>Séminaires</em> have been written in <em>collaboration</em> with other mathematicians, who appear as coauthors on the covers of the corresponding volumes.
    As for the other active participants of the <em>Séminaire</em>, whose roles (from as much of an editorial point of view as a mathematical one) have grown over the years, the name of each participant appears at the top of the exposés for which they are responsible, either as speaker or as writer, and the list of those who appear in a given volume can be found on the flyleaf of the volume in question.
  </p><p>
    It is useful to give some precise remarks concerning the relation between the <em>Séminaire</em> and the <em>Éléments</em>.
    The latter was intended, in principle, to give an exposé of a set of ideas and techniques that were judged to be the most fundamental in Algebraic Geometry, as these ideas and techniques emerge all by themselves from the natural requirements of logical and aesthetic coherence.
    From this point of view, it was natural to consider the <em>Séminaire</em> as a preliminary version of the <em>Éléments</em>, destined to be included almost entirely, sooner or later, in the latter.
    This process had already somewhat started a few years ago, since Exposés I to IV of the current volume (SGA 1) are entirely covered by EGA IV, and Exposés VI to VIII should be, in some years, in EGA VI.
    However, given how the work in constructing the <em>Éléments</em> and the <em>Séminaire</em> is developing, and as the proportions of the two become more precise, the initial principle (that the <em>Séminaire</em> should be only a preliminary and provisional version) seems less and less realistic, for the reason (amongst others) of the limits imposed by the long-sighted nature of the length of the human life.
    Taking into account the care that is generally given to the writing of the various parts of the <em>Séminaire</em>, there will doubtless be no need to go back over them in the <em>Éléments</em> (or other treaties that would take over from it) until further progress in the writing process would allow us to make very substantial improvements, at the cost of rather big changes.
    This is the case as of now for the current seminar SGA 1, as we said above, and also for SGA 2 (thanks to recent results by Mme. Raynaud).
    However, nothing currently indicates that this will also be the case in the near future for any of the other parts mentioned above (SGA 3 to SGA 7).
  </p><p><em>[Trans.] We omit one paragraph from this translation since it simply describes the citation and cross-reference formatting of the book, which we do not precisely follow here.</em></p><p>
    Finally, for the ease of the reader, every time that it seems necessary, at the end of the volumes of the SGA we attach an index of notation and an index of terminology containing, if necessary, an English translation of the French terms used.
  </p><p>
    I want to add an extra-mathematical comment to this introduction.
    In the month of November, 1969, I discovered that the Institut des Hautes Études Scientifiques, where I have been a professor essentially since its founding, had been receiving subventions from the Ministère des Armées for three years.
    Already as a young researcher, I found it extremely regrettable how few qualms the majority of scientists had in agreeing to collaborate in one form or another with military institutions.
    My motivations back then were essentially of a moral nature, and thus not very likely to be taken seriously.
    Today they acquire a new force and dimension, given the danger of destruction of the human species threatened by the proliferation of military institutions and of the means of mass destruction that they posses.
    I have explained my thoughts on these problems, which are much more important than the advancement of any of the sciences (mathematics included), in more detail in other places;
    the reader can, for example, consult the article by G. Edwards in the Volume 1 of the journal <em>Survivre</em> (August, 1970), which gives a more detailed summary of these problems than I have done elsewhere.
    So I found myself working for three years at an institution even though it was, unbeknownst to me, participating in a financing model that I consider immoral and dangerous.
    (It goes without saying that the opinion that I express here is entirely my own, and not that of the publishing house Springer, which is editing this volume.)
    Being currently the only person to have this opinion amongst my colleagues at the IHES, which has condemned to fail my efforts to suppress military subventions from the IHES budget, I have taken the necessary decision to leave the IHES on the 30th of September, 1970, and to equally suspend all scientific collaboration with this institute for as long as it continues to accept such subventions.
    I have asked M. Motchane, the director of the IHES, for the IHES to abstain, starting from the 1st of October, 1970, from sharing mathematical texts of which I am an author, or which form part of the <em>Séminaire de Géométrie Algébrique du Bois-Marie</em>.
    As was mentioned above, the diffusion of this seminar will be undertaken by the publishing house Julius Springer, in the <em>Lecture Notes</em> series.
    I am happy to thank here Springer and Mr. K. Peters for the efficient and polite help that they have given me in making this publication possible, in particular for dealing with the typing of the photo-offset of new exposés added to old seminars, and of missing exposés in incomplete seminars.
  </p><p>
    I equally thank Mr. J.P. Delale, who had the thankless job of compiling the index of notation and the index of terminology.
  </p><p><em>Massy, August 1970.</em></p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5147</anchor>  <addr>index</addr><route>index.xml</route>    <title>Séminaire de Géométrie Algébrique du Bois-Marie</title>   </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
  You can view the entire source code of this translation (and contribute or submit corrections) in the <link href="https://github.com/thosgood/sga" type="external">GitHub repository</link>.
</p><p><strong><em>TO-DO: describe this translation</em></strong></p><p>
  Many thanks to <link href="https://www.jonmsterling.com/index.xml" type="external">Jon Sterling</link> for helping with the technical support in getting this translation ported to run on <link href="https://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml" type="external">Forester</link>.
</p><ul><li><link href="sga1.xml" type="local" addr="sga1" title="SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group"><strong>SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group</strong></link>

    <p>
      Directed by A. Grothendieck.
      Augmented with two exposés by Mme M. Raynaud.
      1960–61.
      <link href="https://arxiv.org/abs/math/0206203v2" type="external">arXiv:math/0206203v2</link></p>

    <ul><li><link href="sga1-introduction.xml" type="local" addr="sga1-introduction" title="SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group › Introduction">Introduction</link> ✓
      </li>
      <li><link href="sga1-foreword.xml" type="local" addr="sga1-foreword" title="SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group › Foreword">Foreword</link> ✓
      </li>
      <li><link href="sga1-i.xml" type="local" addr="sga1-i" title="SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group › Étale morphisms">I. Étale morphisms</link> ✓
      </li></ul></li>
  <li><link href="sga6.xml" type="local" addr="sga6" title="SGA 6: Intersection theory and the Riemann–Roch theorem"><strong>SGA 6: Intersection theory and the Riemann–Roch theorem</strong></link>

    <p>
      Directed by P. Berthelot, A. Grothendieck, and L. Illusie.
      With the collaboration of D. Ferrand, J.P. Jouanolou, O. Jussila, S. Kleiman, M. Raynaud, and J.P. Serre.
      1966–67.
    </p>

    <ul><li><link href="sga6-introduction.xml" type="local" addr="sga6-introduction" title="SGA 6: Intersection theory and the Riemann–Roch theorem › Introduction">Introduction</link></li>
      <li><link href="sga6-0.xml" type="local" addr="sga6-0" title="SGA 6: Intersection theory and the Riemann–Roch theorem › Outline of a programme for a theory of intersections">0. Outline of a programme for an intersection theory</link></li>
      <li><link href="sga6-0rrr.xml" type="local" addr="sga6-0rrr" title="SGA 6: Intersection theory and the Riemann–Roch theorem › Classes of sheaves and the Riemann–Roch theorem">0[RRR]. Classes of sheaves and the Riemann–Roch theorem</link></li>
      <li><link href="sga6-i.xml" type="local" addr="sga6-i" title="SGA 6: Intersection theory and the Riemann–Roch theorem › Generalities on finiteness conditions in derived categories">I. Generalities on finiteness conditions in derived categories</link></li></ul></li></ul></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5148</anchor> <taxon>Exposé</taxon> <addr>sga1-i</addr><route>sga1-i.xml</route>    <title><link href="sga1.xml" type="local" addr="sga1" title="SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group">SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group</link> › Étale morphisms</title> <number>I</number> <parent>sga1</parent> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
  To simplify the exposition, we assume that all preschemes in the following are locally Noetherian (at least, starting from <ref addr="sga1-i.2" href="sga1-i.2.xml" taxon="Section" number="I.2"/>).
</p><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="true" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5149</anchor> <taxon>Section</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.1</addr><route>sga1-i.1.xml</route>    <title><link href="sga1-i.xml" type="local" addr="sga1-i" title="SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group › Étale morphisms"><link href="sga1.xml" type="local" addr="sga1" title="SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group">SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group</link> › Étale morphisms</link> › Basics of differential calculus</title> <number>I.1</number> <parent>sga1-i</parent> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
  Let <tex>X</tex> be a prescheme over <tex>Y</tex>, and <tex>\Delta _{X/Y}</tex> the diagonal morphism <tex>X \to  X \times _Y X</tex>.
  This is an immersion, and thus a closed immersion of <tex>X</tex> into an open subset <tex>V</tex> of <tex>X \times _Y X</tex>.
  Let <tex>\mathcal { I } _X</tex> be the ideal of the closed sub-prescheme corresponding to the diagonal in <tex>V</tex> (N.B. if one really wishes to do things intrinsically, without assuming that <tex>X</tex> is separated over <tex>Y</tex> — a misleading hypothesis — then one should consider the set-theoretic inverse image of <tex>\mathcal { O } _{X \times  X}</tex> in <tex>X</tex> and denote by <tex>\mathcal { I } _X</tex> the augmentation ideal in the above ...).
  The sheaf <tex>\mathcal { I } _X/ \mathcal { I } _X^2</tex> can be thought of as a quasi-coherent sheaf on <tex>X</tex>, which we denote by <tex>\Omega _{X/Y}^1</tex>.
  This sheaf is of finite type if <tex>X \to  Y</tex> is of finite type, and it behaves well with respect to a base change <tex>Y' \to  Y</tex>.
  We also introduce the sheaves <tex>\mathcal { O } _{X \times _Y X}/ \mathcal { I } _X^{n+1}= \mathcal { P } ^n_{X/Y}</tex>, which are sheaves of <em>rings</em> on <tex>X</tex>, giving us preschemes denoted by <tex>\Delta _{X/Y}^n</tex> and called the <em><tex>n</tex>-th infinitesimal neighbourhood of <tex>X/Y</tex></em>.
  The polysyllogism is entirely trivial, even if rather long (cf. EGA IV 16.3);
  it seems wise to not discuss it until we use it for something helpful, with smooth morphisms.
</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="true" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5150</anchor> <taxon>Section</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.2</addr><route>sga1-i.2.xml</route>    <title><link href="sga1-i.xml" type="local" addr="sga1-i" title="SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group › Étale morphisms"><link href="sga1.xml" type="local" addr="sga1" title="SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group">SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group</link> › Étale morphisms</link> › Quasi-finite morphisms</title> <number>I.2</number> <parent>sga1-i</parent> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5151</anchor> <taxon>Proposition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.2.1</addr><route>sga1-i.2.1.xml</route>     <number>I.2.1</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>A \to  B</tex> be a local homomorphism (N.B. all rings are now Noetherian), and let <tex>\mathfrak {m}</tex> be the maximal ideal of <tex>A</tex>.
    Then the following conditions are equivalent:
  </p><p><strong><em>TO-DO: the following list should be i, ii, etc</em></strong></p><ol><li><tex>B/ \mathfrak {m}B</tex> is of finite dimension over <tex>k=A/ \mathfrak {m}</tex>.
    </li>
    <li><tex>\mathfrak {m}B</tex> is an ideal of definition, and <tex>B/ \mathfrak {r}(B)=k(B)</tex> is an extension of <tex>k=k(A)</tex>.
    </li>
    <li>
      The completion <tex>\widehat {B}</tex> of <tex>B</tex> is finite over the completion <tex>\widehat {A}</tex> of <tex>A</tex>.
    </li></ol></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  If the conditions of <ref addr="sga1-i.2.1" href="sga1-i.2.1.xml" taxon="Proposition" number="I.2.1"/> are satisfied, then we say that <tex>B</tex> is <em>quasi-finite</em> over <tex>A</tex>.
  A morphism <tex>f \colon  X \to  Y</tex> is said to be quasi-finite at <tex>x</tex> (or the <tex>Y</tex>-prescheme <tex>f</tex> is said to be quasi-finite at <tex>x</tex>) if <tex>\mathcal { O } _x</tex> is quasi-finite over <tex>\mathcal { O } _{f(x)}</tex>.
  This is equivalent to saying that <tex>x</tex> is <em>isolated in its fibre <tex>f^{-1}(x)</tex></em>.
  A morphism is said to be quasi-finite if it is quasi-finite at each point.
  (In [EGA II 6.2.3] we further suppose that <tex>f</tex> is of finite type.)
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5152</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.2.2</addr><route>sga1-i.2.2.xml</route>     <number>I.2.2</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    If <tex>A</tex> is complete, then quasi-finiteness is equivalent to finiteness.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  We could also give the usual polysyllogism (i), (ii), (iii), (iv), (v) for quasi-finite morphisms, but that doesn't seem necessary here.
</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="true" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5153</anchor> <taxon>Section</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.3</addr><route>sga1-i.3.xml</route>    <title><link href="sga1-i.xml" type="local" addr="sga1-i" title="SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group › Étale morphisms"><link href="sga1.xml" type="local" addr="sga1" title="SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group">SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group</link> › Étale morphisms</link> › Unramified morphisms</title> <number>I.3</number> <parent>sga1-i</parent> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5154</anchor> <taxon>Proposition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.3.1</addr><route>sga1-i.3.1.xml</route>     <number>I.3.1</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>f \colon  X \to  Y</tex> be a morphism of finite type, <tex>x \in  X</tex>, and <tex>y=f(x)</tex>.
    Then the following conditions are equivalent:
  </p><p><strong><em>TO-DO: the following list should be i, ii, etc</em></strong></p><ol><li><tex>\mathcal { O } _x/ \mathfrak {m}_y \mathcal { O } _x</tex> is a finite separable extension of <tex>k(y)</tex>.
    </li>
    <li><tex>\Omega _{X/Y}^1</tex> is zero at <tex>x</tex>.
    </li>
    <li>
      The diagonal morphism <tex>\Delta _{X/Y}</tex> is an open immersion on a neighbourhood of <tex>x</tex>.
    </li></ol>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5155</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      For the implication (i) <tex>\implies</tex> (ii), we can use Nakayama to reduce to the case where <tex>Y= \operatorname {Spec} (k)</tex> and <tex>X= \operatorname {Spec} (k')</tex>, where it is well known, and also trivial by the definition of separable;
      (ii) <tex>\implies</tex> (iii) comes from a nice and easy characterisation of open immersions, using Krull;
      (iii) <tex>\implies</tex> (i) follows as well from reducing to the case where <tex>Y= \operatorname {Spec} (k)</tex> and the diagonal morphism is everywhere an open immersion.
      We must then prove that <tex>X</tex> is finite with separable ring over <tex>k</tex>, and this leads us to consider the case where <tex>k</tex> is algebraically closed.
      But then every closed point of <tex>X</tex> is isolated (since it is identical to the inverse image of the diagonal by the morphism <tex>X \to  X \times _k X</tex> defined by <tex>x</tex>), whence <tex>X</tex> is finite.
      We can thus suppose that <tex>X</tex> consists of a single point, with ring <tex>A</tex>, and so <tex>A \otimes _k A \to  A</tex> is an isomorphism, hence <tex>A=k</tex>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5156</anchor> <taxon>Definition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.3.2</addr><route>sga1-i.3.2.xml</route>     <number>I.3.2</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p><strong><em>TO-DO: the following list should be a, b</em></strong></p><ol><li>
      Let <tex>f</tex> satisfy one of the equivalent conditions of <ref addr="sga1-i.3.1" href="sga1-i.3.1.xml" taxon="Proposition" number="I.3.1"/>.
      Then we say that <tex>f</tex> is <em>unramified</em> at <tex>x</tex>, or that <tex>X</tex> is unramified at <tex>x</tex> on <tex>Y</tex>.
    </li>
    <li>
      Let <tex>A \to  B</tex> be a local homomorphism.
      We say that it is <em>unramified</em>, or that <tex>B</tex> is a local <em>unramified</em> algebra on <tex>A</tex>, if <tex>B/ \mathfrak {r}(A)B</tex> is a finite separable extension of <tex>A/ \mathfrak {r}(A)</tex>, i.e. if <tex>\mathfrak {r}(A)B= \mathfrak {r}(B)</tex> and <tex>k(B)</tex> is a separable extension of <tex>k(A)</tex>.
      (cf. regrets in [III 1.2])
    </li></ol></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5157</anchor> <taxon>Remarks</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    The fact that <tex>B</tex> is unramified over <tex>A</tex> can be seen at the level of the completions of <tex>A</tex> and <tex>B</tex>.
    Unramified implies quasi-finite.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5158</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.3.3</addr><route>sga1-i.3.3.xml</route>     <number>I.3.3</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    The set of points where <tex>f</tex> is unramified is open.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5159</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.3.4</addr><route>sga1-i.3.4.xml</route>     <number>I.3.4</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>X'</tex> and <tex>X</tex> be preschemes of finite type over <tex>Y</tex>, and <tex>g \colon  X' \to  X</tex> a <tex>Y</tex>-morphism.
    If <tex>X</tex> is unramified over <tex>Y</tex>, then the graph morphism <tex>\Gamma _g \colon  X' \to  X \times _Y X</tex> is an open immersion.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  Indeed, this is the inverse image of the diagonal morphism <tex>X \to  X \times _Y X</tex> by
  <tex display="block">g \times _Y  \mathrm {id} _{X'} \colon  X' \times _Y X \to  X \times _Y X.</tex>
  One can also introduce the annihilator ideal <tex>\mathfrak {d}_{X/Y}</tex> of <tex>\Omega _{X/Y}^1</tex>, called the <em>different ideal</em> of <tex>X/Y</tex>;
  it defines a closed sub-prescheme of <tex>X</tex> which, set-theoretically, is the set of point where <tex>X/Y</tex> is ramified, i.e. not unramified.
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5160</anchor> <taxon>Proposition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.3.5</addr><route>sga1-i.3.5.xml</route>     <number>I.3.5</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p><strong><em>TO-DO: the following list should be i, ii, etc</em></strong></p><ol><li>
      An immersion is ramified.
    </li>
    <li>
      The composition of two ramified morphisms is also ramified.
    </li>
    <li>
      Base extension of a ramified morphisms is also ramified.
    </li></ol></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  We are rather indifferent about (ii) and (iii) (the second seems more interesting to me).
  We can, of course, also be more precise, by giving some one-off statements;
  this is more general only in appearance (except for in the case of definition (b)), and is boring.
  We obtain, as per usual, the corollaries:
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5161</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.3.6</addr><route>sga1-i.3.6.xml</route>     <number>I.3.6</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p><strong><em>TO-DO: the following list should be iv, v, etc</em></strong></p><ol><li>
      The cartesian product of two unramified morphisms is unramified.
    </li>
    <li>
      If <tex>gf</tex> is unramified then so too is <tex>f</tex>.
    </li>
    <li>
      If <tex>f</tex> is unramified then so too is <tex>f_ \mathrm {red}</tex>.
    </li></ol></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5162</anchor> <taxon>Proposition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.3.7</addr><route>sga1-i.3.7.xml</route>     <number>I.3.7</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>A \to  B</tex> be a local homomorphism, and suppose that the residue extension <tex>k(B)/k(A)</tex> is trivial, with <tex>k(A)</tex> algebraically closed.
    In order for <tex>B/A</tex> to be unramified, it is necessary and sufficient that <tex>\widehat {B}</tex> be (as an <tex>\widehat {A}</tex>-algebra) a quotient of <tex>\widehat {A}</tex>.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5163</anchor> <taxon>Remarks</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter><ul><li>
      In the case where we don't suppose that the residue extension is trivial, we can reduce to the case where it is by taking a suitable finite flat extension of <tex>A</tex> which destroys the aforementioned extension.
    </li>
    <li>
      Consider the example where <tex>A</tex> is the local ring of an ordinary double point of a curve, and <tex>B</tex> a point of its normalisation:
      then <tex>A \subset  B</tex>, <tex>B</tex> is unramified over <tex>A</tex> with trivial residue extension, and <tex>\widehat {A} \to \widehat {B}</tex> is surjective but <em>not injective</em>.
      We are thus going to strengthen the notion of unramified-ness.
    </li></ul></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="true" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5164</anchor> <taxon>Section</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.4</addr><route>sga1-i.4.xml</route>    <title><link href="sga1-i.xml" type="local" addr="sga1-i" title="SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group › Étale morphisms"><link href="sga1.xml" type="local" addr="sga1" title="SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group">SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group</link> › Étale morphisms</link> › Étale morphisms. Étale covers</title> <number>I.4</number> <parent>sga1-i</parent> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><strong><em>TO-DO: fix the auto-capitalisation of the title not recognising É</em></strong><p>
  We are going to suppose that everything concerning flat morphisms that we need to be true is indeed true;
  these facts will be proved later, if there is time.
  (cf. [sga1-iv <strong>(?)</strong>].)</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5165</anchor> <taxon>Definition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.4.1</addr><route>sga1-i.4.1.xml</route>     <number>I.4.1</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><strong><em>TO-DO: this list should be a, b</em></strong><ol><li>
      Let <tex>f \colon  X \to  Y</tex> be a morphism of finite type.
      We say that <tex>f</tex> is <em>étale</em> at <tex>x</tex> if <tex>f</tex> is both flat and unramified at <tex>x</tex>.
      We say that <tex>f</tex> is étale if it is étale at all points.
      We say that <tex>X</tex> is étale at <tex>x</tex> over <tex>Y</tex>, or that it is a <tex>Y</tex>-prescheme which is étale at <tex>x</tex> etc.
    </li>
    <li>
      Let <tex>f \colon  A \to  B</tex> be a local homomorphism.
      We say that <tex>f</tex> is étale, or that <tex>B</tex> is étale over <tex>A</tex>, if <tex>B</tex> is flat and unramified over <tex>A</tex>
      (cf. regrets in [sga1-iii.1.2 <strong>(?)</strong>].)</li></ol></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5166</anchor> <taxon>Proposition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.4.2</addr><route>sga1-i.4.2.xml</route>     <number>I.4.2</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    For <tex>B/A</tex> to be étale, it is necessary and sufficient that <tex>\widehat {B}/ \widehat {A}</tex> be étale.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5167</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      This is true individually for both &quot;unramified&quot; and &quot;flat&quot;.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5168</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.4.3</addr><route>sga1-i.4.3.xml</route>     <number>I.4.3</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>f \colon  X \to  Y</tex> be of finite type, and <tex>x \in  X</tex>.
    The property of <tex>f</tex> being étale at <tex>x</tex> depends only on the local homomorphism <tex>\mathcal { O } _{f(x)} \to \mathcal { O } _x</tex>, and in fact only on the corresponding homomorphism for the completions.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5169</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.4.4</addr><route>sga1-i.4.4.xml</route>     <number>I.4.4</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Suppose that the residue extension <tex>k(A) \to  k(B)</tex> is trivial, or that <tex>k(A)</tex> is algebraically closed.
    Then <tex>B/A</tex> is étale if and only if <tex>\widehat {A} \to \widehat {B}</tex> is an isomorphism.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  We can combine flatness with <ref addr="sga1-i.3.7" href="sga1-i.3.7.xml" taxon="Proposition" number="I.3.7"/>.
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5170</anchor> <taxon>Proposition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.4.5</addr><route>sga1-i.4.5.xml</route>     <number>I.4.5</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>f \colon  X \to  Y</tex> be a morphism of finite type.
    Then the set of points where <tex>f</tex> is étale is open.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5171</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      Again, this is true individually for both &quot;unramified&quot; and &quot;flat&quot;.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><p>
  This proposition shows that we can forget about the &quot;one-off&quot; comments in the study of morphisms of finite type that are somewhere étale.
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5172</anchor> <taxon>Proposition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.4.6</addr><route>sga1-i.4.6.xml</route>     <number>I.4.6</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><strong><em>TO-DO: this list should be i, ii etc</em></strong><ol><li>
      An open immersion is étale.
    </li>
    <li>
      The composition of two étale morphisms is étale.
    </li>
    <li>
      The base extension of an étale morphism is étale.
    </li></ol>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5173</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      Indeed, (i) is trivial, and for (ii) and (iii) it suffices to note that it is true for &quot;unramified&quot; and &quot;flat&quot;.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><p>
  As a matter of fact, there are also corresponding comments to make about local homomorphisms (without the finiteness condition), which in any case should appear in the multiplodoque (starting with the case of unramified).
  (<em>[Trans.] Grothendieck's &quot;multiplodoque d'algèbre homologique&quot; was the final version of his Tohoku paper — see (2.1) in &quot;Life and work of Alexander Grothendieck&quot; by Ching-Li Chan and Frans Oort for more information.</em>)</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5174</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.4.7</addr><route>sga1-i.4.7.xml</route>     <number>I.4.7</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    The cartesian product of two étale morphisms is étale.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5175</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.4.8</addr><route>sga1-i.4.8.xml</route>     <number>I.4.8</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>X</tex> and <tex>X'</tex> be of finite type over <tex>Y</tex>, and <tex>g \colon  X \to  X'</tex> a <tex>Y</tex>-morphism.
    If <tex>X'</tex> is unramified over <tex>Y</tex> and <tex>X</tex> is étale over <tex>Y</tex>, then <tex>g</tex> is étale.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5176</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      Indeed, <tex>g</tex> is the composition of the graph morphism <tex>\Gamma _g \colon  X \to  X \times _Y X'</tex> (which is an open immersion by <ref addr="sga1-i.3.4" href="sga1-i.3.4.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.3.4"/>) and the projection morphism, which is étale since it is just a &quot;change of base&quot; by <tex>X' \to  Y</tex> of the étale morphism <tex>X \to  Y</tex>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5177</anchor> <taxon>Definition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.4.9</addr><route>sga1-i.4.9.xml</route>     <number>I.4.9</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    We say that a cover of <tex>Y</tex> is étale (resp. unramified) if it is a <tex>Y</tex>-scheme <tex>X</tex> that is finite over <tex>Y</tex> and étale (resp. unramified) over <tex>Y</tex>.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  The first condition means that <tex>X</tex> is defined by a coherent sheaf of algebras <tex>\mathcal { B }</tex> over <tex>Y</tex>.
  The second means that <tex>\mathcal { B }</tex> is locally free over <tex>Y</tex> (resp. means absolutely nothing) <em>and</em>, further, that, for all <tex>y \in  Y</tex>, the fibre <tex>\mathcal { B } (y)= \mathcal { B } _y \otimes _{ \mathcal { O } _y}k(y)</tex> is a separable algebra (i.e. a finite composition of finite separable extensions) over <tex>k(y)</tex>.
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5178</anchor> <taxon>Proposition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.4.10</addr><route>sga1-i.4.10.xml</route>     <number>I.4.10</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>X</tex> be a flat cover of <tex>Y</tex> of degree <tex>n</tex> (the definition of this term deserved to figure in <ref addr="sga1-i.4.9" href="sga1-i.4.9.xml" taxon="Definition" number="I.4.9"/>) defined by a locally free coherent sheaf <tex>\mathcal { B }</tex> of algebras.
    We define, as usual, the trace homomorphism <tex>\mathcal { B } \to \mathcal { A }</tex> (that is, a homomorphism of <tex>\mathcal { A }</tex>-modules, where <tex>\mathcal { A } = \mathcal { O } _Y</tex>).
    For <tex>X</tex> to be étale it is necessary and sufficient that the corresponding bilinear form <tex>\operatorname {tr} _{ \mathcal { B } / \mathcal { A } }xy</tex> define an isomorphism of <tex>\mathcal { B }</tex> over <tex>\mathcal { B }</tex>, or, equivalently, that the <em>discriminant section</em>
    <tex display="block">       d_{X/Y}       = d_{ \mathcal { B } / \mathcal { A } }        \in   \Gamma \big (Y, \wedge ^n \check { \mathcal { B } } \otimes _ \mathcal { A } \wedge ^n \check { \mathcal { B } } \big )     </tex>
    is invertible, or that the discriminant ideal defined by this section is the unit ring.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5179</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      We can reduce to the case where <tex>Y= \operatorname {Spec} (k)</tex>, and then it is a well-known criterion of separability, and thus trivial by passing to the algebraic closure of <tex>k</tex>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5180</anchor> <taxon>Remark</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    We will have a less trivial statement to make later on, when we do not suppose a priori that <tex>X</tex> is flat over <tex>Y</tex>, but instead require some normality hypothesis.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="true" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5181</anchor> <taxon>Section</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.5</addr><route>sga1-i.5.xml</route>    <title><link href="sga1-i.xml" type="local" addr="sga1-i" title="SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group › Étale morphisms"><link href="sga1.xml" type="local" addr="sga1" title="SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group">SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group</link> › Étale morphisms</link> › Fundamental property of étale morphisms</title> <number>I.5</number> <parent>sga1-i</parent> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5182</anchor> <taxon>Theorem</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.5.1</addr><route>sga1-i.5.1.xml</route>     <number>I.5.1</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>f \colon  X \to  Y</tex> be a morphism of finite type.
    For <tex>f</tex> to be an open immersion, it is necessary and sufficient that it be <em>étale</em> and <em>radicial</em>.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5183</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      Recall what &quot;radicial&quot; means: injective, with radicial residual extensions (recall also that it means that the morphism remains injective under any base extension).
      The necessity is trivial, and the sufficiency remains to be shown.
      We are going to give two different proofs: the first is shorter, the second is more elementary.
    </p>

    <ol><li>
        A flat morphism is open, and so we can suppose (by replacing <tex>Y</tex> with <tex>f(X)</tex>) that <tex>f</tex> is an onto <em>homeomorphism</em>.
        For any base extension, it remains true that <tex>f</tex> is flat, radicial, and surjective, thus a homeomorphism, and a fortiori closed.
        Thus <tex>f</tex> is <em>proper</em>.
        Thus <tex>f</tex> is <em>finite</em> (reference: Chevalley's theorem), defined by a coherent sheaf <tex>\mathcal { B }</tex> of algebras.
        Now <tex>\mathcal { B }</tex> is locally free, and further, by hypothesis, of rank 1 everywhere, and so <tex>X=Y</tex>.
      </li>

      <li>
        We can suppose that <tex>Y</tex> and <tex>X</tex> are <em>affine</em>.
        We can further easily reduce to proving the following:
        if <tex>Y= \operatorname {Spec} (A)</tex>, with <tex>A</tex> local, and if <tex>f^{-1}(y)</tex> is non-empty (where <tex>y</tex> is the closed point of <tex>Y</tex>), then <tex>X=Y</tex> (indeed, this would imply that every <tex>y \in  f(X)</tex> has an open neighbourhood <tex>U</tex> such that <tex>X|U=U</tex>).
        We will then have that <tex>X= \operatorname {Spec} (B)</tex>, and wish to prove that <tex>A=B</tex>.
        But for this we can reduce to proving the analogous claim where we replace <tex>A</tex> by <tex>\widehat {A}</tex>, and <tex>B</tex> by <tex>B \otimes _A \widehat {A}</tex>
        (taking into account the fact that <tex>\widehat {A}</tex> is faithfully flat over <tex>A</tex>).
        We can thus suppose that <tex>A</tex> is <em>complete</em>.
        Let <tex>x</tex> be the point over <tex>y</tex>.
        By <ref addr="sga1-i.2.2" href="sga1-i.2.2.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.2.2"/>, <tex>\mathcal { O } _x</tex> is finite over <tex>A</tex>, and is thus (being flat and radicial over <tex>A</tex>) identical to <tex>A</tex>.
        So <tex>X=Y \coprod  X'</tex> (disjoint sum).
        But since <tex>X</tex> is radicial over <tex>Y</tex>, <tex>X'</tex> is empty.
      </li></ol>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5184</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.5.2</addr><route>sga1-i.5.2.xml</route>     <number>I.5.2</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>f \colon  X \to  Y</tex> be a morphism that is both a <em>closed immersion</em> and <em>étale</em>.
    If <tex>X</tex> is connected, then <tex>f</tex> is an isomorphism from <tex>X</tex> to a connected component of <tex>Y</tex>.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5185</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      Indeed, <tex>f</tex> is also an open immersion.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><p>
  We thus deduce:
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5186</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.5.3</addr><route>sga1-i.5.3.xml</route>     <number>I.5.3</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>X</tex> be an unramified <tex>Y</tex>-scheme, with <tex>Y</tex> connected.
    Then every section of <tex>X</tex> over <tex>Y</tex> is an isomorphism from <tex>Y</tex> to a connected component of <tex>X</tex>.
    There is thus a bijective correspondence between the set of such sections and the set of connected components <tex>X_i</tex> of <tex>X</tex> such that the projection <tex>X_i \to  Y</tex> is an isomorphism (or, equivalently, by <ref addr="sga1-i.5.1" href="sga1-i.5.1.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.5.1"/>, surjective and radicial).
    In particular, a section is determined by its value at a point.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5187</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      Only the first claim demands a proof;
      by <ref addr="sga1-i.5.2" href="sga1-i.5.2.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.5.2"/>, it suffices to note that a section is a closed immersion (since <tex>X</tex> is separated over <tex>Y</tex>) and also étale, by <ref addr="sga1-i.4.8" href="sga1-i.4.8.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.4.8"/>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5188</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.5.4</addr><route>sga1-i.5.4.xml</route>     <number>I.5.4</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>X</tex> and <tex>Y</tex> be preschemes over <tex>S</tex>, with <tex>X</tex> unramified and separated over <tex>S</tex>, and <tex>Y</tex> connected.
    Let <tex>f</tex> and <tex>g</tex> be <tex>S</tex>-morphisms from <tex>Y</tex> to <tex>X</tex>, and suppose that <tex>y</tex> is a point of <tex>Y</tex> such that <tex>f(y)=g(y)=x</tex>, and such that the residue homomorphisms <tex>k(x) \to  k(y)</tex> defined by <tex>f</tex> and <tex>g</tex> are identical (&quot;<tex>f</tex> and <tex>g</tex> agree geometrically at <tex>y</tex>&quot;).
    Then <tex>f</tex> and <tex>g</tex> are identical.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5189</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      This follows from <ref addr="sga1-i.5.3" href="sga1-i.5.3.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.5.3"/> by reducing to the case where <tex>Y=S</tex>, and by replacing <tex>X</tex> with <tex>X \times _S Y</tex>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><p>
  Here is a particularly important variant of <ref addr="sga1-i.5.3" href="sga1-i.5.3.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.5.3"/>:
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5190</anchor> <taxon>Theorem</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.5.5</addr><route>sga1-i.5.5.xml</route>     <number>I.5.5</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>S</tex> be a prescheme, and let <tex>X</tex> and <tex>Y</tex> be <tex>S</tex>-preschemes.
    Let <tex>S_0</tex> be a closed sub-prescheme of <tex>S</tex> that has the same underlying space as <tex>S</tex>, and let <tex>X_0=X \times _S S_0</tex> and <tex>Y_0=Y \times _S S_0</tex> be the &quot;restrictions&quot; of <tex>X</tex> and <tex>Y</tex> to <tex>S_0</tex>.
    Suppose that <tex>X</tex> is étale over <tex>S</tex>.
    Then the natural map
    <tex display="block">\operatorname {Hom} _S(Y,X)  \to   \operatorname {Hom} _{S_0}(X_0,Y_0)</tex>
    is <em>bijective</em>.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5191</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      We can again reduce to the case where <tex>Y=S</tex>, and then this follows from the &quot;topological&quot; description of sections of <tex>X/Y</tex> given in <ref addr="sga1-i.5.3" href="sga1-i.5.3.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.5.3"/>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5192</anchor> <taxon>Scholium</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>S</tex> be a prescheme, and let <tex>X</tex> and <tex>Y</tex> be <tex>S</tex>-preschemes.
    Let <tex>S_0</tex> be a closed sub-prescheme of <tex>S</tex> that has the same underlying space as <tex>S</tex>, and let <tex>X_0=X \times _S S_0</tex> and <tex>Y_0=Y \times _S S_0</tex> be the &quot;restrictions&quot; of <tex>X</tex> and <tex>Y</tex> to <tex>S_0</tex>.
    Suppose that <tex>X</tex> is étale over <tex>S</tex>.
    Then the natural map
    <tex display="block">\operatorname {Hom} _S(Y,X)  \to   \operatorname {Hom} _{S_0}(X_0,Y_0)</tex>
    is <em>bijective</em>.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  The following form of <ref addr="sga1-i.5.5" href="sga1-i.5.5.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.5.5"/> (which looks more general) is often useful:
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5193</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.5.6</addr><route>sga1-i.5.6.xml</route>    <title>Extension of liftings</title> <number>I.5.6</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Consider a commutative diagram of morphisms
    <tex display="block">        \begin {CD}         X @&lt;&lt;&lt; Y_0        \\ @VVV @VVV        \\ S @&lt;&lt;&lt; Y        \end {CD}     </tex>
    where <tex>X \to  S</tex> is étale, and <tex>Y_0 \to  Y</tex> is a bijective closed immersion.
    Then we can find a unique morphism <tex>Y \to  X</tex> such that the two corresponding triangles commute.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5194</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      By replacing <tex>S</tex> with <tex>Y</tex>, and <tex>X</tex> with <tex>X \times _S Y</tex>, we can reduce to the case where <tex>Y=S</tex>, and this is then a particular case of <ref addr="sga1-i.5.5" href="sga1-i.5.5.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.5.5"/> for <tex>Y=S</tex>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><p>
  We also note the following immediate consequence of <ref addr="sga1-i.5.1" href="sga1-i.5.1.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.5.1"/> (which we did not give as a corollary, in order to not interrupt the line of ideas developed following <ref addr="sga1-i.5.1" href="sga1-i.5.1.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.5.1"/>):
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5195</anchor> <taxon>Proposition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.5.7</addr><route>sga1-i.5.7.xml</route>     <number>I.5.7</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>X</tex> and <tex>X'</tex> be preschemes that are of finite type and flat over <tex>Y</tex>, and let <tex>g \colon  X \to  X'</tex> be a <tex>Y</tex>-morphism.
    For <tex>g</tex> to be an open immersion (resp. an isomorphism), it is necessary and sufficient that the induced morphism on the fibres
    <tex display="block">       g \otimes _Y k(y) \colon        X \otimes _Y k(y)  \to  X' \otimes _Y k(y)     </tex>
    be an open immersion (resp. an isomorphism) for all <tex>y \in  Y</tex>.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5196</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      It suffices to prove sufficiency;
      since it is true for the property of being a surjection, we can reduce to the case of an open immersion.
      By <ref addr="sga1-i.5.1" href="sga1-i.5.1.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.5.1"/>, we have to show that <tex>g</tex> is <em>radicial</em> (which is trivial) and <em>étale</em> (which follows from <ref addr="sga1-i.5.9" href="sga1-i.5.9.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.5.9"/> below).
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5197</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.5.8</addr><route>sga1-i.5.8.xml</route>     <number>I.5.8</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>X</tex> and <tex>X'</tex> be <tex>Y</tex>-preschemes, <tex>g \colon  X \to  X'</tex> a <tex>Y</tex>-morphism, <tex>x</tex> a point of <tex>X</tex>, and <tex>y</tex> the projection of <tex>x</tex> in <tex>Y</tex>.
    For <tex>g</tex> to be quasi-finite (resp. unramified) at <tex>x</tex>, it is necessary and sufficient that <tex>g \otimes _Y k(y)</tex> be so.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5198</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      The two algebras over <tex>k(g(x))</tex> that we have to study in order to see whether or not we do indeed have a morphism which is quasi-finite (resp. unramified) at <tex>x</tex> are the same for <tex>g</tex> and <tex>g \otimes _Y k(y)</tex>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5199</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.5.9</addr><route>sga1-i.5.9.xml</route>     <number>I.5.9</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    With the notation of <ref addr="sga1-i.5.8" href="sga1-i.5.8.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.5.8"/>, suppose that <tex>X</tex> and <tex>X'</tex> are flat and of finite type over <tex>Y</tex>.
    For <tex>g</tex> to be flat (resp. étale) at <tex>x</tex>, it is necessary and sufficient that <tex>g \otimes _Y k(y)</tex> be so.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5200</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      For &quot;flat&quot;, the statement only serves as a reminder, since this is one of the fundamental criteria of flatness.
      (cf. [sga1-iv.5.9 <strong>(?)</strong>].)
      For &quot;étale&quot;, this follows by taking <ref addr="sga1-i.5.8" href="sga1-i.5.8.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.5.8"/> into account.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="true" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5201</anchor> <taxon>Section</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.6</addr><route>sga1-i.6.xml</route>    <title><link href="sga1-i.xml" type="local" addr="sga1-i" title="SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group › Étale morphisms"><link href="sga1.xml" type="local" addr="sga1" title="SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group">SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group</link> › Étale morphisms</link> › Application to étale extensions of complete local rings</title> <number>I.6</number> <parent>sga1-i</parent> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
  This section is a particular case of the results on formal preschemes, which should appear in the multiplodoque.
  Nevertheless, here we get away without much difficulty, i.e. without the explicit local determination of the étale morphisms in [sga1-i.7 <strong>(?)</strong>] (using the Main Theorem).
  This is perhaps sufficient reason to keep this current section (even in the multiplodoque) where it is.
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5202</anchor> <taxon>Theorem</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.6.1</addr><route>sga1-i.6.1.xml</route>     <number>I.6.1</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>A</tex> be a complete local ring (Noetherian, of course), with residue field <tex>k</tex>.
    For any <tex>A</tex>-algebra <tex>B</tex>, let <tex>R(B)=B \otimes _Ak</tex> be thought of as a <tex>k</tex>-algebra;
    this depends functorially on <tex>B</tex>.
    Then <tex>R</tex> defines an <em>equivalence</em> between the category of <tex>A</tex>-algebras that are <em>finite and étale over <tex>A</tex></em> and the category of algebras that are <em>finite rank and separable over <tex>k</tex></em>.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  Firstly, the functor in question is fully faithful, as follows from the more general fact:
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5203</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.6.2</addr><route>sga1-i.6.2.xml</route>     <number>I.6.2</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>B</tex> and <tex>B'</tex> be <tex>A</tex>-algebras that are finite over <tex>A</tex>.
    If <tex>B</tex> is étale over <tex>A</tex>, then the canonical map
    <tex display="block">        \operatorname {Hom} _{ A \mathsf {-alg} }(B,B')        \to   \operatorname {Hom} _{ k \mathsf {-alg} }(R(B),R(B'))     </tex>
    is bijective.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5204</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      We can reduce to the case where <tex>A</tex> is Artinian (by replacing <tex>A</tex> by <tex>A/ \frak {m}^n</tex>), and then this is a particular case of <ref addr="sga1-i.5.5" href="sga1-i.5.5.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.5.5"/>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><p>
  It remains to prove that, for every finite and separable <tex>k</tex> algebra (or we can simply say &quot;étale&quot;, for brevity) <tex>L</tex>, there exists some <tex>B</tex> étale over <tex>A</tex> such that <tex>R(B)</tex> is isomorphic to <tex>L</tex>.
  We can suppose that <tex>L</tex> is a separable extension of <tex>k</tex>, and, as such, it admits a generator <tex>x</tex>, i.e. it is isomorphic to an algebra <tex>k[t]/Fk[t]</tex>, where <tex>F \in  k[t]</tex> is a monic polynomial.
  We can lift <tex>F</tex> to a monic polynomial <tex>F_1</tex> in <tex>A[t]</tex>, and we take <tex>B=A[t]/F_1A[t]</tex>.
</p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="true" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5205</anchor> <taxon>Section</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.7</addr><route>sga1-i.7.xml</route>    <title><link href="sga1-i.xml" type="local" addr="sga1-i" title="SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group › Étale morphisms"><link href="sga1.xml" type="local" addr="sga1" title="SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group">SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group</link> › Étale morphisms</link> › Local construction of unramified and étale morphisms</title> <number>I.7</number> <parent>sga1-i</parent> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5206</anchor> <taxon>Proposition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.7.1</addr><route>sga1-i.7.1.xml</route>     <number>I.7.1</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>A</tex> be a Noetherian ring, <tex>B</tex> an algebra which is finite over <tex>A</tex>, and <tex>u</tex> a generator of <tex>B</tex> over <tex>A</tex>.
    Let <tex>F \in  A[t]</tex> be such that <tex>F(u)=0</tex> (we do not assume <tex>F</tex> to be monic), and <tex>u'=F'(u)</tex> (where <tex>F'</tex> is the differentiated polynomial).
    Let <tex>\mathfrak {q}</tex> be a prime ideal of <tex>B</tex> not containing <tex>u'</tex>, and <tex>\mathfrak {p}</tex> its intersection with <tex>A</tex>.
    Then <tex>B_ \mathfrak {q}</tex> is unramified over <tex>A_ \mathfrak {p}</tex>.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  In other words, taking <tex>Y= \operatorname {Spec} (A)</tex>, <tex>X= \operatorname {Spec} (B)</tex>, and <tex>X_{u'}= \operatorname {Spec} (B_{u'})</tex>, we claim that <tex>X_{u'}</tex> is unramified over <tex>Y</tex>.
  This statement follows from the following, more precise:
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5207</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.7.2</addr><route>sga1-i.7.2.xml</route>     <number>I.7.2</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    The different ideal of <tex>B/A</tex> contains <tex>u'B</tex>, and is equal to <tex>u'B</tex> if the natural homomorphism <tex>A[t]/FA[t] \to  B</tex> (sending <tex>t</tex> to <tex>u</tex>) is an isomorphism.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5208</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      Let <tex>J</tex> be the kernel of the homomorphism <tex>C=A[t] \to  B</tex>, so that <tex>J</tex> contains <tex>FA[t]</tex>, and is equal to it in the second case described in <ref addr="sga1-i.7.2" href="sga1-i.7.2.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.7.2"/>.
      Since the homomorphism <tex>C \to  B</tex> is surjective, <tex>\Omega _{B/A}^1</tex> can be identified with the quotient of <tex>\Omega _{C/A}^1</tex> by the sub-module generated by <tex>J \Omega _{C/A}^1</tex> and <tex>\mathrm {d} (J)</tex> (we should have explicitly described the definition of the homomorphism <tex>d</tex> and the calculation of <tex>\Omega ^1</tex> for an algebra of polynomials in <ref addr="sga1-i" href="sga1-i.xml" taxon="Exposé" number="I"/>).
      Identifying <tex>\Omega _{C/A}^1</tex> with <tex>C</tex>, via the basis <tex>\mathrm {d}  t</tex>, we obtain <tex>B/B \cdot  J'</tex>, and so the different ideal is generated by the set <tex>J'</tex> of images in <tex>B</tex> of derivatives of <tex>G \in  J</tex> (and it suffices to take <tex>G</tex> that generate <tex>J</tex>).
      Since <tex>F \in  J</tex> (resp. <tex>F</tex> is a generator of <tex>J</tex>), we are done.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5209</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.7.3</addr><route>sga1-i.7.3.xml</route>     <number>I.7.3</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Under the conditions of <ref addr="sga1-i.7.1" href="sga1-i.7.1.xml" taxon="Proposition" number="I.7.1"/>, and supposing that <tex>F</tex> is monic and that <tex>A[t]/FA[t] \to  B</tex> is an isomorphism, in order for <tex>B_ \mathfrak {q}</tex> to be étale over <tex>A_ \mathfrak {p}</tex> it is necessary and sufficient that <tex>\mathfrak {q}</tex> not contain <tex>u'</tex>.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5210</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      Since <tex>B</tex> is flat over <tex>A</tex>, being étale is equivalent to being unramified, and we can apply <ref addr="sga1-i.7.2" href="sga1-i.7.2.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.7.2"/>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5211</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.7.4</addr><route>sga1-i.7.4.xml</route>     <number>I.7.4</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Under the conditions of <ref addr="sga1-i.7.3" href="sga1-i.7.3.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.7.3"/>, in order for <tex>B</tex> to be étale over <tex>A</tex>, it is necessary and sufficient that <tex>u'</tex> be invertible, or for the ideal <tex>F'</tex> generated by <tex>F</tex> in <tex>A[t]</tex> to be the unit ideal.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5212</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      The second claim follows from the first along with Nakayama (in <tex>B</tex>).
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><p>
  A monic polynomial <tex>F \in  A[t]</tex> that has the property stated in <ref addr="sga1-i.7.4" href="sga1-i.7.4.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.7.4"/> is said to be a <em>separable polynomial</em> (if <tex>F</tex> is not monic, we must at least require that the coefficient of its leading term be invertible; in the case where <tex>A</tex> is a field, we recover the usual definition).
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5213</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.7.5</addr><route>sga1-i.7.5.xml</route>     <number>I.7.5</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>B</tex> be an algebra which is <em>finite</em> over the <em>local</em> ring <tex>A</tex>.
    Suppose that <tex>K(A)</tex> is infinite, or that <tex>B</tex> is local.
    Let <tex>n</tex> be the rank of <tex>L=B \otimes _A K(A)</tex> over <tex>K(A)=k</tex>.
    For <tex>B</tex> to be unramified (resp. étale) over <tex>A</tex>, it is necessary and sufficient that <tex>B</tex> be isomorphic to a quotient of (resp. isomorphic to) <tex>A[t]/FA[t]</tex>, where <tex>F</tex> is a separable monic polynomial, which we can assume to be (resp. which is necessarily of) degree <tex>n</tex>.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5214</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      We only have to prove necessity.
      Suppose that <tex>B</tex> is unramified over <tex>A</tex>, and thus that <tex>L</tex> is separable over <tex>k</tex>.
      It then follows from the hypotheses that <tex>L/k</tex> admits a generator <tex>\xi</tex>, and so the <tex>\xi ^i</tex> (for <tex>0 \leq  i&lt;n</tex>) form a basis for <tex>L</tex> over <tex>k</tex>.
      Let <tex>u \in  B</tex> be a lift of <tex>\xi</tex>;
      by Nakayama, the <tex>u^i</tex> (for <tex>0 \leq  i&lt;n</tex>) generate (resp. form a basis of) the <tex>A</tex>-module <tex>B</tex>, and, in particular, we obtain a monic polynomial <tex>F \in  A[t]</tex> such that <tex>F(u)=0</tex>;
      then <tex>B</tex> is isomorphic to a quotient of (resp. isomorphic to) <tex>A[t]/FA[t]</tex>.
      Finally, by applying <ref addr="sga1-i.7.4" href="sga1-i.7.4.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.7.4"/> to <tex>L/k</tex>, we see that <tex>F</tex> and <tex>F'</tex> generate <tex>A[t]</tex> modulo <tex>\mathfrak {m}A[t]</tex>, and so (by Nakayama in <tex>A[t]/FA[t]</tex>) <tex>F</tex> and <tex>F'</tex> generate <tex>A[t]</tex>, and we are done.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5215</anchor> <taxon>Theorem</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.7.6</addr><route>sga1-i.7.6.xml</route>     <number>I.7.6</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>A</tex> be a local ring, and <tex>A \to \mathcal { O }</tex> a local homomorphism such that <tex>\mathcal { O }</tex> is isomorphic to the localisation of an algebra of finite type over <tex>A</tex>.
    Suppose that <tex>\mathcal { O }</tex> is <em>unramified</em> over <tex>A</tex>.
    Then we can find an <tex>A</tex>-algebra <tex>B</tex> that is integral over <tex>A</tex>, a maximal ideal <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex> of <tex>B</tex>, a generator <tex>u</tex> of <tex>B</tex> over <tex>A</tex>, and a monic polynomial <tex>F \in  A[t]</tex> such that <tex>\mathfrak {n} \not \ni  F'(u)</tex> and such that <tex>\mathcal { O }</tex> is isomorphic (as an <tex>A</tex>-algebra) to <tex>B_ \mathfrak {n}</tex>.
    If <tex>\mathcal { O }</tex> is étale over <tex>A</tex>, then we can take <tex>B=A[t]/FA[t]</tex>.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  (Of course, these conditions are more than sufficient ...)
</p><p>
  Before proving <ref addr="sga1-i.7.6" href="sga1-i.7.6.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.7.6"/>, we first state some nice corollaries:
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5216</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.7.7</addr><route>sga1-i.7.7.xml</route>     <number>I.7.7</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    For <tex>\mathcal { O }</tex> to be unramified over <tex>A</tex>, it is necessary and sufficient that <tex>\mathcal { O }</tex> be isomorphic to the quotient of an algebra which is unramified and <em>étale</em> over <tex>A</tex>.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5217</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      We can take <tex>\mathcal { O } '=B'_{ \mathfrak {n}'}</tex>, where <tex>B'=A[t]/FA[t]</tex> and where <tex>\mathfrak {n}'</tex> is the inverse image of <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex> in <tex>B'</tex>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5218</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.7.8</addr><route>sga1-i.7.8.xml</route>     <number>I.7.8</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>f \colon  X \to  Y</tex> be a morphism of finite type, and <tex>x \in  X</tex>.
    For <tex>f</tex> to be unramified at <tex>x</tex>, it is necessary and sufficient that there exist an open neighbourhood <tex>U</tex> of <tex>x</tex> such that <tex>f|U</tex> factors as <tex>U \to  X' \to  Y</tex>, where the first arrow is a closed immersion, and the second is an étale morphism.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5219</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      This is a simple translation of <ref addr="sga1-i.7.7" href="sga1-i.7.7.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.7.7"/>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><p>
  We will now show how the jargon of <ref addr="sga1-i.7.6" href="sga1-i.7.6.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.7.6"/> follows from the main theorem:
  there exists, by <ref addr="sga1-i.7.7" href="sga1-i.7.7.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.7.7"/>, an epimorphism <tex>\mathcal { O } ' \to \mathcal { O }</tex>, where <tex>\mathcal { O }</tex> has all the desired properties;
  but since <tex>\mathcal { O } '</tex> and <tex>\mathcal { O }</tex> are étale over <tex>A</tex>, the morphism <tex>\mathcal { O } ' \to \mathcal { O }</tex> is étale by <ref addr="sga1-i.4.8" href="sga1-i.4.8.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.4.8"/>, and thus an isomorphism.
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5220</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.7.6-proof</addr><route>sga1-i.7.6-proof.xml</route>     <number>I.7.6</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    This mimics a proof from the <em>Séminaire Chevalley</em>.
    By the &quot;Main Theorem&quot;, we have that <tex>\mathcal { O } =B_ \mathfrak {n}</tex>, where <tex>B</tex> is an algebra that is finite over <tex>A</tex>, and <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex> is a maximal ideal.
    Then <tex>B/ \mathfrak {n}=B( \mathcal { O } )</tex> is a separable, and thus monogenous, extension of <tex>k</tex>;
    if <tex>\mathfrak {n}_i</tex> (for <tex>1 \leq  i \leq  r</tex>) are maximal ideas of <tex>B</tex> that are distinct from <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex>, then there thus exists an element <tex>u</tex> of <tex>B</tex> that belongs to all the <tex>\mathfrak {n}_i</tex>, and thus whose image in <tex>B/ \mathfrak {n}</tex> is a generator.
    But <tex>B/ \mathfrak {n}=B_ \mathfrak {n}/ \mathfrak {n}B_ \mathfrak {n}=B_ \mathfrak {n}/ \mathfrak {m}B_ \mathfrak {n}</tex> (where <tex>\mathfrak {m}</tex> is the maximal ideal of <tex>A</tex>).

    Suppose, for the moment, that we have both <ref addr="sga1-i.7.9" href="sga1-i.7.9.xml" taxon="Lemma" number="I.7.9"/> and <ref addr="sga1-i.7.10" href="sga1-i.7.10.xml" taxon="Lemma" number="I.7.10"/>.
    Let <tex>n</tex> be the rank of the <tex>k</tex>-algebra <tex>L=B \otimes _A k</tex>.
    By Nakayama, there exists a monic polynomial of degree <tex>n</tex> in <tex>A[t]</tex> such that <tex>F(u)=0</tex>.
    Let <tex>f</tex> be the polynomial induced from <tex>F</tex> by reduction <tex>\mod \mathfrak {m}</tex>.
    Then <tex>L</tex> is <tex>k</tex>-isomorphic to <tex>k[t]/fk[t]</tex>, and so, by <ref addr="sga1-i.7.3" href="sga1-i.7.3.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.7.3"/>, <tex>f'( \xi )</tex> is not contained in the maximal ideal of <tex>L</tex> that corresponds to <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex> (where <tex>\xi</tex> denotes the image of <tex>t</tex> in <tex>L</tex>, i.e. the image of <tex>u</tex> in <tex>L</tex>).
    Since <tex>f'( \xi )</tex> is the image of <tex>F'(u)</tex>, we are done.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5221</anchor> <taxon>Lemma</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.7.9</addr><route>sga1-i.7.9.xml</route>     <number>I.7.9</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>A</tex> be a local ring, <tex>B</tex> an algebra that is finite over <tex>A</tex>, <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex> a maximal ideal of <tex>B</tex>, and <tex>u</tex> an element of <tex>B</tex> whose image in <tex>B_ \mathfrak {n}/ \mathfrak {m}B_ \mathfrak {n}</tex> is a generator as an algebra over <tex>k=A/ \mathfrak {m}</tex>, and such that <tex>u</tex> is contained in every maximal ideal of <tex>B</tex> that is distinct from <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex>.
    Let <tex>B'=B[u]</tex> and <tex>\mathfrak {n}'= \mathfrak {n}B'</tex>.
    Then the canonical homomorphism <tex>B'_{ \mathfrak {n}'} \to  B_ \mathfrak {n}</tex> is an isomorphism.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5222</anchor> <taxon>Lemma</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.7.10</addr><route>sga1-i.7.10.xml</route>     <number>I.7.10</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>B</tex> be a algebra that is finite over <tex>A</tex> and generated by a single element <tex>u</tex>, and let <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex> be a maximal ideal of <tex>B</tex> such that <tex>B_ \mathfrak {n}</tex> is unramified over <tex>A</tex>.
    Then there exists a monic polynomial <tex>F \in  A[t]</tex> such that <tex>F(u)=0</tex> and <tex>F'(u) \not \in \mathfrak {n}</tex>.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  N.B. <ref addr="sga1-i.7.10" href="sga1-i.7.10.xml" taxon="Lemma" number="I.7.10"/> should have appeared as a corollary to <ref addr="sga1-i.7.1" href="sga1-i.7.1.xml" taxon="Proposition" number="I.7.1"/>, and before <ref addr="sga1-i.7.5" href="sga1-i.7.5.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.7.5"/> (which it implies).
</p><p>
  So <ref addr="sga1-i.7.6" href="sga1-i.7.6.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.7.6"/> now follows from the combination of <ref addr="sga1-i.7.9" href="sga1-i.7.9.xml" taxon="Lemma" number="I.7.9"/> and <ref addr="sga1-i.7.10" href="sga1-i.7.10.xml" taxon="Lemma" number="I.7.10"/>;
  it remains only to prove <ref addr="sga1-i.7.9" href="sga1-i.7.9.xml" taxon="Lemma" number="I.7.9"/>.
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5223</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.7.9-proof</addr><route>sga1-i.7.9-proof.xml</route>     <number>I.7.9</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>S'=B' \setminus \mathfrak {n}'</tex>, so that <tex>B'S'^{-1}=B'_ \mathfrak {n'}</tex>.
    Similarly, let <tex>S=B \setminus \mathfrak {n}</tex>, so that <tex>BS^{-1}=B_ \mathfrak {n}</tex>.
    We then have a natural homomorphism <tex>BS'^{-1} \to  BS^{-1}=B_ \mathfrak {n}</tex>;
    we will show that this is an isomorphism, i.e. that the elements of <tex>S</tex> are invertible in <tex>BS'^{-1}</tex>, i.e. that every maximal ideal <tex>\mathfrak {p}</tex> of <tex>BS'^{-1}</tex> does not meet <tex>S</tex>, i.e. that every maximal ideal of <tex>BS'^{-1}</tex> induces <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex> on <tex>B</tex>.
    <tex display="block">        \begin {CD}         B @&gt;&gt;&gt; BS'^{-1} @&gt;&gt;&gt; BS^{-1} = B_ \mathfrak {n}        \\ @AAA @AAA        \\ B' @&gt;&gt;&gt; B'S'^{-1} = B'_{ \mathfrak {n}'}        \end {CD}     </tex>
    Since <tex>BS'^{-1}</tex> is finite over <tex>B'S'^{-1}=B'_{ \mathfrak {n}'}</tex>, <tex>\mathfrak {p}</tex> induces the unique maximal ideal <tex>\mathfrak {n}'B_{ \mathfrak {n}'}</tex> of <tex>B'_{ \mathfrak {n}'}</tex>, and thus induces the maximal ideal <tex>\mathfrak {n}'</tex> of <tex>B'</tex>;
    since <tex>B</tex> is finite over <tex>B'</tex>, the ideal <tex>\mathfrak {q}</tex> of <tex>B</tex> induced by <tex>\mathfrak {p}</tex>, which lives over <tex>\mathfrak {n}'</tex>, is necessarily maximal, and does not contain <tex>u</tex>, and is thus identical to <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex>.
    (We have just used the fact that <tex>u</tex> belongs to every maximal ideal of <tex>B</tex> that is distinct from <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex>).
    We now prove that <tex>BS'^{-1}</tex> is equal to <tex>B'S'^{-1}</tex>:
    since the former is finite over the latter, we can reduce, by Nakayama, to proving equality modulo <tex>\mathfrak {n}'BS'^{-1}</tex>, and, a fortiori, it suffices to prove equality modulo <tex>\mathfrak {m}BS'^{-1}</tex>;
    but <tex>BS'^{-1}/ \mathfrak {m}BS'^{-1}=B_ \mathfrak {n}/ \mathfrak {m}B_ \mathfrak {n}</tex> is generated, over <tex>k</tex>, by <tex>u</tex> (here we use the other property of <tex>u</tex>), and so the image of <tex>B'</tex> (and, a fortiori, of <tex>B'S'^{-1}</tex>) inside is everything (as a sub-ring that contains <tex>k</tex> and the image of <tex>u</tex>.)
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5224</anchor> <taxon>Remark</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    We must be able to state <ref addr="sga1-i.7.6" href="sga1-i.7.6.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.7.6"/> for a ring <tex>\mathcal { O }</tex> that is only semi-local, so that we also cover <ref addr="sga1-i.7.5" href="sga1-i.7.5.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.7.5"/>:
    we make the hypothesis that <tex>\mathcal { O } / \mathfrak {m} \mathcal { O }</tex> is a <em>monogenous</em> <tex>k</tex>-algebra;
    we can thus find some <tex>u \in  B</tex> whose image in <tex>B/ \mathfrak {m}B</tex> is a generator, and belongs to every maximal ideal of <tex>B</tex> that doesn't come from <tex>\mathcal { O }</tex>.
    Both <ref addr="sga1-i.7.9" href="sga1-i.7.9.xml" taxon="Lemma" number="I.7.9"/> and <ref addr="sga1-i.7.10" href="sga1-i.7.10.xml" taxon="Lemma" number="I.7.10"/> should be able to be adapted without difficulty.
    More generally, ...
  </p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="true" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5225</anchor> <taxon>Section</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.8</addr><route>sga1-i.8.xml</route>    <title><link href="sga1-i.xml" type="local" addr="sga1-i" title="SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group › Étale morphisms"><link href="sga1.xml" type="local" addr="sga1" title="SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group">SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group</link> › Étale morphisms</link> › Infinitesimal lifting of étale schemes. Applications to formal schemes</title> <number>I.8</number> <parent>sga1-i</parent> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5226</anchor> <taxon>Proposition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.8.1</addr><route>sga1-i.8.1.xml</route>     <number>I.8.1</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>Y</tex> be a prescheme, <tex>Y_0</tex> a sub-prescheme, <tex>X_0</tex> an étale <tex>Y_0</tex>-scheme, and <tex>x</tex> a point of <tex>X_0</tex>.
    Then there exists an étale <tex>Y</tex>-scheme <tex>X</tex>, a neighbourhood <tex>U_0</tex> of <tex>x</tex> in <tex>X_0</tex>, and a <tex>Y_0</tex>-isomorphism <tex>U_0 \xrightarrow { \sim }X \times _Y Y_0</tex>.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5227</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      Let <tex>y</tex> be the projection of <tex>x</tex> in <tex>Y_0</tex>;
      applying <ref addr="sga1-i.7.6" href="sga1-i.7.6.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.7.6"/> to the étale local homomorphism <tex>A_0 \to  B_0</tex> of local rings of <tex>y</tex> and <tex>x</tex> in <tex>Y_0</tex> and <tex>X_0</tex>, we obtain an isomorphism
      <tex display="block">          \begin {aligned}           B_0 &amp;= (C_0)_{ \mathfrak {n}_0}          \\ C_0 &amp;= A_0[t]/F_0A_0[t]          \end {aligned}       </tex>
      where <tex>F_0</tex> is a monic polynomial, and <tex>\mathfrak {n}_0</tex> is a maximal ideal of <tex>C_0</tex> not containing the class of <tex>F'_0(t)</tex> in <tex>C_0</tex>.
      Let <tex>A</tex> be the local ring of <tex>y</tex> in <tex>Y</tex>, let <tex>F</tex> be a monic polynomial in <tex>A[t]</tex> that gives <tex>F_0</tex> under the surjective homomorphism <tex>A \to  A_0</tex> (we lift the coefficients of <tex>F_0</tex>), and let <tex>C=A[t]/FA[t]</tex>, with <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex> the maximal ideal of <tex>C</tex> given by the inverse image of <tex>\mathfrak {n}_0</tex> under the natural epimorphism <tex>C \to  C \otimes _A A_0=C_0</tex>.
      Let
      <tex display="block">         B = C_ \mathfrak {n}.       </tex>
      It is immediate, by construction and by <ref addr="sga1-i.7.1" href="sga1-i.7.1.xml" taxon="Proposition" number="I.7.1"/>, that <tex>B</tex> is étale over <tex>A</tex>, and that we have an isomorphism <tex>B \otimes _A A_0=A_0</tex>.
    </p>

    <p>
      We know that there exists a <tex>Y</tex>-scheme <tex>X</tex> of finite type, along with a point <tex>z</tex> of <tex>X</tex> over <tex>y</tex> such that <tex>\mathcal { O } _z</tex> is <tex>A</tex>-isomorphic to <tex>C</tex>;
      since the latter is étale over <tex>A= \mathcal { O } _y</tex>, we can (by taking <tex>X</tex> to be small enough) assume that <tex>X</tex> is étale over <tex>Y</tex>.
      Let <tex>X'_0=X \times _Y Y_0</tex>.
      Then the local ring of <tex>z</tex> in <tex>X'_0</tex> can be identified with <tex>\mathcal { O } _z \otimes _A A_0=B \otimes _A A_0</tex>, and is thus isomorphic to <tex>B_0</tex>.
      This isomorphism is defined by an isomorphism from a neighbourhood <tex>U_0</tex> of <tex>x</tex> in <tex>X</tex> to a neighbourhood of <tex>z</tex> in <tex>X'_0</tex>, and we can assume this to be identical to <tex>X'_0</tex> by taking <tex>X</tex> to be small enough.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5228</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.8.2</addr><route>sga1-i.8.2.xml</route>     <number>I.8.2</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    The analogous claim holds for étale <em>covers</em>, if we suppose the residue field <tex>k(y)</tex> to be infinite.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5229</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      The proof is the same, just replacing <ref addr="sga1-i.7.5" href="sga1-i.7.5.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.7.5"/> by <ref addr="sga1-i.7.6" href="sga1-i.7.6.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.7.6"/>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5230</anchor> <taxon>Theorem</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.8.3</addr><route>sga1-i.8.3.xml</route>     <number>I.8.3</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    The functor described in <ref addr="sga1-i.5.5" href="sga1-i.5.5.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.5.5"/> is an <em>equivalence</em> of <em>categories</em>.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5231</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    By <ref addr="sga1-i.5.5" href="sga1-i.5.5.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.5.5"/>, it remains only to show that every étale <tex>S_0</tex>-scheme <tex>X_0</tex> is isomorphic to an <tex>S_0</tex>-scheme <tex>X \times _S S_0</tex>, where <tex>X</tex> is an étale <tex>S</tex>-scheme.
    The underlying topological space of <tex>X</tex> must necessarily be identical to the one of <tex>X_0</tex>, and with <tex>X_0</tex> being identified with a closed sub-prescheme of <tex>X</tex>.
    The problem is thus equivalent to the following:
    find, on the underlying topological space <tex>|X_0|</tex> of <tex>X_0</tex>, a sheaf of algebras <tex>\mathcal { O } _X</tex> over <tex>f_0^*( \mathcal { O } _S)</tex> (where <tex>f_0</tex> is the projection <tex>X_0 \to  S_0</tex>, thought of here as a continuous map of the underlying spaces) that makes <tex>|X_0|</tex> an étale <tex>S</tex>-prescheme <tex>X</tex>, as well as an algebra homomorphism <tex>\mathcal { O } _X \to \mathcal { O } _{X_0}</tex> that is compatible with the homomorphism <tex>f_0^*( \mathcal { O } _S) \to  f_0^*( \mathcal { O } _{S_0})</tex> on the sheaves of scalars, and that induces an isomorphism <tex>\mathcal { O } _X \otimes _{f_0^*( \mathcal { O } _S)*}f_0^*( \mathcal { O } _{S_0}) \xrightarrow { \sim } \mathcal { O } _{X_0}</tex>.
    (Then <tex>X</tex> will be an étale <tex>S</tex>-prescheme that is reduced along <tex>X_0</tex>, and thus separated over <tex>S</tex>, since <tex>X_0</tex> is separated over <tex>S_0</tex>, and <tex>X</tex> satisfies all the desired properties).

    If <tex>(U_i)</tex> is an open cover of <tex>X_0</tex>, and if we find a solution to the problem on each of the <tex>U_i</tex>, then it follows from the uniqueness theorem <ref addr="sga1-i.5.5" href="sga1-i.5.5.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.5.5"/> that these solutions glue (i.e. the sheaves of algebras that they define, endowed with their augmentation homomorphisms, glue), and we claim that the ringed space thus constructed over <tex>S</tex> is an étale <tex>S</tex>-prescheme <tex>X</tex> endowed with an isomorphism <tex>X \times _S S_0 \xleftarrow { \sim }X_0</tex>.
    It thus suffices to find a solution locally, which we know is possible by <ref addr="sga1-i.8.1" href="sga1-i.8.1.xml" taxon="Proposition" number="I.8.1"/>.
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5232</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.8.4</addr><route>sga1-i.8.4.xml</route>     <number>I.8.4</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>S</tex> be a locally Noetherian formal prescheme, endowed with an ideal of definition <tex>\mathcal { J }</tex>, and let <tex>S_0=(|S|, \mathcal { O } _S/ \mathcal { J } )</tex> be the corresponding ordinary prescheme.
    Then the functor <tex>\mathfrak {X} \mapsto \mathfrak {X} \times _S S_0</tex> from the category of étale covers of <tex>S</tex> to the category of étale covers of <tex>S_0</tex> is an equivalence of categories.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5233</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      Of course, we define an étale cover of a <em>formal</em> prescheme <tex>S</tex> to be a cover of <tex>S</tex> (i.e a formal prescheme over <tex>S</tex> defined by a coherent sheaf of algebras <tex>\mathcal { B }</tex>) such that <tex>\mathcal { B }</tex> is <em>locally free</em>, and such that the residue fibres <tex>\mathcal { B } _s \otimes _{ \mathcal { O } _s}k(s)</tex> of <tex>\mathcal { B }</tex> are <em>separable</em> algebras over <tex>k(s)</tex>.
      If we denote by <tex>S_n</tex> the ordinary prescheme <tex>(|S|, \mathcal { O } _S/ \mathcal { J } ^{n+1})</tex>, then the data of a coherent sheaf of algebras <tex>\mathcal { B }</tex> on <tex>S</tex> is equivalent to the data of a sequence of coherent sheaves of algebras <tex>\mathcal { B } _n</tex> on the <tex>S_n</tex>, endowed with a transitive system of homomorphisms <tex>\mathcal { B } _m \to \mathcal { B } _n</tex> (for <tex>m \geq  n</tex>) defining the isomorphisms <tex>\mathcal { B } _m \otimes _{ \mathcal { O } _{S_m}} \mathcal { O } _{S_n} \xrightarrow { \sim } \mathcal { B } _n</tex>.
      It is immediate that <tex>\mathcal { B }</tex> is locally free if and only if the <tex>\mathcal { B } _n</tex> are locally free over the <tex>S_n</tex>, and that the separability condition is satisfied if and only if it is satisfied for <tex>\mathcal { B } _0</tex>, or for all the <tex>\mathcal { B } _n</tex>.
      Thus <tex>\mathcal { B }</tex> is étale over <tex>S</tex> if and only if the <tex>\mathcal { B } _n</tex> are étale over the <tex>S_n</tex>.
      Taking this into account, <ref addr="sga1-i.8.4" href="sga1-i.8.4.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.8.4"/> follows immediately from <ref addr="sga1-i.8.3" href="sga1-i.8.3.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.8.3"/>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5234</anchor> <taxon>Remark</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    It was not necessary to restrict ourselves to the case of <em>covers</em> in <ref addr="sga1-i.8.4" href="sga1-i.8.4.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.8.4"/>, but this is the only case that we will use for the moment.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="true" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5235</anchor> <taxon>Section</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.9</addr><route>sga1-i.9.xml</route>    <title><link href="sga1-i.xml" type="local" addr="sga1-i" title="SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group › Étale morphisms"><link href="sga1.xml" type="local" addr="sga1" title="SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group">SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group</link> › Étale morphisms</link> › Invariance properties</title> <number>I.9</number> <parent>sga1-i</parent> </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
  Let <tex>A \to  B</tex> be a morphism that is local and étale;
  we study here some cases where a certain property of <tex>A</tex> implies the same property for <tex>B</tex>, or vice versa.
  A certain number of such propositions are already consequences of the simple fact that <tex>B</tex> is <em>quasi-finite</em> and <em>flat</em> over <tex>A</tex>, and we content ourselves with &quot;recalling&quot; some of them.
  <em><tex>A</tex> and <tex>B</tex> have the same Krull dimension, and the same depth</em> (Serre's &quot;cohomological codimension&quot;, in the more modern language).
  It also follows, for example, that <em><tex>A</tex> is Cohen–Macaulay if and only if <tex>B</tex> is</em>.
  Also, for any prime ideal <tex>\mathfrak {q}</tex> of <tex>B</tex> (inducing some <tex>\mathfrak {p}</tex> of <tex>A</tex>), <tex>B_ \mathfrak {q}</tex> is again quasi-finite and flat over <tex>A_ \mathfrak {p}</tex>, as long as we suppose that <tex>B</tex> is the localisation of an algebra of finite type over <tex>A</tex> (this follows from the fact that the set of points where a morphism of finite type is quasi-finite (resp. flat) is open);
  furthermore, <em>every</em> prime ideal <tex>\mathfrak {p}</tex> of <tex>A</tex> is induced by a prime ideal <tex>\mathfrak {q}</tex> of <tex>B</tex> (since <tex>B</tex> is <em>faithfully</em> flat over <tex>A</tex>).
  It thus follows, for example, that <em><tex>\mathfrak {q}</tex> and <tex>\mathfrak {p}</tex> have the same rank</em>;
  also, <em><tex>A</tex> has no embedded prime ideals if and only if <tex>B</tex> has none</em>.
</p><p>
  We will thus content ourselves with more specific propositions concerning the case of étale morphisms.
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5236</anchor> <taxon>Proposition</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.9.1</addr><route>sga1-i.9.1.xml</route>     <number>I.9.1</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>A \to  B</tex> be an étale local homomorphism.
    For <tex>A</tex> to be regular, it is necessary and sufficient that <tex>B</tex> be regular.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5237</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      Let <tex>k</tex> be the residue field of <tex>A</tex>, and <tex>L</tex> the residue field of <tex>B</tex>.
      Since <tex>B</tex> is flat over <tex>A</tex>, and since <tex>L=B \otimes _A k</tex> (i.e. <tex>\mathfrak {n}= \mathfrak {m}B</tex>, where <tex>\mathfrak {m}</tex> and <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex> are the maximal ideals of <tex>A</tex> and <tex>B</tex> respectively), the <tex>\mathfrak {m}</tex>-adic filtration on <tex>B</tex> is identical to the <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex>-adic filtration, and
      <tex display="block">          \operatorname {gr} ^ \bullet (B) =  \operatorname {gr} ^ \bullet (A) \otimes _k L.       </tex>
      It follows that <tex>\operatorname {gr} ^ \bullet (B)</tex> is a polynomial algebra over <tex>L</tex> if and only if <tex>\operatorname {gr} ^ \bullet (A)</tex> is a polynomial algebra over <tex>K</tex>.
      (N.B. we have not used the fact that <tex>L/k</tex> is separable.)
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5238</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.9.2</addr><route>sga1-i.9.2.xml</route>     <number>I.9.2</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>f \colon  X \to  Y</tex> be an étale morphism.
    If <tex>Y</tex> is regular, then <tex>X</tex> is regular;
    the converse is true if <tex>f</tex> is surjective.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5239</anchor> <taxon>Proposition</taxon>      <number>I.9.2</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>f \colon  X \to  Y</tex> be an étale morphism.
    If <tex>Y</tex> is reduced, then <tex>X</tex> is reduced;
    the converse is true if <tex>f</tex> is surjective.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  This is equivalent to the following:
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5240</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.9.3</addr><route>sga1-i.9.3.xml</route>     <number>I.9.3</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>f \colon  A \to  B</tex> be an étale local homomorphism, with <tex>B</tex> isomorphic to the localisation of an <tex>A</tex>-algebra of finite type over <tex>A</tex>.
    For <tex>A</tex> to be reduced, it is necessary and sufficient that <tex>B</tex> be reduced.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5241</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    <p>
      The necessity is trivial, since <tex>A \to  B</tex> is injective (since <tex>B</tex> is faithfully flat over <tex>A</tex>).
      For the sufficiency, let <tex>\mathfrak {p}_i</tex> be the minimal prime ideals of <tex>A</tex>.
      By hypothesis, the natural map <tex>A \to \prod _i A/ \mathfrak {p}_i</tex> is injective, and so tensoring with the flat <tex>A</tex>-module <tex>B</tex> gives that <tex>B \to \prod _i B/ \mathfrak {p}_iB</tex> is injective, and we can thus reduce to proving that the <tex>B/ \mathfrak {p}_iB</tex> are reduced.
      Since <tex>B/ \mathfrak {p}_iB</tex> is étale over <tex>A/ \mathfrak {p}_i</tex>, we can reduce to the case where <tex>A</tex> is integral.
      Let <tex>K</tex> be the field of fractions of <tex>A</tex>, so that <tex>A \to  K</tex> is injective, and thus so too is <tex>B \to  B \otimes _A K</tex> (since <tex>B</tex> is <tex>A</tex>-flat), and we can thus reduce to proving that <tex>B \otimes _A K</tex> is reduced.
      But <tex>B</tex> is the localisation of an <tex>A</tex>-algebra of finite type over <tex>A</tex>, and thus is the local ring of a point <tex>x</tex> of a scheme of finite type <tex>X= \operatorname {Spec} (C)</tex> over <tex>Y= \operatorname {Spec} (A)</tex> that is also <em>étale</em> over <tex>Y</tex>, so <tex>B \otimes _A K</tex> is a localisation (with respect to some suitable multiplicatively stable set) of the ring <tex>C \otimes _A K</tex> of <tex>X \otimes _A K</tex>.
      Since <tex>X \otimes _A K</tex> is étale over <tex>K</tex>, its ring is a finite product of fields (that are separable extensions of <tex>K</tex>), and thus so too is <tex>B \otimes _A K</tex>.
    </p>
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5242</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.9.4</addr><route>sga1-i.9.4.xml</route>     <number>I.9.4</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>f \colon  A \to  B</tex> be an étale local homomorphism, with <tex>A</tex> analytically reduced (i.e. such that the completion <tex>\widehat {A}</tex> of <tex>A</tex> has no nilpotent elements).
    Then <tex>B</tex> is analytically reduced, and a fortiori reduced.
  </p>
  
    
    <tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="false" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5243</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon>        </frontmatter> <mainmatter>
    Indeed, <tex>\widehat {B}</tex> is <em>finite</em> and étale over <tex>\widehat {A}</tex>;
    we can apply <ref addr="sga1-i.9.3" href="sga1-i.9.3.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.9.3"/>.
  </mainmatter> </tree>
  
</mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5244</anchor> <taxon>Theorem</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.9.5</addr><route>sga1-i.9.5.xml</route>     <number>I.9.5</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>f \colon  A \to  B</tex> be a local homomorphism, with <tex>B</tex> isomorphic to the localisation of an <tex>A</tex>-algebra of finite type over <tex>A</tex>.
  </p><p><strong><em>TO-DO: the following list should be i, ii</em></strong></p><ol><li>
      If <tex>f</tex> is étale, then <tex>A</tex> is normal if and only if <tex>B</tex> is normal.
    </li>
    <li>
      If <tex>A</tex> is normal, then <tex>f</tex> is étale if and only if <tex>f</tex> is injective and unramified (and then <tex>B</tex> is normal, by (i)).
    </li></ol></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  We will give two different proofs of (i):
  the first using certain properties of quasi-finite flat morphisms (stated at the start of this section) and without using <ref addr="sga1-i.7.6" href="sga1-i.7.6.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.7.6"/> (and thus the Main Theorem);
  the second proof does the opposite.
  For (ii), it seems like we do indeed need the Main Theorem, no matter what.
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5245</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.9.5.i-proof-1</addr><route>sga1-i.9.5.i-proof-1.xml</route>    <title>First proof</title> <number>I.9.5.i</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    We use the following necessary and sufficient condition for a local Noetherian ring <tex>A</tex> of dimension <tex>\neq0</tex> to be normal.
  </p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5246</anchor>  <addr>sga1-i.9-serres-criterion</addr><route>sga1-i.9-serres-criterion.xml</route>    <title>Serre's criterion</title>   </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p><strong><em>TO-DO: the following list should be i, ii</em></strong></p><ol><li>
        For every rank-<tex>1</tex> prime ideal <tex>\mathfrak {p}</tex> of <tex>A</tex>, <tex>A_ \mathfrak {p}</tex> is normal (or, equivalently, regular);
      </li>
      <li>
        For every rank-<tex>\geq2</tex> prime ideal <tex>\mathfrak {p}</tex> of <tex>A</tex>, the depth of <tex>A_ \mathfrak {p}</tex> is <tex>\geq2</tex>.
        (cf. EGA IV 5.8.6.)</li></ol></mainmatter> </tree><p>
    We assume this criterion here, but it should also appear in the section on flatness.
    Its main advantage is that it does not suppose a priori that <tex>A</tex> is reduced, nor a fortiori that <tex>A</tex> is integral.
    Here, we can already suppose that <tex>\dim  A= \dim  B \neq0</tex>.
  </p><p>
    By the statements at the start of this section, the rank-<tex>1</tex> (resp. rank-<tex>\geq2</tex>) prime ideals <tex>\mathfrak {p}</tex> of <tex>A</tex> are exactly the intersections of <tex>A</tex> with the rank-<tex>1</tex> (resp. rank-<tex>\geq2</tex>) prime ideals <tex>\mathfrak {q}</tex> of <tex>B</tex>.
    Finally, if <tex>\mathfrak {p}</tex> and <tex>\mathfrak {q}</tex> correspond to one another, then <tex>B_ \mathfrak {q}</tex> is étale over <tex>A_ \mathfrak {p}</tex>, and thus of the same depth as <tex>A_ \mathfrak {p}</tex>, and is regular if and only if <tex>A_ \mathfrak {p}</tex> is (by <ref addr="sga1-i.9.1" href="sga1-i.9.1.xml" taxon="Proposition" number="I.9.1"/>).
    Applying <link href="sga1-i.9-serres-criterion.xml" type="local" addr="sga1-i.9-serres-criterion" title="SGA 1: Étale covers and the fundamental group › Étale morphisms › Invariance properties › First proof › Serre's criterion">Serre's criterion</link>, we see that <tex>A</tex> is normal if and only if <tex>B</tex> is.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5247</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.9.5.i-proof-2</addr><route>sga1-i.9.5.i-proof-2.xml</route>    <title>Second proof</title> <number>I.9.5.i</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Suppose that <tex>B</tex> is normal, with field of fractions <tex>L</tex>;
    let <tex>K</tex> be the field of fractions of <tex>A</tex> (and note that <tex>A</tex> is integral, since <tex>B</tex> is integral).
    We have already seen, in the proof of <ref addr="sga1-i.9.3" href="sga1-i.9.3.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.9.3"/>, that <tex>B \otimes _A K</tex> is a finite product of fields;
    since it is contained in <tex>L</tex>, it is a field;
    since it contains <tex>B</tex>, it is equal to <tex>L</tex> itself.
    An element of <tex>K</tex> that is integral over <tex>A</tex> is integral over <tex>B</tex>, and is thus in <tex>B</tex>, since <tex>B</tex> is normal, and thus also in <tex>A</tex>, since <tex>B \cap  K=A</tex> (as follows from the fact that <tex>B</tex> is faithfully flat over <tex>A</tex>).
  </p><p>
    Now suppose that <tex>A</tex> is normal;
    we will prove that <tex>B</tex> is also normal.
    By <ref addr="sga1-i.7.6" href="sga1-i.7.6.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.7.6"/>, we have that <tex>B=B'_ \mathfrak {n}</tex>, where <tex>B'=A[t]/FA[t]</tex> (with <tex>F</tex> and <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex> as in <ref addr="sga1-i.7.6" href="sga1-i.7.6.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.7.6"/>).
    Thus <tex>L=B \otimes _A K</tex> is a localisation of <tex>B' \otimes _A K=K[t]/FK[t]</tex>, and also a product of fields (finite separable extensions of <tex>K</tex>).
    This latter product (<tex>B' \otimes _A K</tex>) is a direct factor of <tex>B'_K</tex> (since each time we localise an Artinian ring (here <tex>B'_K</tex>) with respect to a multiplicatively stable set), and thus corresponds to a decomposition <tex>F=F_1F_2</tex> in <tex>K[t]</tex>, with the generator of <tex>L</tex> corresponding to <tex>t</tex> being annihilated by <tex>F_1</tex>.
    But, <em>since <tex>A</tex> is normal, the <tex>F_i</tex> are in <tex>A[t]</tex></em> (supposing that they are monic).
    Note that <tex>B \to  L=B \otimes _A K</tex> is injective (since <tex>A \to  K</tex> is, since <tex>B</tex> is flat over <tex>A</tex>), and so <tex>F_1(u)=0</tex>, with <tex>u</tex> being the class of <tex>t</tex> in <tex>L</tex>.
    Suppose that <tex>F</tex> were of minimal degree;
    then it would follows that <tex>F_2=1</tex>.
    (N.B. we would have <tex>F'(u)=F'_1(u)F_2(u)+F_1(u)F'_2(u)=F'_1(u)F_2(u)</tex>, since <tex>F_1(u)=0</tex>, whence <tex>F'_1(u) \neq  0</tex> since <tex>F'(u) \neq0</tex>.)
    Thus
    <tex display="block">       L = B \otimes _A K = K[t]/FK[t]     </tex>
    and so <tex>F</tex> is a separable polynomial in <tex>K[T]</tex> (but evidently not necessarily in <tex>A[t]</tex>).
    (N.B. for now, we have only shown, essentially, that we can choose <tex>F</tex> and <tex>\mathfrak {n}</tex> in <ref addr="sga1-i.7.6" href="sga1-i.7.6.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.7.6"/> such that, with the above notation, <tex>B' \to  B'_ \mathfrak {n}=B</tex> is <em>injective</em>;
    for this, we have used the fact that <tex>A</tex> is normal;
    I do not know if this remains true without this normality hypothesis).
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  Now recall the well-known lemma, taken from Serre's lectures last year:
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5248</anchor> <taxon>Lemma</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.9.6</addr><route>sga1-i.9.6.xml</route>     <number>I.9.6</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>K</tex> be a ring, <tex>F \in  K[t]</tex> a separable monic polynomial, <tex>L=K[t]/FK[t]</tex>, and <tex>u</tex> the class of <tex>t</tex> in <tex>L</tex> (so that <tex>F'(u)</tex> is an invertible element of <tex>L</tex>).
    Then
    <tex display="block">        \operatorname {tr} _{L/K} u^i/F'(u) =        \begin {cases}         0 &amp; \text {if }0 \leq  i&lt;n-1 \text {;}        \\ 1 &amp; \text {if }i=n-1        \end {cases}     </tex>
    where <tex>n= \deg  F</tex>.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5249</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.9.7</addr><route>sga1-i.9.7.xml</route>     <number>I.9.7</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    The determinant of the matrix <tex>(u^j \cdot  u^i/F'(u))_{0 \leq  i,j \leq  n-1}</tex> is equal to <tex>(-1)^{n(n-1)/2}</tex>, and thus invertible in every sub-ring <tex>A</tex> of <tex>K</tex>.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5250</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.9.8</addr><route>sga1-i.9.8.xml</route>     <number>I.9.8</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Let <tex>A</tex> be a sub-ring of <tex>K</tex>, <tex>V</tex> the <tex>A</tex>-module generated by the <tex>u^i</tex> (for <tex>0 \leq  i \leq  n-1</tex>), and <tex>V'</tex> the sub-<tex>A</tex>-module of <tex>L</tex> consisting of the <tex>x \in  L</tex> such that <tex>\operatorname {tr} _{L/K}(xy) \in  A</tex> for all <tex>y \in  V</tex> (i.e. for <tex>y</tex> of the form <tex>u^i</tex>, for <tex>0 \leq  i \leq  n-1</tex>).
    Then <tex>V'</tex> is the <tex>A</tex>-module given by the basis <tex>u^i/F'(u)</tex> (for <tex>0 \leq  i \leq  n-1</tex>).
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5251</anchor> <taxon>Corollary</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.9.9</addr><route>sga1-i.9.9.xml</route>     <number>I.9.9</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    Suppose that <tex>K</tex> is the field of fractions of an integral normal ring <tex>A</tex>, with the coefficients of <tex>F</tex> lying in <tex>A</tex>.
    Then, with the notation of <ref addr="sga1-i.9.8" href="sga1-i.9.8.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.9.8"/>, <tex>V'</tex> contains the normal closure <tex>A'</tex> of <tex>A</tex> in <tex>L</tex>, which is thus contained in <tex>A[u]/F'(u)</tex>, and a fortiori in <tex>A[u][F'(u)^{-1}]</tex>.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  We can apply <link href="sga1-i.9.9.xml" type="local" addr="sga1-i.9.9">the above corollary</link> to the situation that we have obtained in the proof: since <tex>F'(u)</tex> is invertible in <tex>B</tex>, and since <tex>B</tex> contains <tex>A[u]</tex>, <tex>B</tex> contains <tex>A'</tex>.
  By the Main Theorem (or by the fact that <tex>B=A[u]_ \mathfrak {n}</tex>), <tex>B</tex> is a localisation of <tex>A'</tex>.
  Since <tex>A'</tex> is normal, so too is <tex>B</tex>.
</p><tree expanded="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" toc="true" numbered="false" root="false"><frontmatter><anchor>5252</anchor> <taxon>Proof</taxon> <addr>sga1-i.9.5.ii-proof</addr><route>sga1-i.9.5.ii-proof.xml</route>     <number>I.9.5.ii</number>  </frontmatter> <mainmatter><p>
    We proceed as in the above proof to show that we can choose <tex>F</tex> in <ref addr="sga1-i.7.6" href="sga1-i.7.6.xml" taxon="Theorem" number="I.7.6"/> such that we again have
    <tex display="block">       L = B \otimes _A K = K[t]/FK[t]     </tex>
    The only obstacle a priori is that we can no longer prove that <tex>B \to  L</tex> is injective, since <tex>B</tex> is no longer assumed to be flat over <tex>A</tex>, and so we can only apply the same argument a priori to the image <tex>B_1</tex> of <tex>B</tex> under the aforementioned homomorphism.
    It immediately follows that <tex>B_1</tex> is flat over <tex>A</tex> (since it is the localisation of a free <tex>A</tex>-algebra).
    By <ref addr="sga1-i.4.8" href="sga1-i.4.8.xml" taxon="Corollary" number="I.4.8"/>, the morphism <tex>B \to  B_1</tex> is étale, and thus an isomorphism, which finishes the proof.
  </p></mainmatter> </tree><p>
  (From an editorial point of view, we should perform the two proofs above, and place the formal calculations of the lemma and of its corollaries in a separate section).
</p></mainmatter> </tree></mainmatter> </tree></backlinks> <references/></backmatter></tree>